<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document><page number="1"><paragraph>Received: December 15, 2018; Accepted: September 30, 2019 
♦Corresponding Author: 
 
Isaac Rahimian Boogar, PhD   
Department 
of 
Clinical 
Psychology, 
Faculty 
of 
Psychology and Educational 
Sciences, Semnan University, 
Semnan, Iran     
Tel: +98 23 33623300 
Fax: +98 23 33626888 
Email: i_rahimian@semnan.ac.ir 
Original Article 
Middle East Journal of Cancer; April 2020; 11(2): 216-224
The Effectiveness of Mindfulness-based 
Stress Reduction on Fear of Cancer 
Recurrence in Colorectal and Breast 
Cancer Patients: A Randomized 
Controlled Trial 
  
Nasrin Ahmadiqaragezlou*, Isaac Rahimian Boogar**♦, Javanshir Asadi*, 
Reza Vojdani*** 
  
*Department of Psychology, Gorgan Branch, Islamic Azad University, Gorgan, Iran 
**Department of Clinical Psychology, Faculty of Psychology and Educational Sciences, 
Semnan University, Semnan, Iran 
***Department of Internal Medicine, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran 
          
 
Abstract 
Background: Strong fear of cancer recurrence is frequently reported among the 
cancer survivors. Such influential and universal fear is one of the factors that cause 
considerable emotional distress, anxiety, and decreasing quality of life among such 
patients. Given the importance of the subject, it is necessary to select psychological 
interventions in which the efficiency and feasibility have been proved in different 
trials. The present study aims to determine the efficacy of mindfulness-based stress 
reduction on fear of cancer recurrence in patients with colorectal and breast cancer. 
Methods: The current study is a randomized clinical trial with experiment and 
control groups. We selected 38 patients with breast and colorectal cancer who referred 
to Shahid Motahari Clinic and Amir Oncology Hospital in Shiraz (96-97), then 
randomly assigned them to intervention and control groups. They filled out questionnaires 
in the pre-test and post-test. The data were analyzed by multivariate statistical test 
with SPSS v. 23 software. 
Results: Findings show that the post-test mean scores in the fear of cancer inventory 
have decreased in the intervention group and there was a significant difference between 
experimental and control groups in the components of fear of cancer inventory as 
follows: triggers (F=55.289, P&lt;0.0001), severity (F= 75.785, P&lt;0.0001), psychological 
distress (F=24.078, P&lt;0.0001), dysfunction (F=62/025, P&lt;0.0001), coping strategies 
(F=15.592, P&lt;0.0001), reassurance (F= 6.235, P&lt;0.017), and except insight (F= 
1.396, P&lt;0.245). 
Conclusion: The results from this study showed that MBSR is an efficacious intervention 
to reduce fear of cancer recurrence in patients with breast and colorectal cancer.  
 
Keywords: Mindfulness-based stress reduction, Fear of cancer recurrence, Breast 
cancer, Colorectal cancer</paragraph></page><page number="2"><paragraph>Mindfulness-based Stress Reduction in Colorectal and Breast Cancer Patients 
Middle East J Cancer 2020; 11(2): 216-224
217
Introduction 
Developments in the early detection and 
treatment of cancer have led to the improvement 
of cancer survival rates. However, one of the 
most common concerns among cancer patients 
is fear of cancer recurrence (FCR). FCR is defined 
as a fear or concern about the return or progression 
of the disease in the same organ or other parts of 
the body.1 According to studies, 22% to 87% of  
patients with cancer experience moderate to strong 
FCR throughout survivorship. Those who have 
high level of FCR can experience negative 
behavioral changes including personal 
examination behaviors, avoidance behavior, 
increased use of health services, inability to plan 
for the future, and psychological distress including 
depression and anxiety.2-10 FCR is often 
considered as a multidimensional phenomenon 
with the emotional components and cognitive 
dimensions, including fear, anxiety, mental 
preoccupation, and disturbing thoughts.11 Physical 
symptoms, perceived risk, psychological 
disturbances, loss of quality of life, and functional 
impairment are of underlying factors in FCR. 
While a normal level of FCR can hinder a person’s 
awareness of symptoms, the high levels can 
negatively affect the quality of life and social 
activities of the individuals.12-20 Because FCR is 
one of the sources of significant emotional 
disturbances among the survivors of cancer, it is 
a logical and relevant goal for clinical 
interventions.21, 22  
Mindfulness is defined as a moment to moment 
awareness in being present and the attitude of 
non-judgmentally, non-reactively, openheartedly, 
and acceptance. Training of mindfulness-based 
stress reduction (MBSR) is an 8-week group 
training program. In 1979, John Kabat Zein 
applied mindfulness to treat patients with chronic 
pain and showed how changing the way patients 
relate to their pain can alter their experience of 
pain.23, 24 Recent efforts have identified three 
specific components of mindfulness: 1) the 
intention that involves motivation and knowing 
why they are paying attention 2) attention, which 
directly knows what is happening, 3) attitudes 
that address attention through admission, 
preservation of the properties of the mindfulness, 
or attention with kindness. For cancer survivors, 
the meditation and training approach in the context 
of the mindfulness cognitive process facilitates 
self- regulation of emotions during distress and 
suffering. This training emphasizes the moment 
to moment, non-judgmental, and non-reactive 
attitude to internal and external experiences which 
reduce mental rumination and employment with 
unpleasant experiences.25 Mindfulness-based 
interventions are simple as they do not need any 
specific equipment, whether at home or outside, 
and can be practiced anywhere. Similarly, stress 
reduction through long-term meditation practice 
can be especially helpful for the prevention of 
cancer.26-34 Sarizadeh et al., in a randomized 
clinical trial, showed the efficacy of acceptance 
and commitment therapy on FCR and post-
traumatic growth in breast cancer patients.35 In a 
randomized clinical trial, Lengacher et al. showed 
that MBSR has favorable effects on reducing 
FCR in intervention group compared to the control 
group.36 Riech et al. examined the effectiveness 
of MBSR on cancer patients. Their results 
indicated improvement especially in both clusters 
of psychological symptoms and fatigue compared 
to baseline as well as sustained recovery after 12 
weeks of follow-up. However, the follow-up study 
did not show any improvement compared to post-
test.37 Similarly, Lengacher et al., in their study 
on breast cancer patients, demonstrated that the 
group which received MBSR intervention showed 
a greater reduction in FCR than control.38 In 
another study, Chambers et al. showed the only 
tendency to reduce FCR as a result of participating 
in MBSR course among the 19 survivors of 
prostate cancer.39 Given the significant 
disturbances caused by FCR and a few studies 
conducted to determine the usefulness of 
psychological interventions to reduce this 
pervasive fear, the current research poses an 
important question: Is MBSR effective to reduce 
FCR in the breast and colorectal cancer patients 
who live in Iran?</paragraph></page><page number="3"><paragraph>Nasrin Ahmadiqaragezlou et al.
Middle East J Cancer 2020; 11(2): 216-224
218
Methods and Materials 
The present study is a randomized controlled 
trial (IRCT20180331039163N1) with control and 
experimental groups, approved by the Ethics 
Committee of Research in Shiraz University of 
Medical Sciences (IR.SUMS.REC.1396.192). 
The statistical population of the present study 
included all patients with colorectal and breast 
cancer in Shiraz in 2017. To determine the sample 
size based on a prevalence of 22% FCR among 
patients with cancer, a sample size of 30 people 
was obtained from the Cochran formula, 8 of 
whom were added to the sample to prevent the 
loss. They were randomly assigned to either 
experimental (19) or control (19) groups by using 
the table of random numbers. The CONSORT 
diagram is shown in figure 1. Through interviews 
with patients, the entry criteria would be evaluated 
and included in the study, if eligible. The criteria 
to enter this study included receiving a diagnosis 
Figure 1. CONSORT Diagram. People declined to participate due to transportation issues, not interested, family obligations, and health 
issues.</paragraph></page><page number="4"><paragraph>Mindfulness-based Stress Reduction in Colorectal and Breast Cancer Patients 
Middle East J Cancer 2020; 11(2): 216-224
219
of colorectal and breast cancer approved by an 
oncologist, patients who have completed treatment 
or were still receiving treatment, aged over 18 
years. The excluded patients included those who 
were absent for more than two sessions, attended 
yoga classes and meditated before the study, had 
hearing and speaking problems, participated in 
mindfulness-based stress reduction intervention, 
received psychotherapy or psychiatrist, and 
participated in other psychosocial programs. 
 
 
Table 1. The content of the therapeutic sessions 
Sessions
Session content 
Session 1
This session includes a review of MBSR approach and creating a therapeutic commitment and motivation 
in patients. The patients experientially practice the mindful eating. The session continues with group 
discussion and then the body scan meditation is done. Homework is assigned by using the body scan 
meditation recorded audio file to become aware of the body. Informal practice involves eating at least 
one meal mindfully. Experiential mindfulness training and cultivation of mindful awareness, body 
scan meditation, 30 minute focused conversation about patient's experience of body scan, and reflection 
on home practice. Standing yoga. Home practice is assigned with an emphasis on the regular daily 
practice of the body scan for a second week, as well as, introduction of short periods of sitting meditation, 
and asking the patients to bring mindfulness into their daily life. 
 
Session 2
Patients practiced several distinct but interrelated formal mindfulness practices –mindfulness hatha 
yoga (ending with a brief body scan), sitting meditation and walking meditation which extended formal 
practices by query into and exploration of participant's experiences with in-class and assigned homework. 
Focused dialogue about challenges and insights at the time of formal practice and integrating 
mindfulness into daily life. 
 
Session 3
Patients practice a combination of the three major formal mindfulness practices that they have also 
been doing at home within the preceding three weeks. Directions emphasize on the cultivation of 
concentration, embodiment, the capability to teach and re-direct attention, and the systematic development 
of the realm of awareness. 
 
Session 4
This session indicates the halfway point of the program underscoring the ability of patients to adapt 
more quickly and effectively to daily challenges and stressors. Experiential skills of mindfulness 
proceeds with an emphasis on responding instead of reacting to stressors and the value and efficiency 
of mindfulness in learning to stop, step back and observe more distinctly/objectively and then to be in 
a better position to make informed choices (responding) in facing various situations. 
 
Session 5
Experiential training in MBSR continues with an emphasis on the growing ability to self-manage and 
copes more effectively with stress. Discussion is oriented about the ongoing cultivation of "transforma
tional coping strategies": Awareness, ideas, and behaviors that improve the psychological characteristic 
known as "stress hardiness" or resilience.  
 
Session 6
Empirical training continues in mindfulness. Participants are asked to practice more expansive personal 
experiences instead of formal mindfulness practices done as homework during the week leading up to 
the eighth session. Emphasis is on 45 minutes of daily practice, without recorded instructions.  
 
Session 7
Experiential mindfulness practice continues and patients are given sufficient opportunities to inquire 
into and clear any remaining questions about the different practices and their applications in daily life. 
 
Session 8
Opportunities to inquire into and clear any remaining questions about the different practices and their 
applications in daily life. A review of the course is involved with an emphasis on daily strategies for 
maintaining and amplifying the skills achieved during the program. Time is also allocated for a satisfying 
closure by admiring both the end of this course and starting living one's life enlightened with 
mindfulness.</paragraph></page><page number="5"><paragraph>Nasrin Ahmadiqaragezlou et al.
Measurement 
Demographic information questionnaire: This 
questionnaire contains demographic information 
such as gender, age, marital status, education, 
and duration of illness that was prepared by 
researchers. 
FCR Inventory: Simard and Savard, empirically 
prepared the questionnaire to provide a multidi-
mensional self- report scale to assess fear of 
cancer recurrence.40 The questionnaire had 42 
items that evaluated seven aspects related to FCR 
encompassing triggers (potential triggers that 
activate fear of cancer recurrence), severity (the 
presence and severity of intrusive thoughts 
associated with FCR), psychological disturbance 
(emotional dysfunction associated with FCR), 
functional impairment (the effect of FCR on 
functional areas), insight (self- blaming against 
the intensity of FCR), reassurance (reassurance 
through examination, recurring medical 
counseling), and coping strategies (strategies to 
address FCR). Each item of this questionnaire 
was ranked on a Likert scale between Zero (at 
all or never) to four (very or always). The overall 
score could be obtained for each subscale which 
was done to get the overall scores by aggregating 
item rankings and higher scores indicate more 
fear of cancer recurrence. The original version 
of the French report has a high internal consistency 
scale (0.75) and a test-retest reliability (0.85).  
 
Intervention Protocol 
After randomly assigning eligible patients to 
the experimental and control groups, both groups 
were asked to complete demographic information 
and FCR questionnaires. After collecting 
questionnaires, the participants of the experimental 
group participated in the two-hour weekly 
mindfulness-based stress reduction program which 
was held at the Faculty of Rehabilitation, Shiraz 
University of Medical Sciences and the control 
group did not receive intervention. At the end of 
the program, both groups were asked to respond 
to FCR questionnaire. This research was done 
with ethical considerations including obtaining 
informed written consent, confidentiality of their 
information, and using a suitable place for 
intervention group. In addition, the used tools 
did not have any side-effect for the participants. 
The summary of the content of the therapeutic 
sessions is presented in table 1. 
 
Results 
The result of demographic information was 
shown in the table 2. After examining the 
preconditions of the multivariate covariance test, 
this test was used to examine the differences 
between the two groups in FCR variable. 
Kolmogrov -Smirnov test showed that the data 
was normal. One of the important preconditions 
of the analysis of covariance was the homogeneity 
of covariance matrices. The result of the Mbox 
test (P&lt;0.0001) showed that this precondition 
was not provided. Therefore, the Lambda-wilkes 
was used (F= 16.525, P&lt;0.0001).  Leven test was 
used to measure the error variance equation in 
different stages including (F= 0.889, P= 0.352), 
Middle East J Cancer 2020; 11(2): 216-224
220
Table 2. Demographics and participants’ characteristics 
Gender
 
Female
30 
Male
8 
 
Mean age ±SD (years)
 
Intervention
44.4 ± 0.7 
Control
48.4 ± 9.7 
 
Cancer type
 
Colorectal
16 
Breast
22 
 
Marital status
 
Single
4 
Married
34 
 
Education
 
Below high school
4 
High school
13 
B.A
19 
Ph.D.
2 
 
Job status
 
Unemployed
20 
Full time job
8 
Part time Job
4 
Retired
6 
Duration of disease (months)   20.5 – 120 ± 25.2</paragraph></page><page number="6"><paragraph>Mindfulness-based Stress Reduction in Colorectal and Breast Cancer Patients 
in the post-test component of insight, (F=1.019, 
P=0.319) in the post-test component of 
psychological distress, (F=3.611, P=0.065) in the 
post-test component of triggers, (F=2.569, 
P=0.118) in post-test component of severity, 
(F=3.722, P=0.062) in the post-test component 
of reassurance it was determined that the variance 
of the error of the various components of the test, 
except for the dysfunction component (F=4.638, 
P=0.038), and coping strategies (F=9.616, 
P=0.004) is similar in the post-test. Regarding 
the obtained significant level (P=0.59), we 
conclude that there is no interaction and regression 
lines that do not interrupt each other and their 
slope is homogeneous. Therefore, multivariate 
covariance analysis was used with regard to 
adherence to the preconditions. In table 3, values 
related to the test of effects of between the subjects 
are reflected. 
Based on the results of the table 4, there was 
a significant difference between the experimental 
and control groups in the all subscales of FCR 
inventory in the post-test, just insight (P=0.245). 
And MBSR had the greatest effect on the trigger 
and dysfunction. As table 5 shows, there is a 
significant difference (P=0.001), between the two 
groups in the post-test. 
 
Discussion 
According to the results, participating in this 
course had a favorable effect on all subscales of 
FCR and led to reduction of FCR in these patients. 
Findings from several studies illustrated the 
effectiveness of MBSR on FCR.33,35-37 Although 
the scales used to measure FCR were different 
in these studies, the results have shown the 
effectiveness of MBSR on FCR reduction 
improving other symptoms associated with cancer 
and its treatment such as cognitive impairment, 
fatigue, stress, and anxiety. According to the 
patient reports, physical symptoms are the most 
stressful triggers that evoke FCR, while negative 
thoughts, emotions, and reappraisals about cancer 
recurrence or progression may unconsciously 
continue and affect the psychological and physical 
well-being of the patients. Hall et al. showed that 
concerns about recurrence or progression of cancer 
are the underlying cause of stress for the survivors 
of cancer and they suggest that teaching strategies 
can help these patients in order to manage the 
Middle East J Cancer 2020; 11(2): 216-224
221
Table 3. The mean and standard deviation of the components of FCR* in experimental and control groups in pre-test and post-test 
Subscale
Group
Pre-test
Post-test 
(mean±standared diviation)
(mean±standared diviation) 
Trigger
Intervention
7.9±0.7
1±0.3 
Control
8.9±1.2
8.2±1.2 
 
Severity
Intervention
16.6±0.9
6±0.6 
Control
16.8±1
15.8±1 
 
Psychological distress
Intervention
6.9±0.5
2.3±0.6 
Control
6.8±0.5
7.6±1 
 
Coping strategies
Intervention
11.6±1
4±0.5 
Control
9.7±1.1
9.4±1.3 
 
Dysfunction 
Intervention
8.1±0.96
1.4±0.22 
Control
6.9±1.3
6.7±0.7 
 
Insight
Intervention
1.7±0.46
0.5±0.2 
Control
1.8±0.62
0.9±0.5 
 
Reassurance
Intervention
5±0.52
2.3±0.6 
Control
4.53±0.5
4±0.4 
*FCR: Fear of cancer recurrence</paragraph></page><page number="7"><paragraph>Nasrin Ahmadiqaragezlou et al.
cancer-related uncertainties and stress deriving 
from physical symptoms.41 To explain the 
effectiveness of mindfulness-based stress reduction 
on FCR, MBSR has a direct impact on antecedents 
causing FCR, such as physical symptoms and 
cancer reminders. It requires more studies to 
examine this issue in different types of cancer 
populations. In other words, mindfulness 
meditation is similar to exposure therapy situation 
because the goals of exposure therapy are to 
prevent the response of fear, instead of gaining a 
sense of security in the presence of previously 
frightening stimuli by confronting those stimuli 
and preventing the respondent from responding 
to the usual way. MBSR participants get this 
capacity to observe their emotional experiences 
and unpleasant thoughts without reacting to 
them.42 The principles of MBSR program are 
based on the mindfulness therapeutic power which 
is utilized through two cognitive processes of 
awareness and attention. Through MBSR program, 
patients learn self-regulation of awareness and 
attention and develop a non-judgmental attitude 
to make a change. Through awareness of cognitive 
process, internal experiences are processed in the 
form of imaginations and emotions. These 
imaginations and emotions are transiently evoked, 
but they continue to be judged by the fact that 
they are pleasant or unpleasant. These reactions 
depend on the past experiences and can be linked 
with a memorable one and they are easily absorbed 
in other schemas. In the context of processing 
attention, there is a step back in which feelings 
and thoughts are perceived objectively as they 
appear which is observed through the record of 
raw facts. Generally, they are taught to be present 
in reality rather than to react to reality or to rumble 
on past emotional experiences.23 The limitations 
of the present study are small sample size; cases 
in both groups were not matched for age, sex, 
and level of education; a small number of male 
participants who make it impossible to analyze 
gender-related data in this study; and the variety 
of the stages of the disease. The lack of follow-
up has the difficulty of estimating the duration 
of the intervention effectiveness. It is suggested 
that future studies should be done with a large 
number of individuals and also considering the 
gender differences in the level of FCR and other 
related factors from both men and women in 
equal numbers, as well as other necessary recon-
ciliations as much as possible to obtain reliable 
results for matching interventions. It is difficult 
to determine the effectiveness of MBSR on 
different stages of cancer which is recommended 
to be considered in future studies. Also, in order 
to assess the duration of effectiveness of MBSR, 
the follow-up studies were recommended. The 
strength of this study is showing that MBSR is a 
feasible and acceptable intervention for colorectal 
and breast cancer patients in any stage of disease 
and treatment who live in Iran. Given the efficacy 
of MBSR, it is suggested to consider this 
intervention as a complementary therapy to reduce 
the psychological disturbances and disorders that 
result from FCR and interfere with daily 
functioning and also lead to reduced quality of 
life of the patients with cancer. 
 
Acknowledgments 
This research was carried out with the 
participation and collaboration of outpatients with 
breast and colorectal cancers, who were referred 
to Shahid Motahari Clinic and Amir Oncology 
Middle East J Cancer 2020; 11(2): 216-224
222
Table 4. Multivariate covariance analysis of FCR* with control of the effect of pre-test. 
source
Dependent variable
df.    Sum of squares
   F.       Sig. squared.      Partial Eta power 
Observed 
Group
Trigger
1
528.51
55.28
0.000
0.61
1.00 
Severity
1
946.71
75.78
0.000
1.00
Psychological distress
1
285.36
24.07
0.000
0.40
0.998 
Coping strategies
1
277.93
15.59
0.000
0.30
0.97 
Dysfunction
1
277.98
62.02
0.000
0.63
1.00 
Insight
1
3.36
1.39
0.245
0.03
0.21 
Reassurance
1
30.36
6.23
0.017
0.15
0.68 
*FCR: Fear of cancer recurrence</paragraph></page><page number="8"><paragraph>Mindfulness-based Stress Reduction in Colorectal and Breast Cancer Patients 
Hospital in Shiraz. We are indebted to the officials 
and staff of these centers as well as the study 
participants. 
 
Conflict of Interest 
None declared. 
   
References 
1.
Maheu C, Lebel S, Courbasson C, Lefebvre M, Singh 
M, Bernstein LJ, et al. Protocol of a randomized 
controlled trial of the fear of recurrence therapy (FORT) 
intervention for women with breast or gynecological 
cancer. BMC Cancer. 2016; 16:291. doi: 
10.1186/s12885-016-2326-x. 
2.
Lebel S, Ozakinci G, Humphris G, Mutsaers B, Thewes 
B, Prins J, et al. From normal response to clinical 
problem: definition and clinical features of fear of 
cancer recurrence. Support Care Cancer. 2016; 24: 
3256-68. 
3.
Shay LA, Carpentier MY, Vernon SW. Prevalence and 
correlates of fear of recurrence among adolescent and 
young adult versus older adult post-treatment cancer 
survivors. Support Care Cancer. 2016; 24(11):4689-
96. doi: 10.1007/s00520-016-3317-9.  
4.
Mellon S, Kershaw TS, Northhouse LL, Freeman-
Gibb L. A family-based model to predict fear of 
recurrence for cancer survivors and their caregivers. 
Psychooncology. 2007;16(3):214-23. 
5.
Dunn LB, Langford DJ, Paul SM, Berman MB, 
Shumay DM, Kober K, et al. Trajectories of fear of 
recurrence in women with breast cancer. Support Care 
Cancer. 2014;23(7):2033-43. doi.org/10.1007/s00520-
014-2513-8. 
6.
Dinkel A, Herschbach P. Fear of progression in cancer 
patients and survivors. Recent Results Cancer Res. 
2018; 210: 13-33. 
7.
Crist JV, Grunfeld EA. Factors reported to influence 
fear of recurrence in cancer patients: a systematic 
review. Psychooncology. 2013;22(5):978-86. 
8.
Ozga M, Aghajanian C, Myers-Virtue S, McDonnell 
G, Jhanwar S, Hichenberg S, et al. A systematic review 
of ovarian cancer and fear of recurrence. Palliat 
Support Care. 2015;13(6):1771-80. doi: 10.1017/ 
S1478951515000127. 
9.
Yang Y, Cameron J, Bedi C, Humphris G. FCR 
trajectory during radiation treatment and follow-up 
into survivorship of patients with breast cancer. BMC 
Cancer. 2018;18(1):1002. doi:10.1186/s12885-018-
4908-2 
10. Simard S, Thewes B, Humphris G, Dixon M, Hayden 
C, Mireskandari S, et al. Fear of cancer recurrence in 
adult cancer survivors: a systematic review of 
quantitative studies. J Cancer Surviv. 2013;7(3):300-
22. 
11. Ziner KW, Sledge GW, Bell CJ, Johns S, Miller KD, 
Champion VL. Predicting fear of breast cancer 
recurrence and self-efficacy in survivors by age at 
diagnosis. Oncol Nurs Forum. 2012;39(3):287-95. 
12. Hall DL, Lennes IT, Pirl WF, Friedman ER, Park ER. 
Fear of recurrence or progression as a link between 
somatic symptoms and perceived stress among cancer 
survivors. Support Care Cancer. 2016;25(5):1401-7. 
13. Lichtenthal WG, Corner GW, Slivjak ET, Roberts KE, 
Breitbart W, Lacey S, et al. A pilot randomized 
controlled trial of cognitive bias modification to reduce 
fear of breast cancer recurrence. Cancer. 
2017;123(8):1424-33. 
14. Cohee AA, Adams RN, Johns SA, Von Ah D, Zoppi 
K, Fife B, et al. Long-term fear of recurrence in young 
breast cancer survivors and partners. Psychooncology. 
2015;26(1):22-8. 
15. Jansen L, Koch L, Brenner H, Arndt v. Quality of life 
among long-term (≥5 years) colorectal cancer 
survivors- systematic review. Eur J Cancer. 2010; 
4(16):2879-88  
16. Smith-Gagen J, Cress RD, Drake CM, Romano PS, 
Yost KJ, Ayanian JZ. Quality-of-life and surgical 
treatments for rectal cancer--a longitudinal analysis 
using the California Cancer Registry. Psychooncology. 
2010;19(8):870-8. 
17. Mehnert A, Berg P, Henrich G, Herschbach P. Fear of 
cancer progression and cancer related intrusive 
cognitions in breast cancer patients. Psychooncology. 
2009; 18:1273-80. 
18. Van de Wal M, Servaes P, Berry R, Thewes B, Prins 
J. Cognitive behavior therapy for fear of cancer 
recurrence: a case study. J Clin Psychol Med Settings. 
2018; 25(4): 390-407. 
19. Lebel S, Simard S, Harris C, Feldstain A, Beattie S, 
Mc Callum M, et al. Empirical validation of the English 
version of  fear of cancer recurrence inventory. Qual 
Life Res. 2016; 25(2): 311-21. 
20. Fisher A, Beeken RJ, Heinrich M, Williams K, Wardle 
J. Health behaviours and fear of cancer recurrence in 
10 969 colorectal cancer (CRC) patients. 
Psychooncology. 2016; 25(12): 1434-40. doi: 
10.1002/pon.4076. 
21. Thewes B, Kaal SEJ, Custers JAE, Manten-Horst E, 
Jansen R, Servaes P, et al. Prevalence and correlates 
of high fear of cancer recurrence in late adolescents 
Middle East J Cancer 2020; 11(2): 216-224
223
Table 5. Univariate covariance analysis of FCR by controlling the effect of pre-test scores 
source
df. 
Sum of squares
   F. 
Sig. squared.
Partial Eta squared.     Observed power 
Pre FCR
1
1399.218
17.966
0.0001
0.346
0.984 
FCR: Fear of cancer recurrence</paragraph></page><page number="9"><paragraph>Nasrin Ahmadiqaragezlou et al.
and young adults consulting a specialist adolescent 
and young adult (AYA) cancer service. Support Care 
Cancer. 2017;26(5):1479-87. 
22. Custers JA, Gielissen MF, de Wilt JH, Honkoop A, 
Smilde TJ, Van Spronsen DJ, et al. Towards an 
evidence-based model of FCR for breast cancer 
survivors. J Cancer Surviv. 2016;11(1):41-7. doi: 
10.1007/s11764-016-0558-z. 
23. Kabat - Zinnn J, Lipworth L, Burney R. The clinical 
use of mindfulness meditation for the self - regulation 
of chronic pain. J Behav Med. 1985;8(2):163-90. 
24. Kabat-Zinn J, Massion AO, Kristeller J, Peterson LG, 
Fletcher KE, Pbert L, et al. Effectiveness of a 
meditation-based stress reduction program in the 
treatment of anxiety disorders. Am J Psychiatry. 1992; 
149:936-43. 
25. Perlman DM, Salomons TV, Davidson RJ, Lutz A. 
Differential effects on pain intensity and unpleasantness 
of two meditation practices. Emotion. 2010;10(1):65-
71. doi: 10.1037/a0018440. 
26. Nyklícek I, Kuijpers KF. Effects of mindfulness-based 
stress reduction intervention on psychological well-
being and quality of life: is increased mindfulness 
indeed the mechanism? Ann Behav Med. 
2008;35(3):331-40. doi:10.1007/s12160-008-9030-2.  
27. Hawley ST, Janz NK, Griffith KA, Jagsi R, Friese 
CR, Kurian AW, et al. Recurrence risk perception and 
quality of life following treatment of breast cancer. 
Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2017;161(3):557-65. doi: 
10.1007/s10549-016-4082-7. 
28. Gotink RA, Chu P, Busschbach JJ, Benson H, 
Fricchione GL, Hunink MG. Standardised mindfulness-
based interventions in healthcare: an overview of 
systematic reviews and meta-analyses of RCTs. PLoS 
One. 2015;10(4):e0124344. doi: 10.1371/journal. 
pone.0124344. 
Retraction 
in: PLoS 
One. 
2019;14(4):e0215608. 
29. Pouy S, Attari Peikani F, Nourmohammadi H, Sanei 
P, Tarjoman A, Borji M. Investigating the effect of 
mindfulness-based training on psychological status 
and quality of life in patients with breast cancer. Asian 
Pac 
J 
Cancer 
Prev. 
2018;19(7):1993-8. 
doi:10.22034/APJCP.2018.19.7.1993. 
30. Huang J, Shi L. The effectiveness of mindfulness-
based stress reduction (MBSR) for survivors of breast 
cancer: study protocol for a randomized controlled 
trial. Trials. 2016;17(1):209. doi: 10.1186/s13063-
016-1335-z. 
31. Ledesma D, Kumano H. Mindfulness-based stress 
reduction and cancer: a meta-analysis. Psychooncology. 
2009; 18(6):571-9. 
32. Matousek RH, Dobkin PL. Weathering storms: a cohort 
study of how participation in a mindfulness-based 
stress reduction program benefits women after breast 
cancer treatment. Curr Oncol. 2010; 17(4):62-70. 
33. Rouleau CR, Garland SN, Carlson LE. The impact of 
mindfulness-based interventions on symptom burden, 
positive psychological outcomes, and biomarkers  in 
cancer patients. Cancer Manag Res. 2015;7:121-31. 
doi:10.2147/CMAR.S64165. 
34. Saxe GA, Hebert JR, Carmody JF, Kabat-Zinn J, 
Rosenzweig PH, Jarzobski D, et al. Can diet in 
conjunction with stress reduction affect the rate of 
increase in prostate specific antigen after biochemical 
recurrence of prostate cancer? J Urol. 2001; 166(6): 
2202-7.  
35. Sarizadeh MS, Mozaffari S, Rahimian Boogar I. 
Effectiveness of acceptance and commitment therapy 
on fear of cancer recurrence and post-traumatic growth 
among patients with breast cancer.[In Persian] 
Koomesh. 2018; 20(4):626-32. 
36. Lengacher CA, Shelton MM, Reich RR, Barta MK, 
Johnson-Mallard V, Moscoso MS, et al. Mindfulness 
based stress reduction (MBSR(BC)) in breast cancer: 
evaluating fear of recurrence (FOR) as a mediator of 
psychological and physical symptoms in a randomized 
control trial (RCT). J Behav Med. 2014;37(2):185-
95. doi: 10.1007/s10865-012-9473-6. 
37. Reich RR, Lengacher CA, Alinat CB, Kip KE, Paterson 
C, Ramesar S, et al. Mindfulness-based stress reduction 
in post-treatment breast cancer patients: immediate 
and sustained effects across multiple symptom clusters. 
J Pain Symptom Manage. 2017; 53(1): 85-95. 
38. Lengacher CA, Johnson-Mallard V, Post-White J, 
Moscoso MS, Jacobsen PB, Klein TW, et al. 
Randomized controlled trial of mindfulness-based 
stress reduction (MBSR) for survivors of breast cancer. 
Psychooncology. 2009; 18(12):1261-72. 
39. Chambers SK, Smith DP, Berry M, Lepore  SJ, Foley 
E, Clutton S, et al. A randomised controlled trial of a 
mindfulness intervention for men with advanced 
prostate cancer. BMC Cancer. 2013;13:89. 
doi:10.1186/1471-2407-13-89.  
40. Simard S, Savard J. Fear of cancer recurrence 
inventory: development and initial validation of a 
multidimensional measure of fear of cancer recurrence. 
Support Care Cancer. 2009; 17(3): 241-51 
41. Hall DL, Lennes IT, Pirl WF, Friedman ER, Park ER. 
Fear of recurrence or progression as a link between 
somatic symptoms and perceived stress among cancer 
survivors. Support Care Cancer. 2016;25(5):1401-7. 
42. Tang YY, Holzel BK, Posner MI. The neuroscience 
of mindfulness meditation. Nat Rew Neurosci. 2015; 
16(4): 213-25. 
Middle East J Cancer 2020; 11(2): 216-224
224</paragraph></page></document>