<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document><page number="1"><paragraph>European Journal of Oncology Nursing 61 (2022) 102219
Available online 5 October 2022
1462-3889/© 2022 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.
Mindfulness-based stress reduction with acupressure for sleep quality in 
breast cancer patients with insomnia undergoing chemotherapy: A 
randomized controlled trial 
Qixi Liu a,b,1, Chunfeng Wang a,1, Ying Wang a, Wenkui Xu a, Chenju Zhan b, Jinqing Wu b, 
Rong Hu a,* 
a The School of Nursing, Fujian Medical University, No. 1 of Xueyuan Road, Shangjie Town, Minhou County, Fuzhou City, Fujian Province, China 
b Mindong Hospital Affiliated to Fujian Medical University, No.89 of Heshan Road, Fu’an City, Fujian Province, China   
A R T I C L E  I N F O   
Keywords: 
Breast cancer 
Fatigue 
Sleep disorders 
Acupressure 
Mindfulness-based stress reduction 
A B S T R A C T   
Purpose: The objective of this randomized controlled trial was to evaluate and compare the effectiveness of 
mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR), acupressure, and MBSR combined with acupressure in improving 
sleep quality in breast cancer patients with sleep disorders, as well as the potential effects of these interventions 
on relieving fatigue, anxiety, and depression. 
Methods: A four-arm parallel-group randomized controlled trial was conducted in a tertiary hospital in Fujian 
between July 2019 and January 2021. A total of 147 breast cancer patients were randomly assigned to a usual 
care group (n = 34), a MBSR group (n = 38), an acupressure group (n = 36), or a combined group (n = 39). We 
assessed patients’ sleep quality (Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index-PSQI and 6 actigraphy indices), fatigue, anxiety, 
and depression at baseline and at the mid-intervention (fourth week) and the end of intervention (eighth week). 
Results: The ANOVA showed a significant difference (p &lt; 0.05) in PSQI, and all sleep parameters measured by 
wrist actigraphy, and anxiety between groups. The three active treatments led to better PSQI outcomes (p &lt;
0.001), reduced fatigue (p &lt; 0.001), decreased anxiety (p &lt; 0.05), and improved sleep measured by all actig-
raphy indices with two exceptions (MBSR did not differ from control on Sleep Latency (p = 0.235) and mean 
waking by time (MWBT) (p = 0.058)). Both acupressure and the combined intervention outperformed MBSR on 
four actigraphy indices: Sleep Efficiency (SE), Sleep Latency (SL), Totatl Sleep Time (TST), and Wake after sleep 
onset (WASO) (p &lt; 0.05), and the combined intervention further outperformed MBSR on PSQI (p = 0.03) and 
Number of awakings (NOA) (p = 0.003). Moreover, there was no significant difference across all outcomes 
between acupressure and combined intervention (p ≥ 0.05). 
Conclusions: MBSR, acupressure, and combined therapy all show a remarkable advantages in allemiating sleep 
quality, fatigue, and anxiety. Acupressure and combined therapy outperformed MBSR in improving sleep quality.   
1. Introduction 
Global Cancer Statistics 2020 showed that female breast cancer has 
surpassed lung cancer as the most commonly diagnosed cancer with an 
estimated 2.3 million new cases (11.7%) (Sung et al., 2021). While ad-
vancements in early detection and treatment have increased breast 
cancer survival rates, the outlook for the physical and psychosocial 
health of breast cancer patients is still not optimistic (Guimond et al., 
2020; Maass et al., 2020). Approximately 14%–93% of breast cancer 
patients experience sleep problems (Leysen et al., 2019). Long-term 
sleep disturbances may potentiate the vulnerability of immune alter-
ations caused by chemotherapy and increase susceptibility to infections 
during cancer care (Ruel et al., 2020). In addition, chemotherapy may 
cause a series of side effects and further impair patients’ sleep quality 
(Ratcliff et al., 2021). Cancer-related fatigue is another burdensome and 
long-lasting symptom among breast cancer patients, affecting up to 72% 
during treatment, and it may remain a continuous burden even after 
treatment completion (Puigpinos-Riera et al., 2020). Meanwhile, the 
* Corresponding author. The School of Nursing, Fujian Medical University, Fuzhou City, Fujian Province, China. 
E-mail address: ronghu1246@fjmu.edu.cn (R. Hu).   
1 Qixi Liu and Chunfeng Wang contributed to this work equally and are co-first authors. 
Contents lists available at ScienceDirect 
European Journal of Oncology Nursing 
journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/ejon 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejon.2022.102219 
Received 14 April 2022; Received in revised form 29 August 2022; Accepted 30 September 2022</paragraph></page><page number="2"><paragraph>European Journal of Oncology Nursing 61 (2022) 102219
2
majority of breast cancer patients are reported to experience varying 
degrees of depression and anxiety during chemotherapy treatment (Hajj 
et al., 2021; Liu et al., 2021; Pilevarzadeh et al., 2019). 
Several interventions have been conducted to alleviate the physical 
or psychological symptoms experienced by breast cancer patients un-
dergoing chemotherapy (Abrahams et al., 2020; Vallance et al., 2020; 
VanderWalde et al., 2021). Mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) 
is an eight-week program originally developed by Professor Jon 
Kabat-Zinn and characterized by learning to concentrate on the present 
moment with openness, curiosity, and acceptance (Gu et al., 2015). 
There are three main formal practical exercises: body scan (mindful 
body perception), gentle yoga, and traditional sitting meditation (Witek 
Janusek, Tell and Mathews, 2019). MBSR is widely practiced across 
varied populations, including in the field of breast and lung cancer to 
help relieve patients’ subjective stress, pain, fatigue, and psychological 
symptoms including anxiety, depression, and fear of recurrence (Tian 
et al., 2021; Zhang et al, 2019). In 2019, a review of MBSR for women 
diagnosed with breast cancer systematically analyzed published ran-
domized clinical trials and found that MBSR can slightly alleviate fatigue 
(SMD -0.50, 95% CI -0.86 to −0.14), anxiety (SMD -0.29, 95% CI -0.50 
to −0.08), moderately reduce depression (SMD -0.54, 95% CI -0.86 to 
−0.22), and slightly improve sleep quality (SMD -0.38, 95% CI -0.79 to 
0.04) in the short term (Schell et al., 2019). Relevant studies conducted 
in Chinese breast cancer patients have demonstrated that MBSR can 
improve female sexual function and mental health (Chang et al., 2022) 
and posttraumatic growth (Zhang et al., 2017), and reduce psycholog-
ical symptoms (Kang et al., 2021). 
Acupressure, a method derived from traditional Chinese medicine, is 
a treatment in which pressure is applied with fingers, thumbs, or a de-
vice on the body’s acupoints. Although the mechanism of acupoint 
stimulation is unclear, there is sufficient evidence that acupoint stimu-
lation can play a significant role in medical treatment. Acupressure is 
well-received because it is noninvasive, safe, and convenient compared 
with acupuncture (Ge et al., 2022), and it has shown promise as a 
treatment for chemotherapy-induced nausea, vomiting, and anxiety in 
patients with breast cancer (Tan et al., 2020). Several studies have 
demonstrated the positive effects of acupressure on improving sleep 
quality in breast cancer patients (Nourizadeh et al., 2022; Yoon and 
Park, 2019). Moreover, a pilot randomized sham-controlled trial indi-
cated that self-acupressure is feasible for managing the symptom cluster 
of insomnia, depression, and anxiety in cancer patients undergoing 
chemotherapy 
and 
suggested 
the 
potential 
effectiveness 
of 
self-acupressure in improving the targeted symptom cluster (Hoang 
et al., 2022). In addition, acupressure is also used to improve sleep 
quality in other various populations such as menopausal women (Abe-
dian et al., 2015), psychogeriatric inpatients (Lu et al., 2013), and he-
modialysis patients (Arab et al., 2016). Moreover, acupressure has been 
demonstrated to decrease cancer-related fatigue in different cancer pa-
tients (Khanghah et al., 2019; L. Lin et al., 2021). A community-based 
randomized controlled trial showed that self-acupressure was also 
beneficial for reducing cancer-related fatigue in ovarian cancer survi-
vors (Zick et al., 2021). Furthermore, a recent systematic review and 
meta-analysis including 14 RCTs demonstrated that acupressure is 
effective in reducing depression and anxiety in various populations (J. 
Lin et al., 2022). Another systematic review also indicated that 
acupressure significantly reduced patients’ anxiety (Chen et al, 2022a, 
2022b). 
Although there is relatively abundant evidence indicating that MBSR 
and acupressure both show a positive effect on ameliorating sleep 
quality, fatigue, anxiety, and depression in cancer patients, we hy-
pothesize that MBSR combined with acupressure may have stronger 
positive effects on improving sleep quality, and potentially relieving 
fatigue, anxiety, and depression compared to MBSR, acupressure, and 
routine care. Therefore, the primary objective of this randomized 
controlled trial was to evaluate and compare the effectiveness of MBSR, 
acupressure, and MBSR combined with acupressure, and routine care in 
improving sleep quality in breast cancer patients with sleep disorders. 
The secondary purpose is to evaluate and compare the potential effects 
of these interventions on relieving fatigue, anxiety, and depression. 
2. Methods 
2.1. Study design 
This study was designed as a four-arm parallel group randomized 
controlled trial and has been registered in the Chinese Clinical Trial 
Registry with the number “ChiCTR190002561.” We followed the 
Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT 2010). 
2.2. Setting and participants 
The participants were recruited from Mindong Hospital Affiliated to 
Fujian Medical University between July 2019 and January 2021. The 
inclusion criteria for patients were as follows: (1) inpatients diagnosed 
with breast cancer; (2) undergoing chemotherapy; (3) aged 18 years or 
older; (4) informed of disease diagnosis and treatment; (5) the total 
score of Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) &gt; 7 and sleep efficiency 
according to the wrist actigraphy index of &lt;85% simultaneously; and (6) 
understanding and speaking Chinese. The exclusion criteria for patients 
were as follows: (1) breast cancer combined with serious organ 
dysfunction diseases, nervous system diseases, and others; (2) receiving 
endocrine therapy; (3) taking sleeping pills, antidepressants, and other 
drugs that might affect observation outcomes; (4) cognitive impairment 
(comprehension or expression problems); and (5) received psychother-
apy or exercise therapy within the last three months. 
2.3. Sample size calculation 
The sample size was calculated using PASS 15.0 statistical software 
under the repeat measurement analysis module (Muller and Barton, 
1989). In this study, sleep quality (PSQI) was recognized as the primary 
outcome. The sample size was determined according to the results of our 
preliminary study with 35 subjects divided into four groups (control, 
MBSR, acupressure and combined group). Assuming a power of 0.8 with 
an alpha of 0.05, 24 participants were needed in each group. With an 
expected attrition rate of 30% (Hoang et al., 2022; Witek Janusek et al., 
2019), each study arm required at least 34 participants. Finally, this 
study recruited 147 participants, which met the requirements of the 
sample size. 
2.4. Randomized allocation 
A random sequence set was generated from the Research Random-
izer Website (https://www.randomizer.org/). The sequence contained 
136 nonrepeating numbers ranging from 1 to 136. The random numbers 
were packaged in sequentially numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes by a 
third party to ensure allocation concealment. After the participants were 
included, we randomly divided them into groups according to the 
numbers in the envelopes with 1–34 as the MBSR, 35–68 as the 
acupressure, and 69–102 as the MBSR with acupressure, and 103–136 as 
the control groups. Afterwards, these steps were repeated for grouping. 
In addition, as the interventionists were not blind to group allocation, 
data collection and analysis were performed by a research assistant and 
a statistician who did not know the group allocation. 
2.5. Intervention 
2.5.1. Training program for interventionists 
One group of six licensed clinical nurses in the breast oncology 
department undertook the responsibilities of performing interventions. 
They were required to attend seven MBSR training sessions (90 min/ 
time) and one examination performed by one senior nurse (the first 
Q. Liu et al.</paragraph></page><page number="3"><paragraph>European Journal of Oncology Nursing 61 (2022) 102219
3
author) who was trained and qualified in MBSR. The MBSR training 
program contains an interpretation of the theoretical basis, skill prac-
tice, MBSR procedure, and practice exercises. The acupressure training 
program, containing two training sessions, was performed by one 
licensed nurse with rich experience in acupressure in the traditional 
Chinese medicine department. The first training session (lasting 4 h) was 
conducted to introduce and explain the location, manipulation, and time 
of acupressure. The second is a practice session (lasting 4 h) for in-
terventionists to feel the manipulation and strength of the acupressure. 
Then, the operation exam was performed to check the mastery of all 
interventionists. The main researcher (the first author) monitored all 
training sessions and checked the MBSR and acupressure mastery of 
interventionists after the training sessions in the MBSR, acupressure, and 
MBSR with acupressure groups. To ensure content equivalency, a Chi-
nese standardized session-by-session video of MBSR and an instruction 
manual of acupressure were used as education and guidance materials, 
and the interventionists were requested to follow these instruction ma-
terials. Notably, each nurse is responsible for the whole-course inter-
vention of the patients she recruited. 
2.5.2. Routine care 
Control patients received routine care in the breast oncology 
department including symptom assessment and management, diet 
guidance, rest and exercise guidance, and usual psychological support. 
2.5.3. MBSR 
Patients randomized to the MBSR group received weekly group 
sessions delivered by the primary interventionist in a large recreational 
area of the breast oncology department. Patients were required to 
perform MBSR practice once daily (lasting 45 min) for eight weeks (each 
session for one week). The weekly group session was led by the main 
researcher (the first author) and one nurse. The participants were 
required to conduct the individual practice on their own (using the 
recording) when they were both inpatient and outpatient, which was 
monitored and guided by one nurse. After discharge, the interventionist 
informed that participants must attempt to practice this daily on time 
and delivered weekly group sessions using WeChat (a popular social 
media application) to address any issues patients encountered during 
the practice. The MBSR program followed in this study contained eight 
sessions including breath awareness, seated mindfulness meditation, 
focusing on one thing, body scanning, compassionate meditation, 
sounds and thoughts, choiceless awareness, and coming full circle. The 
session content of the MBSR program is provided in Appendix 1. During 
hospitalization, the MBSR practice was suggested to be fixed around 10 
a.m. daily to avoid interfering with patients’ mealtimes and breaks. 
Patients were allowed to practice on the ward bed or recreational area if 
they preferred. Each patient was provided a mini speaker box to listen to 
the instructions of each session for daily practice. Meanwhile, daily face- 
to-face discussions were held between interventionists and patients to 
ensure adherence to program content/objectives and to address any is-
sues, and participants were asked to log their daily mindfulness practice. 
Interventionists were asked to check the log daily mindfulness practice 
of the participants. 
2.5.4. Acupressure 
Patients in the acupressure group received a self-administered 
acupressure program. Five acupoints were selected in this study ac-
cording to the recommendations of previous studies and included Yin-
tang, Shenmen, Neiguan, Baihui, and Anmian, which were demonstrated 
to improve patients’ sleep quality (Ge et al., 2022; Yeung et al., 2022). 
The specific locations of acupoints appear in Appendix 2. Participants 
were required to perform acupressure twice daily (each acupoint lasting 
for 6 min at a time) for eight weeks. Since the instructors of interventions 
were registered clinical nurses in the study setting, the intervention time 
was fixed in the daytime to avoid disrupting nurses’ off-duty hours. In 
addition, to ensure the consistency of program implementation, the 
acupressure was suggested to be performed around 10 a.m. and 3 p.m. 
daily to avoid patients’ mealtimes and breaks. Before the formal inter-
vention, the responsible licensed clinical nurses would teach and 
instruct the manipulation and strength of acupressure for patients 
or/and their family caregivers. Patients’ family members could help 
patients perform acupressure if necessary. Daily discussions were held 
between the interventionists and patients or family caregivers to ensure 
the accurate location and appropriate manipulation and strength. The 
correctness of acupressure was confirmed if the participants felt sore, 
numb, distended, and/or warm. After discharge, the interventionists 
sent daily reminders via WeChat to inform the patients to perform 
acupressure, and delivered a weekly group meeting to address any issues 
patients encountered during the practice. Likewise, the interventionist 
needs to check the completion daily via WeChat. 
2.5.5. MBSR combined with acupressure 
Patients allocated to the combined group synchronously received 
MBSR and acupressure for eight weeks. The specific content of the in-
terventions was the same as that set out in the MBSR and Acupressure 
sections above. Participants in the combined group were suggested to 
start the MBSR practice around 10 a.m., followed by half an hour of 
acupressure. Similarly, patients in the combined group still need to 
complete one acupressure session around 3 p.m. Daily discussions and 
weekly group meetings were held between participants and 
interventionists. 
2.6. Data collection 
Two research assistants (RA) were included in the study and trained 
by the principal investigator (the first author) of the research. After 
obtaining informed consent, the RA collected the baseline data including 
sociodemographic information (a self-designed questionnaire) and in-
formation about sleep, fatigue, anxiety, and depression through a face- 
to-face questionnaire survey on the day of enrollment (T0). PSQI, 
Brief Fatigue Inventory (BFI–C), Hospital Anxiety and Depression 
(HADS), and the sleep parameters of wrist actigraphy data were 
collected repeatedly at the end of the fourth (T1) and eighth weeks (T2) 
of intervention. Notably, patients wore the wrist actigraphy for 12 h 
from 8:00 p.m. to 8:00 a.m. the next day at the data collection point 
including baseline, the mid-intervention (fourth week), and the end of 
intervention (eighth week). The data of wrist actigraphy were calculated 
and generated by ActiLife6.11.4 software. Participants completed 
questionnaires when they were undergoing chemotherapy in the hos-
pital or waiting for a chemotherapy appointment at the outpatient clinic. 
If the participant was not scheduled to return to the hospital at the data 
collection time, a research assistant performed a telephone interview. 
2.7. Measurements 
2.7.1. Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) 
The PSQI was used to measure patients’ sleep disturbance (Buysse 
et al., 1989). It is a self-reported questionnaire including nine items (the 
fifth item contains ten subitems.) The score for each domain ranges from 
0 to 3, and the total score ranges from 0 to 21 with a higher score 
indicating poorer sleep quality. The Chinese-version PSQI was found to 
have satisfactory reliability and validity in patients with lung cancer 
(Chen et al., 2008). Only the total score was calculated in this study, and 
a total score greater than 7 indicates that the patient has sleep disorders 
(Wang et al., 2022). The Cronbach alpha value was 0.70 in this study. 
2.7.2. Wrist actigraphy 
Wrist actigraphy is an instrument developed to monitor activity in-
tensity and is used in medicine to assess patients’ sleep quality. In this 
study, the Xiaomi Mi Band 2.0 was uniformly selected to monitor pa-
tients’ sleep quality (Pino-Ortega et al., 2021), and parameters related to 
wrist actigraphy were set according to the product manual. The data 
Q. Liu et al.</paragraph></page><page number="4"><paragraph>European Journal of Oncology Nursing 61 (2022) 102219
4
from the wrist activity meter were analyzed using ActiLife6.11.4 soft-
ware. The main sleep parameters were (1) sleep efficiency (SE): total 
sleep time/bedtime; (2) sleep latency (SL): time from going to bed to 
falling asleep; (3) total sleep time (TST): actual sleep time; (4) wake after 
sleep onset (WASO): time of waking during sleep; (5) number of 
awaking (NOA): the number of awakenings during total sleep time; and 
(6) mean waking by time (MWBT): wake after sleep onset/number of 
awaking. 
2.7.3. Brief Fatigue Inventory (BFI–C) 
The nine-item BFI was used to assess participants’ fatigue (Mendoza 
et al., 1999). The first three items assessed fatigue severity at its worst, 
usual, and right now, and the final six assessed impacts of fatigue on 
daily activity, mood, walking, work, enjoyment of life, and relations 
with others. Higher scores indicate more severe fatigue or more inter-
ference in life. The Chinese-version BFI–C had excellent internal con-
sistency with Cronbach’s coefficient alphas of 0.92 for three fatigue 
severity items and 0.90 for six fatigue interference items in cancer pa-
tients, and a rating of 0–6 for fatigue severity indicates “non-severe”, 
and 7 or greater indicates “severe” (Wang et al., 2004). The Cronbach 
alpha value was 0.86 in this study. 
2.7.4. Hospital Anxiety and Depression (HADS) 
The HADS was widely used to assess nonpsychotic anxiety and 
depression of inpatients (Zigmond and Snaith, 1983). It contains 14 
items—7 for assessing anxiety and 7 for depression. Each item is scored 
from 0 to 3, and the subscale total scores range from 0 to 21 with higher 
scores indicating more anxiety or depressive symptoms. In this study, 
the subscale with a score ≥8 would represent significant anxiety or 
depression (Bjelland et al., 2002). The Chinese version demonstrated 
good validity and reliability in cancer patients (Li et al., 2016). In this 
study, the Cronbach alpha values were 0.63 and 0.67 for the subscales of 
anxiety and depression, respectively. 
2.8. Statistical analysis 
IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, version 26.0 (IBM SPSS Data 
Collection, New York, NY, USA), was used to analyze data. Participants’ 
demographic and clinical characteristics were compared using variance 
analysis, Mann–Whitney U test, chi-square, or Fisher’s exact test when 
appropriate. The intention-to-treat (ITT) principle was adopted for 
analyzing the data. Missing data were supplemented using a multiple 
imputation approach. A repeated-measures analysis of variance 
(ANOVA) was used to explore between-group, within-group, and 
interaction effects, followed by a Least Significant Difference (LSD) test 
used to compare the outcomes between groups. The data of non-normal 
distribution (SL, WASO, MWBT) were transformed by rank order fol-
lowed by repeated-measures ANOVA. The criterion for statistical sig-
nificance was set at p &lt; 0.05 in a two-tailed test. 
2.9. Ethical considerations 
This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Mindong Hos-
pital Affiliated to Fujian Medical University (No.: 2019/0621–2). Par-
ticipants were given detailed information about the study and written 
informed consent was obtained from each patient before data collection. 
Patients’ wishes are fully respected, and they had the right to withdraw 
from the study at any time. The information collected was kept confi-
dential and will not be disclosed to others. 
3. Results 
3.1. Characteristics of participants 
Total 147 patients were included and randomly assigned to the 
routine care (n = 34), MBSR (n = 38), acupressure (n = 36), or MBSR 
with acupressure group (n = 39). Thirteen patients withdrew from the 
study after eight weeks due to condition deterioration (n = 1), refusal to 
participate (n = 10), and family caregivers’ refusal (n = 2)—10 in the 
MBSR group and three from the MBSR with acupressure group. Fig. 1 
presents a flowchart of recruitment and specific reasons for participants’ 
dropout. Notably, the 13 dropout patients show a significant (p &lt; 0.05) 
lower fatigue, anxiety, depression, WASO, MWBT, and higher SE and 
TST in the baseline compared to the completer (Appendix 3). Table 1 
demonstrates that there were no significant differences (p ≥ 0.05) in 
sociodemographic and clinical characteristics across the four groups. 
The vast majority of participants were female (98.64%) and married 
(98.64%). Their mean age was 51.41 ± 8.85 years, and the majority had 
a primary-school education level or below (68.03%), were unemployed 
(81.63%), and had undergone surgery (90.48%) without recurrence 
(99.32%). In addition, most patients were at neoplasm stage II or below 
(76.87%). Most (70.75%) had already received between one and five 
rounds of chemotherapy. 
3.2. Study outcomes 
The results of interventions on PSQI, sleep parameters measured by 
wrist actigraphy, fatigue, anxiety, and depression are presented in 
Table 2. The changes over time in the mean (and standard deviation) of 
all outcomes are shown in Appendix 4. The results of ANOVA showed a 
significant difference (p &lt; 0.05) in PSQI, and all sleep parameters 
measured by wrist actigraphy, and anxiety between groups. Simulta-
neously, ANOVA showed a significant difference (p &lt; 0.05) over time in 
PSQI, and all sleep parameters measured by wrist actigraphy, fatigue, 
and anxiety. The interaction effects were significant for PSQI, anxiety, 
and all sleep parameters measured by wrist actigraphy with an excep-
tion for SL (p = 0.243). Notably, there was no significant difference (p ≥
0.05) in the depression between groups, within the group, and interac-
tion effects. The results of further pairwise comparisons between the 
four groups by LSD are presented in Table 3. The three active treatments 
led to better PSQI outcomes (p &lt; 0.001), reduced fatigue (p &lt; 0.001), 
decreased anxiety (p &lt; 0.05), and improved sleep measured by all 
actigraphy indices with two exceptions (MBSR did not differ from con-
trol on SL (p = 0.235) and MWBT (p = 0.058)). Additionally, MBSR, but 
not acupressure and combined treatment, led to reduced depression, 
compared to control (p &lt; 0.05). Importantly, both acupressure and the 
combined intervention outperformed MBSR on four actigraphy indices: 
SE, SL, TST, and WASO (p &lt; 0.05), and the combined intervention 
further outperformed MBSR on PSQI (p = 0.03) and NOA (p = 0.003). 
Moreover, there was no significant difference (p ≥ 0.05) across all 
outcomes between acupressure and combined intervention. 
4. Discussion 
This study is the first to compare the effects of MBSR, acupressure, 
and MBSR combined with acupressure on sleep quality and fatigue in 
patients with breast cancer. The main findings are that MBSR, 
acupressure, and MBSR with acupressure all have varying degrees of 
positive effect on breast cancer patients’ sleep quality, fatigue, and 
anxiety. Notably, MBSR combined with acupressure shows a remarkable 
advantage in improving sleep quality in breast cancer patients. 
Unexpectedly, the rate of participants refusing to participate 
(37.76%) was high. This may be partly explained by how most cancer 
patients and family members are more concerned with disease treatment 
and prognosis than psychological well-being. In addition, all partici-
pants in this study experienced sleep disorders, possibly resulting in 
their disinterest in participation. Surprisingly, the dropout rate was 
relatively higher (26.32%) in the MBSR group. This may be because 
more than half of the patients (64.29%) in the MBSR group had a 
primary-school education level or below, which may have caused some 
difficulty in understanding and maintaining the essence of MBSR. This 
result is consistent with a previous study with a drop-out rate of 28.89% 
Q. Liu et al.</paragraph></page><page number="5"><paragraph>European Journal of Oncology Nursing 61 (2022) 102219
5
after completion of an eight-week MBSR intervention (Witek Janusek 
et al., 2019). Another surprising result is that the mean age was signif-
icantly lower for dropout patients than for included patients. This might 
be partly due to the fact that the majority of older patients are more 
accustomed to a static lifestyle and are more likely to accept and adhere 
to MBSR practices. The dropout participants also showed lower fatigue, 
anxiety, depression, WASO, and MWBT as well as higher SE and TST 
than the included participants. This may explain one reason for drop-
ping out; patients were less motivated to participate after their sleep and 
psychological problems improved. 
In this study, the participants were patients diagnosed with sleep 
disorders through both self-reporting and actigraphy monitoring; thus, 
the simple subjective sleep disorder can be partly avoided. This study 
showed that MBSR, acupressure, and MBSR with acupressure all 
significantly improved patients’ sleep quality compared to the control 
group. Meanwhile, further pairwise comparison results indicated that 
acupressure and combined therapy were more effective for improving 
objective sleep quality than MBSR, and the combined treatment further 
outperformed MBSR on subjective sleep quality. However, compared to 
acupressure, combined treatment had no significant advantage in 
improving sleep quality. This suggests that acupressure alone can 
improve the objective sleep quality of patients in the short term, while 
combined treatment was recommended to improve patients’ subjective 
and objective sleep. A recent study indicated that self-administered 
acupressure taught as a short training course is effective in improving 
sleep quality in individuals with insomnia disorder (Yeung et al., 2022). 
Since acupressure can stimulate body nerves, and muscles through 
finger massage and pressure to promote nerve and muscle regulation 
and inhibit cerebral cortex response, the human body enters a relaxed 
and comfortable natural state, and sleep quality is improved (Min et al., 
2021). 
Although MBSR is not better than acupressure or combined therapy 
at improving patients’ subjective or objective sleep quality, MBSR was 
effective at improving patients’ subjective or objective sleep quality 
compared with the control group. As MBSR intends to cultivate 
nonjudgmental awareness of the present moment to develop greater 
emotional balance, it may reduce stress and facilitate sleep quality in 
those confronted with cancer (Zhang et al., 2019). Related research 
indicated that mindfulness meditation can affect cognitive behavior 
patterns and improve sleep quality by changing brain structures and 
networks, decreasing automatic responses, and increasing relaxation 
responses (Black et al, 2015). However, there is limited evidence that 
MBSR can improve actigraphy sleep parameters, and most studies only 
focus on patients’ self-reported sleep quality rather than objective out-
comes (Chen et al., 2020). In addition, the actual effect of MBSR may be 
affected by the higher rate of loss to follow-up in the MBSR group. 
Gaining patients’ trust and making MBSR more well-received are 
important for improving compliance with MBSR interventions in future 
studies. 
Our study indicated that MBSR, acupressure, and MBSR with 
acupressure were all beneficial for relieving breast cancer patients’ fa-
tigue. Further, pairwise comparison results showed that there was no 
significant difference in effect on fatigue among the three intervention 
groups. This shows that acupressure, MBSR, or combined therapy can be 
used as an effective strategy for relieving fatigue in breast cancer pa-
tients. Research has demonstrated that acupressure is effective at alle-
viating the fatigue of cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy and has 
suggested that nursing personnel could incorporate acupressure into 
clinical practice as part of a multimodal approach to alleviating fatigue 
in cancer survivors (Khanghah et al., 2019). Although compliance was 
lower in the MBSR group, patients who remained enrolled in the study 
still benefited from MBSR practice. In this study, MBSR with acupressure 
did not demonstrate better effects in alleviating patients’ fatigue. The 
combination of the two interventions could cause patients to be 
distracted or choose only one intervention in practice based on their 
preferences. 
MBSR, acupressure, and combined therapy all showed a positive 
effect on patients’ anxiety; there was no difference between their out-
comes. This result is consistent with those of previous studies indicating 
that acupressure can promote sleep and calm emotions by stimulating 
nerve responses and releasing serotonin (Chen et al., 2022a, 2022b). In 
addition, research has demonstrated that sleep quality is associated with 
anxiety, which can indirectly explain why MBSR, acupressure, and 
combined therapy can alleviate patients’ anxiety (Maass et al., 2020). 
Since anxiety is characterized as a kind of agitated emotion produced by 
excessive worry about the safety of relatives or their own lives, future, 
Fig. 1. Participants CONSORT flow chart.  
Q. Liu et al.</paragraph></page><page number="6"><paragraph>European Journal of Oncology Nursing 61 (2022) 102219
6
and fate (Zigmond and Snaith, 1983), the practice of MBSR and 
acupressure allows patients to focus on the present, relax their mind and 
body, get rid of worries about irrelevant things, and further ameliorate 
anxiety. Interestingly, MBSR is beneficial for decreasing depression, 
compared with the control group. This result is consistent with a pre-
vious systematic review indicating that MBSR interventions are highly 
beneficial for reducing depression in the short term (Chang et al., 2021). 
However, acupressure and combined therapy were ineffective at alle-
viating patients’ depression. This result is inconsistent with an existing 
systematic review (Lin et al., 2022). This may be partly explained by the 
fact that the baseline depression score of participants in this study was 
&gt;10. The significant difference in anxiety and depression between in-
terventions was not likely to be found due to a ceiling effect because the 
average baseline HADS scores of participants in this study were over the 
threshold for clinically significant anxiety and depression. 
Notably, in this study, the MBSR and acupressure were delivered by 
trained clinical nurses. Integrating acupressure and MBSR into clinical 
nursing care might achieve positive effects. This reflects the dissemi-
nation and application potential of MBSR, and acupressure in hospital-
ized patients. In this study, the adherence of participants in the 
acupressure group was higher than that of the MBSR and combined 
groups. This may be partly explained by that acupressure, as a common 
treatment of traditional Chinese medicine, is more easily accepted and 
trusted by the Chinese population. MBSR practice requires participants 
to fully understand instructions and focus their attention, which may be 
difficult for some older patients with low education levels. Notably, 
although there was no COVID-19 outbreak in the study setting, many 
public health measures such as quarantine requirements for admission 
to the hospital were still being implemented to prevent the spread of 
COVID-19, which makes recruitment and follow-up of this study more 
difficult. 
4.1. Limitations 
Despite the positive effects of MBSR, acupressure, and MBSR with 
acupressure on patients’ sleep quality, fatigue, and anxiety, this study 
has several limitations. First, the participants were recruited from only 
one hospital in the south of China, which limits the generalizability of 
the findings. Second, although the number of participants met the re-
quirements of sample size, the sample size is relatively small, which may 
reduce the possibility of finding positive results. Third, part of the in-
terventions was performed in an inpatient setting, which may increase 
the risk of some contamination and confounding factors. Notably, the 10 
repeated measure ANOVAs conducted increase the likelihood of a type I 
error. In addition, although the intervention lasted for eight weeks, the 
long-term effects cannot be observed due to a lack of further follow-up. 
A future study with a longer follow-up period should be conducted to 
confirm the effects. Moreover, since the control group received routine 
Table 1 
Social-demographic and clinical characteristics of participants.  
Variables 
Total(N = 147) n 
(%) 
Control (N = 34) n 
(%) 
MBSR (N = 38) n 
(%) 
Acupressure (N = 36) n 
(%) 
Combined (N = 39) n 
(%) 
F/χ2 
p 
Gender      
5.949 
0.114a 
Male 
2(1.36) 
2(5.88) 
0(0) 
0(0) 
0(0)   
Female 
145(98.64) 
32(94.12) 
38(100) 
36(100) 
39(100) 
Age(Mean ± SD) 
51.41 ± 8.85 
51.41 ± 10.10 
48.58 ± 8.48 
53.06 ± 8.29 
52.67 ± 8.19 
2.013 
0.115b 
Age cohorts      
14.002 
0.122a 
≤44 
27(18.37) 
7(20.59) 
11(28.95) 
3(8.34) 
6(15.38)   
45–59 
89(60.54) 
20(58.82) 
24(63.16) 
21(58.33) 
24(61.54) 
60–74 
29(19.73) 
6(17.65) 
3(7.89) 
12(33.33) 
8(20.52) 
75–89 
2(1.36) 
1(2.94) 
0(0) 
0(0) 
1(2.56) 
Marital status      
2.774 
0.428a 
Married 
145(98.64) 
34(100) 
37(97.37) 
35(97.22) 
39(100)   
Unmarried or Divorced 
2(1.36) 
0(0) 
1(2.63) 
1(2.78) 
0(0) 
Education level      
3.619 
0.728a 
Primary school or below 
100(68.03) 
26(76.47) 
25(65.79) 
24(66.67) 
25(64.11)   
Middle or high school 
27(18.36) 
5(14.71) 
9(23.68) 
7(19.44) 
6(15.38) 
University degree 
20(13.61) 
3(8.82) 
4(10.53) 
5(13.89) 
8(20.51) 
Employment      
2.678 
0.444a 
Employed 
27(18.37) 
6(17.65) 
4(10.53) 
8(22.22) 
9(23.08)   
Unemployed 
120(81.63) 
28(82.35) 
34(89.47) 
28(77.78) 
30(76.92) 
Relapse      
2.951 
0.399a 
Yes 
1(0.68) 
1(2.94) 
0(0) 
0(0) 
0(0)   
No 
146(99.32) 
33(97.06) 
38(100) 
36(100) 
39(100)   
Surgery      
7.294 
0.063a 
Yes 
133(90.48) 
33(97.06) 
37(97.37) 
30(83.33) 
34(87.18)   
No 
14(9.52) 
1(2.94) 
1(2.63) 
6(16.67) 
5(12.82)   
Neoplasm staging      
5.064 
0.956a 
0 
5(3.40) 
2(5.88) 
0(0) 
1(2.78) 
2(5.13)   
I 
33(22.45) 
8(23.53) 
8(21.05) 
9(25.00) 
8(20.51)   
II 
75(51.02) 
17(50.00) 
20(52.64) 
17(47.22) 
21(53.85)   
III 
25(17.01) 
5(14.71) 
8(21.05) 
7(19.44) 
5(12.82)   
IV 
9(6.12) 
2(5.88) 
2(5.26) 
2(5.56) 
3(7.69)   
Frequency of 
chemotherapy      
2.013 
0.339a 
1-5 
104(70.75) 
26(76.47) 
27(71.06) 
24(66.67) 
27(69.23)   
6-10 
31(21.09) 
4(11.76) 
9(23.68) 
10(27.77) 
8(20.51)   
11-15 
5(3.40) 
1(2.95) 
2(5.26) 
0(0) 
2(5.13)   
16-20 
3(2.04) 
2(5.88) 
0(0) 
1(2.78) 
0(0)   
20 or above 
4(2.72) 
1(2.94) 
0(0) 
1(2.78) 
2(5.13)   
Note：. 
MBSR: Mindfulness-based stress reduction. 
SD: Standard deviation. 
a χ2 test. 
b Analysis of variance. 
Q. Liu et al.</paragraph></page><page number="7"><paragraph>European Journal of Oncology Nursing 61 (2022) 102219
7
care and was not given a placebo, we could not find and explain the 
contribution of the placebo effect in this study. Lastly, a consistency 
analysis between subjective and objective sleep quality was not con-
ducted in this study. 
5. Conclusion 
These findings provide supplementary evidence for ameliorating 
sleep quality, fatigue, anxiety, and depression in breast cancer patients 
with sleep disorders by comparing the effects of MBSR, acupressure, and 
MBSR with acupressure. Compared to MBSR, acupressure and combined 
therapy demonstrate a remarkable advantage in improving actigraphy- 
assessed sleep quality. Importantly, MBSR combined with acupressure 
outperformed MBSR in improving subjective sleep quality. In future 
clinical practice, we should select appropriate intervention methods 
according to the symptoms and characteristics of cancer patients with 
sleep disorders. This study suggested that it would be a valuable attempt 
to incorporate MBSR and acupressure as complementary therapies for 
ameliorating patients’ sleep quality into daily nursing care. 
Credit author statement 
Qixi Liu: Conceptualization, project implementation. Chunfeng 
Wang: Methodology, drafting the article, and revising. Ying Wang: Data 
curation, Writing – review &amp; editing. Wenkui Xu: Data curation and 
interpretation of data. Jinqing Wu: Resources, project administration. 
Chenju Zhan: Resources, project administration. Rong Hu: Methodol-
ogy, Validation, project design, and supervision. 
Funding 
This study was supported by the Clinical special project of Fujian 
University of Traditional Chinese Medicine (Grant No. XB2019060). 
Table 2 
Comparisons of outcomes between three intervention groups and control group at different time points.  
Outcomes 
Group 
T0（Mean ± SD） 
T1（Mean ± SD） 
T2（Mean ± SD） 
Between groups (F, p) 
Within group (F, p) 
Interaction effect (F, p) 
PSQI 
Control 
11.15 ± 1.73 
11.21 ± 2.98 
11.26 ± 2.84 
13.223,＜0.001 
101.560, &lt;0.001 
15.529, &lt;0.001 
MBSR 
10.82 ± 2.51 
10.26 ± 2.89 
7.18 ± 2.84 
Acupressure 
11.42 ± 2.38 
8.33 ± 2.48 
7.03 ± 2.15 
Combined 
11.28 ± 2.73 
8.10 ± 2.86 
5.92 ± 1.91 
SE 
Control 
81.32 ± 4.32 
82.11 ± 4.98 
80.61 ± 9.57 
21.856, &lt;0.001 
69.126, &lt;0.001 
11.986, &lt;0.001 
MBSR 
81.86 ± 5.69 
84.52 ± 8.37 
92.42 ± 6.63 
Acupressure 
82.29 ± 3.33 
91.27 ± 6.13 
91.86 ± 7.60 
Combined 
80.77 ± 5.81 
90.47 ± 6.99 
93.74 ± 5.72 
SL* 
Control 
271.97 ± 89.36 
265.99 ± 106.96 
221.16 ± 163.04 
5.245, 0.002 
10.704, &lt;0.001 
1.330, 0.243 
MBSR 
268.87 ± 117.87 
240.79 ± 106.78 
191.53 ± 116.83 
Acupressure 
239.18 ± 114.79 
162.88 ± 119.22 
199.83 ± 117.64 
Combined 
255.81 ± 134.11 
181.15 ± 134.80 
161.45 ± 133.62 
TST 
Control 
439.13 ± 23.35 
443.41 ± 26.92 
435.31 ± 51.70 
20.307, &lt;0.001 
57.674, &lt;0.001 
9.621, &lt;0.001 
MBSR 
442.07 ± 30.73 
458.01 ± 50.12 
491.58 ± 45.32 
Acupressure 
444.34 ± 18.00 
492.85 ± 33.11 
496.06 ± 41.05 
Combined 
436.17 ± 31.40 
490.72 ± 40.00 
505.35 ± 32.75 
WASO* 
Control 
309.41 ± 72.69 
289.93 ± 102.45 
268.21 ± 126.18 
17.301, &lt;0.001 
84.082, &lt;0.001 
7.011, &lt;0.001 
MBSR 
290.70 ± 95.73 
238.36 ± 134.11 
138.63 ± 101.72 
Acupressure 
309.65 ± 75.28 
146.06 ± 92.39 
113.81 ± 108.17 
Combined 
292.89 ± 104.75 
156.49 ± 99.86 
117.04 ± 97.86 
NOA 
Control 
20.74 ± 5.78 
19.03 ± 6.80 
19.09 ± 7.75 
11.968, &lt;0.001 
36.118, &lt;0.001 
2.815, 0.011 
MBSR 
20.32 ± 5.75 
17.55 ± 7.45 
13.66 ± 5.23 
Acupressure 
20.39 ± 6.35 
14.00 ± 7.06 
12.67 ± 4.07 
Combined 
19.82 ± 7.94 
12.95 ± 7.67 
10.72 ± 5.37 
MWBT* 
Control 
249.94 ± 92.49 
264.21 ± 124.05 
256.51 ± 138.05 
4.51, 0.005 
11.202, &lt;0.001 
2.505, 0.024 
MBSR 
234.50 ± 101.45 
238.38 ± 136.05 
195.13 ± 136.77 
Acupressure 
258.03 ± 93.55 
187.08 ± 129.10 
127.15 ± 119.26 
Combined 
262.95 ± 98.17 
215.27 ± 123.32 
169.80 ± 151.85 
Fatigue 
Control 
7.00 ± 2.01 
6.90 ± 1.39 
7.01 ± 1.54 
15.856, &lt;0.001 
50.568, &lt;0.001 
6.349, &lt;0.001 
MBSR 
6.40 ± 1.43 
5.61 ± 1.43 
4.65 ± 1.26 
Acupressure 
6.79 ± 1.10 
5.39 ± 1.30 
5.25 ± 1.36 
Combined 
6.69 ± 1.15 
5.17 ± 1.28 
4.80 ± 1.06 
Anxiety 
Control 
11.18 ± 2.12 
11.24 ± 2.27 
11.47 ± 2.29 
3.439, 0.019 
10.893, &lt;0.001 
2.289, 0.039 
MBSR 
10.47 ± 3.40 
9.74 ± 3.47 
9.29 ± 2.95 
Acupressure 
11.25 ± 3.07 
10.39 ± 2.76 
9.06 ± 3.07 
Combined 
11.15 ± 3.45 
10.56 ± 2.54 
8.85 ± 2.33 
Depression 
Control 
10.29 ± 2.26 
10.74 ± 2.09 
11.44 ± 3.14 
2.226, 0.088 
0.145, 0.853 
0.808, 0.558 
MBSR 
9.74 ± 4.68 
9.74 ± 3.52 
9.34 ± 3.29 
Acupressure 
10.69 ± 3.38 
10.42 ± 3.10 
10.17 ± 3.46 
Combined 
10.21 ± 3.48 
9.92 ± 4.16 
9.26 ± 3.06 
These results were obtained from a repeated-measures analysis of variance (ANOVA). 
MD: Mean difference. 
SD: Standard deviation. 
MBSR: Mindfulness-based stress reduction. 
PSQI: Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index. 
SE: sleep efficiency. 
SL: sleep latency. 
TST: total sleep time. 
WASO: wake after sleep onset. 
NOA: number of awakings. 
MWBT: mean waking by time. 
Q. Liu et al.</paragraph></page><page number="8"><paragraph>European Journal of Oncology Nursing 61 (2022) 102219
8
Data availability 
The datasets used or analyzed during the current study are available 
from the corresponding author on reasonable request. 
Declaration of competing interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. 
Acknowledgments 
We would like to thank all participants for their time and feedback. 
We would like to thank Editage (www.editage.cn) for English language 
editing. 
Appendix A. Supplementary data 
Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. 
org/10.1016/j.ejon.2022.102219. 
References 
Abedian, Z., Eskandari, L., Abdi, H., Ebrahimzadeh, S., 2015. The effect of acupressure 
on sleep quality in menopausal women: a randomized control trial. Iran. J. Med. Sci. 
40 (4), 328–334. 
Abrahams, H.J.G., Knoop, H., Schreurs, M., Aaronson, N.K., Jacobsen, P.B., Newton, R. 
U., Courneya, K.S., Aitken, J.F., Arving, C., Brandberg, Y., Chambers, S.K., 
Gielissen, M.F.M., Glimelius, B., Goedendorp, M.M., Graves, K.D., Heiney, S.P., 
Horne, R., Hunter, M.S., Johansson, B., Northouse, L.L., Oldenburg, H.S.A., Prins, J. 
B., Savard, J., van Beurden, M., van den Berg, S.W., Verdonck-de Leeuw, I.M., 
Buffart, L.M., 2020. Moderators of the effect of psychosocial interventions on fatigue 
in women with breast cancer and men with prostate cancer: Individual patient data 
meta-analyses. Psychooncology 29 (11), 1772–1785. https://doi.org/10.1002/ 
pon.5522. 
Arab, Z., Shariati, A.R., Asayesh, H., Vakili, M.A., Bahrami-Taghanaki, H., Azizi, H., 
2016. A sham-controlled trial of acupressure on the quality of sleep and life in 
haemodialysis patients. Acupunct. Med. 34 (1), 2–6. https://doi.org/10.1136/ 
acupmed-2014-010369. 
Bjelland, I., Dahl, A., Haug, T., Neckelmann, D.J. J.o. p. r., 2002. The validity of the 
hospital anxiety and depression scale: an Updated literature review. J. Psychosom. 
Res. 52 (2), 69–77. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0022-3999(01)00296-3. 
Black, D., O’Reilly, G., Olmstead, R., Breen, E., Irwin, M., 2015. Mindfulness meditation 
and improvement in sleep quality and daytime impairment among older adults with 
sleep disturbances: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Intern. Med. 175 (4), 494–501. 
https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2014.8081. 
Buysse, D., Reynolds, C., Monk, T., Berman, S., Kupfer, D., 1989. The Pittsburgh Sleep 
Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research. Psychiatr. 
Res. 28 (2), 193–213. https://doi.org/10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4. 
Chang, Y., Lin, G., Yeh, T., Chang, Y., Yang, C., Lo, C., Hu, W.Y., 2022. Impact of 
mindfulness-based stress reduction on female sexual function and mental health in 
patients with breast cancer. Support. Care Cancer 30 (5), 4315–4325. https://doi. 
org/10.1007/s00520-021-06540-y. 
Chang, Y.C., Yeh, T.L., Chang, Y.M., Hu, W.Y., 2021. Short-term effects of randomized 
mindfulness-based intervention in female breast cancer survivors: A systematic 
review and meta-analysis. Cancer Nurs 44 (6), E703–E714. https://doi.org/ 
10.1097/NCC.0000000000000889. 
Chen, M.L., Yu, C.T., Yang, C.H., 2008. Sleep disturbances and quality of life in lung 
cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy. Lung Cancer 62 (3), 391–400. https:// 
doi.org/10.1016/j.lungcan.2008.03.016. 
Chen, S., Hou, W., Lai, J., Kwong, J., Lin, P., 2022a. Effects of acupressure on anxiety: a 
systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Integr. Compl. Med. 28 (1), 25–35. https:// 
doi.org/10.1089/jicm.2020.0256. 
Chen, S.R., Hou, W.H., Lai, J.N., Kwong, J.S.W., Lin, P.C., 2022b. Effects of acupressure 
on anxiety: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Integr. Complement. Med. 28 
(1), 25–35. https://doi.org/10.1089/jicm.2020.0256. 
Chen, T.L., Chang, S.C., Hsieh, H.F., Huang, C.Y., Chuang, J.H., Wang, H.H., 2020. 
Effects of mindfulness-based stress reduction on sleep quality and mental health for 
insomnia patients: a meta-analysis. J. Psychosom. Res. 135, 110144 https://doi.org/ 
10.1016/j.jpsychores.2020.110144. 
Ge, L., Wang, Q., He, Y., Wu, D., Zhou, Q., Xu, N., International Trustworthy traditional 
Chinese Medicine Recommendations Working, G, 2022. Acupuncture for cancer 
pain: an evidence-based clinical practice guideline. Chin. Med. 17 (1), 8. https://doi. 
org/10.1186/s13020-021-00558-4. 
Gu, J., Strauss, C., Bond, R., Cavanagh, K., 2015. How do mindfulness-based cognitive 
therapy and mindfulness-based stress reduction improve mental health and 
wellbeing? A systematic review and meta-analysis of mediation studies. Clin. 
Psychol. Rev. 37, 1–12. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpr.2015.01.006. 
Guimond, A.J., Ivers, H., Savard, J., 2020. Clusters of psychological symptoms in breast 
cancer: is there a common psychological mechanism? Cancer Nurs. 43 (5), 343–353. 
https://doi.org/10.1097/NCC.0000000000000705. 
Hajj, A., Hachem, R., Khoury, R., Hallit, S., El, J.B., Nasr, F., Rabbaa Khabbaz, L., 2021. 
Clinical and genetic factors associated with anxiety and depression in breast cancer 
patients: a cross-sectional study. BMC Cancer 21 (1), 872. https://doi.org/10.1186/ 
s12885-021-08615-9. 
Hoang, H.T.X., Molassiotis, A., Chan, C.W., Vu, A.H., Bui, P.T., 2022. Pilot randomized 
sham-controlled trial of self-acupressure to manage the symptom cluster of 
insomnia, depression, and anxiety in cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy. 
Sleep Breath. 26 (1), 445–456. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11325-021-02370-8. 
Kang, C., Sun, S., Yang, Z., Fan, X., Yuan, J., Xu, L., Yang, J., 2021. The psychological 
effect of internet-based mindfulness-based stress reduction on the survivors of breast 
cancer during the COVID-19. Front. Psychiatr. 12, 738579 https://doi.org/10.3389/ 
fpsyt.2021.738579. 
Khanghah, A.G., Rizi, M.S., Nabi, B.N., Adib, M., Leili, E.K.N., 2019. Effects of 
acupressure on fatigue in patients with cancer who underwent chemotherapy. 
J. Acupunct. Meridian Stud. 12 (4), 103–110. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. 
jams.2019.07.003. 
Leysen, L., Lahousse, A., Nijs, J., Adriaenssens, N., Mairesse, O., Ivakhnov, S., 
Beckwee, D., 2019. Prevalence and risk factors of sleep disturbances in breast 
Table 3 
Pairwise comparisons of sleep quality, fatigue, anxiety and depression between three intervention groups and control group.  
Outcomes 
MBSR vs. Control 
Acupressure vs. Control 
Combined vs. Control 
MBSR vs. Acupressure 
MBSR vs. Combined 
Acupressure vs. Combined 
MD 
p 
MD 
p 
MD 
p 
MD 
p 
MD 
p 
MD 
p 
PSQI 
−1.785 
&lt;0.001 
−2.280 
&lt;0.001 
−2.770 
&lt;0.001 
0.495 
0.283 
0.985 
0.030 
0.490 
0.285 
SE 
4.920 
&lt;0.001 
7.124 
&lt;0.001 
6.976 
&lt;0.001 
−2.204 
0.026 
−2.056 
0.034 
0.148 
0.879 
SL 
−19.311 
0.235 
−52.410 
0.002 
−53.569 
0.001 
33.098 
0.040 
34.258 
0.030 
1.160 
0.942 
TST 
24.603 
&lt;0.001 
38.469 
&lt;0.001 
38.132 
&lt;0.001 
−13.866 
0.013 
−13.529 
0.014 
0.337 
0.951 
WASO 
−66.620 
&lt;0.001 
−99.343 
&lt;0.001 
−100.378 
&lt;0.001 
32.723 
0.038 
33.758 
0.029 
1.035 
0.947 
NOA 
−2.442 
0.008 
−3.933 
&lt;0.001 
−5.122 
&lt;0.001 
1.490 
0.096 
2.680 
0.003 
1.190 
0.180 
MWBT 
−34.216 
0.058 
−66.133 
&lt;0.001 
−40.883 
0.023 
31.916 
0.072 
6.667 
0.700 
−25.250 
0.152 
Fatigue 
−1.418 
&lt;0.001 
−1.157 
&lt;0.001 
−1.418 
&lt;0.001 
−0.261 
0.268 
−0.000 
1.000 
0.261 
0.265 
Anxiety 
−1.461 
0.003 
−1.063 
0.029 
−1.106 
0.021 
0.398 
0.397 
−0.355 
0.442 
0.043 
0.926 
Depression 
−1.218 
0.024 
−0.398 
0.465 
−1.029 
0.055 
−0.821 
0.122 
−0.190 
0.714 
0.631 
0.231 
These results were obtained from a Least Significant Difference (LSD) test. 
MD: Mean difference. 
SD: Standard deviation. 
MBSR: Mindfulness-based stress reduction. 
PSQI: Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index. 
SE: sleep efficiency. 
SL: sleep latency. 
TST: total sleep time. 
WASO: wake after sleep onset. 
NOA: number of awaking. 
MWBT: mean waking by time. 
Q. Liu et al.</paragraph></page><page number="9"><paragraph>European Journal of Oncology Nursing 61 (2022) 102219
9
cancersurvivors: systematic review and meta-analyses. Support. Care Cancer 27 (12), 
4401–4433. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00520-019-04936-5. 
Li, Q., Lin, Y., Hu, C., Xu, Y., Zhou, H., Yang, L., Xu, Y., 2016. The Chinese version of 
hospital anxiety and depression scale: psychometric properties in Chinese cancer 
patients and their family caregivers. Eur. J. Oncol. Nurs. 25, 16–23. https://doi.org/ 
10.1016/j.ejon.2016.09.004. 
Lin, J., Chen, T., He, J., Chung, R.C.K., Ma, H., Tsang, H.W.H., 2022. Impacts of 
acupressure treatment on depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis. World 
J. Psychiatr. 12 (1), 169–186. https://doi.org/10.5498/wjp.v12.i1.169. 
Lin, L., Zhang, Y., Qian, H.Y., Xu, J.L., Xie, C.Y., Dong, B., Tian, L., 2021. Auricular 
acupressure for cancer-related fatigue during lung cancer chemotherapy: a 
randomised trial. BMJ Support. Palliat. Care 11 (1), 32–39. https://doi.org/ 
10.1136/bmjspcare-2019-001937. 
Liu, B., Wu, X., Shi, L., Li, H., Wu, D., Lai, X., Li, D., 2021. Correlations of social isolation 
and anxiety and depression symptoms among patients with breast cancer of 
Heilongjiang province in China: the mediating role of social support. Nurs. Open 8 
(4), 1981–1989. https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.876. 
Lu, M.J., Lin, S.T., Chen, K.M., Tsang, H.Y., Su, S.F., 2013. Acupressure improves sleep 
quality of psychogeriatric inpatients. Nurs. Res. 62 (2), 130–137. https://doi.org/ 
10.1097/NNR.0b013e3182781524. 
Maass, S., Boerman, L.M., Brandenbarg, D., Verhaak, P.F.M., Maduro, J.H., de Bock, G. 
H., Berendsen, A.J., 2020. Symptoms in long-term breast cancer survivors: a cross- 
sectional study in primary care. Breast 54, 133–138. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. 
breast.2020.09.013. 
Mendoza, T., Wang, X., Cleeland, C., Morrissey, M., Johnson, B., Wendt, J., Huber, S., 
1999. The rapid assessment of fatigue severity in cancer patients: use of the Brief 
Fatigue Inventory. Cancer 85 (5), 1186–1196. https://doi.org/10.1002/(sici)1097- 
0142(19990301)85:5&lt;1186::aid-cncr24&gt;3.0.co;2-n. 
Min, J., Kim, B., Park, H., 2021. The effects of auricular acupressure on the sleep of the 
elderly using polysomnography, actigraphy and blood test: randomized, single-blind, 
sham control. Compl. Ther. Clin. Pract. 45, 101464 https://doi.org/10.1016/j. 
ctcp.2021.101464. 
Muller, K.E., Barton, C.N., 1989. Approximate power for repeated-measures ANOVA 
lacking sphericity. J. Am. Stat. Assoc. 84 (406), 549–555. 
Nourizadeh, R., Khanipour, S., Zamiri, R., Namin, M., Khalili, A., Hakimi, S.J. M.a., 2022. 
A comparison of the effects of self-acupressure and aerobic exercises on sleep 
disorders of breast cancer survivors: A controlled randomized clinical trial. Med. 
Acupunct. 34 (2), 131–136. https://doi.org/10.1089/acu.2020.1515. 
Pilevarzadeh, M., Amirshahi, M., Afsargharehbagh, R., Rafiemanesh, H., Hashemi, S.M., 
Balouchi, A., 2019. Global prevalence of depression among breast cancer patients: a 
systematic review and meta-analysis. Breast Cancer Res. Treat. 176 (3), 519–533. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10549-019-05271-3. 
Pino-Ortega, J., Gomez-Carmona, C.D., Rico-Gonzalez, M., 2021. Accuracy of Xiaomi Mi 
Band 2.0, 3.0 and 4.0 to measure step count and distance for physical activity and 
healthcare in adults over 65 years. Gait Posture 87, 6–10. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. 
gaitpost.2021.04.015. 
Puigpinos-Riera, R., Serral, G., Sala, M., Bargallo, X., Quintana, M.J., Espinosa, M., 
Vidal, E., 2020. Cancer-related fatigue and its determinants in a cohort of women 
with breast cancer: the DAMA Cohort. Support. Care Cancer 28 (11), 5213–5221. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00520-020-05337-9. 
Ratcliff, C.G., Zepeda, S.G., Hall, M.H., Tullos, E.A., Fowler, S., Chaoul, A., Cohen, L., 
2021. Patient characteristics associated with sleep disturbance in breast cancer 
survivors. Support. Care Cancer 29 (5), 2601–2611. https://doi.org/10.1007/ 
s00520-020-05777-3. 
Ruel, S., Ivers, H., Savard, M., Gouin, J., Lemieux, J., Provencher, L., Savard, J., 2020. 
Insomnia, immunity, and infections in cancer patients: results from a longitudinal 
study. Health Psychol. 39 (5), 358–369. https://doi.org/10.1037/hea0000811. 
Schell, L.K., Monsef, I., Wockel, A., Skoetz, N., 2019. Mindfulness-based stress reduction 
for women diagnosed with breast cancer. Cochrane Database Syst. Rev. 3, CD011518 
https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD011518.pub2. 
Sung, H., Ferlay, J., Siegel, R.L., Laversanne, M., Soerjomataram, I., Jemal, A., Bray, F., 
2021. Global cancer Statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and 
mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA A Cancer J. Clin. 71 (3), 
209–249. https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21660. 
Tan, J.Y., Liu, J., Suen, L.K.P., Molassiotis, A., Wang, T., 2020. Development and 
validation of an evidence-based auricular acupressure intervention for managing 
chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in breast cancer patients. Compl. Ther. 
Med. 52, 102502 https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ctim.2020.102502. 
Tian, X., Zhang, Z.L., Jin, Y.F., Chen, H., Jimenez-Herrera, M.F., 2021. The use of 
mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) for lung cancer patients: protocol for a 
systematic review and meta-analysis. Ann. Palliat. Med. 10 (7), 8276–8282. https:// 
doi.org/10.21037/apm-21-194. 
Vallance, J.K., Nguyen, N.H., Moore, M.M., Reeves, M.M., Rosenberg, D.E., Boyle, T., 
Milton, S., Friedenreich, C.M., English, D.R., Lynch, B.M., 2020. Effects of the 
ACTIVity And TEchnology (ACTIVATE) intervention on health-related quality of life 
and fatigue outcomes in breast cancer survivors. Psychooncology 29 (1), 204–211. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/pon.5298. 
VanderWalde, N., Martin, M., Kocak, M., Morningstar, C., Deal, A., Nyrop, K., Muss, H., 
2021. Randomized phase II study of a home-based walking intervention for 
radiation-related fatigue among older patients with breast cancer. J. Geriatr. 12 (2), 
227–234. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jgo.2020.09.013. 
Wang, L., Wu, Y.X., Lin, Y.Q., Wang, L., Zeng, Z.N., Xie, X.L., Wei, S.C., 2022. Reliability 
and validity of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index among frontline COVID-19 health 
care workers using classical test theory and item response theory. J. Clin. Sleep Med. 
18 (2), 541–551. https://doi.org/10.5664/jcsm.9658. 
Wang, X.S., Hao, X.S., Wang, Y., Guo, H., Jiang, Y.Q., Mendoza, T.R., Cleeland, C.S., 
2004. Validation study of the Chinese version of the Brief fatigue inventory (BFI-C). 
J. Pain Symptom Manag. 27 (4), 322–332. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. 
jpainsymman.2003.09.008. 
Witek Janusek, L., Tell, D., Mathews, H.L., 2019. Mindfulness based stress reduction 
provides psychological benefit and restores immune function of women newly 
diagnosed with breast cancer: a randomized trial with active control. Brain Behav. 
Immun. 80, 358–373. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2019.04.012. 
Yeung, W., Yu, B., Chung, K., Zhang, Z., Lao, L., Ho, F., 2022. Self-administered 
acupressure for insomnia disorder: a randomized controlled trial. 
Phytopharmacology 99, 153993. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phymed.2022.153993. 
Yoon, H.G., Park, H., 2019. The effect of auricular acupressure on sleep in breast cancer 
patients undergoing chemotherapy: a single-blind, randomized controlled trial. 
Appl. Nurs. Res. 48, 45–51. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apnr.2019.05.009. 
Zhang, J.Y., Zhou, Y.Q., Feng, Z.W., Fan, Y.N., Zeng, G.C., Wei, L., 2017. Randomized 
controlled trial of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) on posttraumatic 
growth of Chinese breast cancer survivors. Psychol. Health Med. 22 (1), 94–109. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/13548506.2016.1146405. 
Zhang, Q., Zhao, H., Zheng, Y., 2019. Effectiveness of mindfulness-based stress reduction 
(MBSR) on symptom variables and health-related quality of life in breast cancer 
patients-a systematic review and meta-analysis. Support. Care Cancer 27 (3), 
771–781. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00520-018-4570-x. 
Zick, S.M., Kruger, G., Harte, S., Sen, A., Harris, R.E., Pearce, C.L., 2021. Acupressure for 
Cancer-fatigue in Ovarian Cancer Survivor (AcuOva) Study: a community-based 
clinical trial study protocol examining the impact of self-acupressure on persistent 
cancer-related fatigue in ovarian cancer survivors. Contemp. Clin. Trials 107, 
106477. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cct.2021.106477. 
Zigmond, A., Snaith, R., 1983. The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta Psychiatr. 
Scand. 67 (6), 361–370. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0447.1983.tb09716.x. 
Q. Liu et al.</paragraph></page></document>