<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document><page number="1"><paragraph>© 2019 Liu et al. This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at https://www.dovepress.com/terms. 
php and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/). By accessing the work 
you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For 
permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php).
Cancer Management and Research 2019:11 467–474
Cancer Management and Research
Dovepress
submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com
Dovepress 
467
O R i g i n a l  R e s e a R C h
open access to scientific and medical research
Open Access Full Text Article
http://dx.doi.org/10.2147/CMAR.S183299
Mindfulness-based stress reduction in patients 
with differentiated thyroid cancer receiving 
radioactive iodine therapy: a randomized 
controlled trial
Tianji liu1,*  
Wenqi Zhang1,*  
shuai Xiao2  
lei Xu3  
Qiang Wen1  
lin Bai1  
Qingjie Ma1  
Bin Ji1
1Department of nuclear Medicine, 
China-Japan Union hospital of Jilin 
University, Changchun, Jilin, China; 
2Department of nursing, China-Japan 
Union hospital of Jilin University, 
Changchun, Jilin, China; 3Department 
of Psychology and neurology, 
China-Japan Union hospital of Jilin 
University, Changchun, Jilin, China
*These authors contributed equally to 
this work
Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate the efficacy of mindfulness-based stress 
reduction (MBSR) on health-related quality of life (QoL), depression, and anxiety in patients 
with differentiated thyroid cancer (DTC) receiving radioactive iodine therapy (RIT).
Patients and methods: A randomized controlled trial of MBSR with 120 DTC patients was 
performed. They were randomly assigned into the MBSR intervention group and usual care 
(UC) group. An 8-week MBSR program was administered to the MBSR group starting 8 weeks 
before RIT. Health-related QoL, depression, and anxiety were measured immediately before 
the start of MBSR (T1), immediately after RIT hospitalization was concluded (1 week after 
concluding the last MBSR session, T2), and 3 months after RIT hospitalization (T3), using the 
QoL Questionnaire Core 30 Items (QLQ-C30), Self-rating Depression Scale (SDS), and Self-
rating Anxiety Scale (SAS).
Results: Fifty-three patients in the UC group and 49 patients in the MBSR group completed 
the study and were analyzed. Both the UC and MBSR groups reported low QoL and high SDS 
and SAS scores immediately after RIT hospitalization. Patients randomly assigned to the MBSR 
group showed significantly greater improvements in emotional function (P=0.012, d=–0.03 
for T2 and d=1.17 for T3), fatigue (P=0.037, d=1.00 for T2 and d=–0.69 for T3), global QoL 
(P=0.015, d=1.61 for T2 and d=1.56 for T3), depression (P=0.027, d=–1.19 for T2 and d=–0.83 
for T3), and anxiety (P=0.043, d=–1.00 for T2 and d=–0.86 for T3).
Conclusion: An 8-week MBSR program significantly improved a wide range of scales in 
health-related QoL and mitigated depression and anxiety among DTC patients receiving RIT.
Keywords: mindfulness-based stress reduction, differentiated thyroid cancer, radioactive iodine 
therapy, quality of life, anxiety, depression
Introduction
Thyroid cancer, the most frequently occurring endocrine malignancy, is becoming 
increasingly prevalent worldwide and accounts for more deaths than all other endocrine 
cancers combined.1 In China, the incidence of thyroid cancer has increased five times 
during the past 10 years and is now ranking as the seventh most prevalent malignancy 
among all cancers.2 Differentiated thyroid cancer (DTC), which includes papillary 
and follicular histologies, accounts for 70%–90% of all thyroid cancers. According to 
the American Thyroid Association (ATA) guidelines, standard management of DTC 
includes surgical removal of thyroid gland (thyroidectomy) followed by radioactive 
iodine therapy (RIT) and thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) suppression therapy.3
Correspondence: Bin Ji; Qingjie Ma
Department of nuclear Medicine, China-
Japan Union hospital of Jilin University, 
nO.126 Xiantai street Changchun, Jilin, 
China 130033
Tel +86 431 8499 5196
email jibin1983104@163.com; 
maqingjiejlu@163.com
This article was published in the following Dove Medical Press journal:
Cancer Management and Research</paragraph></page><page number="2"><paragraph>Cancer Management and Research 2019:11
submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com
Dovepress 
Dovepress
468
liu et al
With an estimated overall 20-year relative survival rate 
of 95.4%, DTC is known to have a favorable prognosis upon 
effective treatment.4 However, in clinical practice, while 
patients were told they have the “good” cancer, this does 
not reflect their personal experience with this disease. For 
example, although RIT after thyroidectomy is associated 
with dramatic decreases in locoregional recurrences, distant 
metastasis, and disease-related mortality,5 patients receiv-
ing high-dose radioactive iodine still experience significant 
depression and anxiety associated with previous surgical 
complications (such as neck pain, dysphonia, and hypocal-
cemia), hormone withdrawal (causing a state of transient 
hypothyroidism symptoms such as fatigue, neurological 
deficiencies, and depression), fear of radiation, loneliness 
of isolation (being housed within radiation isolation wards), 
and side effect of radioactive iodine (such as swelling neck, 
sialadenitis, gastrointestinal symptoms, appetite loss, and 
insomnia).6
In modern medicine, psychological intervention has 
become an essential part of patient management. Mindfulness 
is a state of meditation that originated from Buddhist philoso-
phy. It can be defined as the awareness that emerges through 
paying attention on purpose, in the present moment, and 
nonjudgmentally to the unfolding of experience moment by 
moment.7 Mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) was 
introduced to psychological treatment in 1979 by Kabat-Zinn8 
to help patients cope with their stress, pain, and emotions. It 
is widely used in the field of clinical cancer on patients and 
has shown improvement in several psychosomatic problems, 
such as insomnia, stress, anxiety, and depression.9–11 How-
ever, to the best of our knowledge, no previous research has 
investigated the effects of MBSR on patients with thyroid 
cancer receiving RIT.
Therefore, the aim of this study was to explore whether 
MBSR intervention is effective in improving health-related 
quality of life (QoL) and reducing depression and anxiety in 
DTC patients receiving RIT.
Patients and methods
Patient inclusion
Patients were recruited from the Department of Nuclear Medi-
cine in China-Japan Union Hospital, Changchun, China, from 
September 2015 to June 2016. Inclusion criteria were as fol-
lows: 1) planning for RIT with a definitive total thyroidectomy 
record and pathological report; 2) patients from 18 years to 70 
years; 3) normal electrocardiography (ECG) and blood pres-
sure. Exclusion criteria included the following: 1) a history 
of RIT; 2) having metastasis to other organs; 3) having other 
types of cancer, cardiovascular diseases, endocrine diseases, or 
mental disorder; 4) declining to participate in this study. This 
study was approved by the local independent ethics commit-
tees and the institutional review boards of China-Japan Union 
Hospital, Changchun, China, and conducted in accordance 
with the Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent 
was obtained from all included patients.
Design and random assignment
This study was a two-arm randomized controlled trial. The 
sample size was estimated by G*Power version 3.1 program 
with a power (1–β) of 80% and a significance level of 5%. 
Using an effect size of 0.59 which was reported by related 
studies, we established that a minimum sample size of 94 
patients was required. Allowing for 20% loss to follow-up 
of sample, 120 patients were randomized 1:1 into the MBSR 
intervention group or the usual care (UC) group. The allo-
cation sequence was generated by random permuted block 
randomization (with a block size of 4) conducted using a 
computer-based system and concealed in sequentially num-
bered envelopes. Patients were blinded to study hypotheses 
and had no knowledge of the content of the group to which 
they were not assigned. The research staff were not blinded 
to the randomization or patient outcome. The UC group 
underwent admission education, medication guidance, 
isolation protection education, and discharge guidance, as 
they were conventionally performed for these patients. As 
for the MBSR group, we designed a timetable starting 8 
weeks before RIT hospitalization (Figure 1), after which 
they would become a radioactive source. For these patients, 
in addition to routine guidance, a brief overview of the 
MBSR program, emphasizing the 8-week session schedule, 
was given 8 weeks before RIT hospitalization. All sessions 
were based on the original 8-week MBSR program that was 
developed by Kabat-Zinn12 and were adjusted according to 
the corresponding conditions (Table 1). Each session also 
included group discussions and individual reports to create 
an interactive learning environment. The MBSR program was 
provided by a psychologist who was qualified in delivering 
mindfulness skills. Prior to the study, we also performed an 
8-week pilot feasibility MBSR program with eight patients. 
The pilot study was designed to help provide the psychologist 
practice in running the program under clinical supervision 
and to resolve any potential practical problems.
Data collection
The assessments were conducted at three time points, which 
were the initial baseline that was immediately before the</paragraph></page><page number="3"><paragraph>Cancer Management and Research 2019:11
submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com
Dovepress 
Dovepress
469
MBsR in DTC patients receiving radioactive iodine therapy
start of MBSR (T1), immediately after RIT hospitalization 
was concluded (T2), and 3 months after RIT hospitaliza-
tion (T3).
Qol questionnaire (QlQ)
QoL was assessed using the QoL Questionnaire Core 30 
Items (QLQ-C30) of the European Organization for Research 
and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC), which is a validated, 
self-reported, cancer-specific measure of QoL, with high 
Figure 1 The relationship of time schedule between RiT procedure and MBsR intervention.
Abbreviations: MBsR, mindfulness-based stress reduction; RiT, radioactive iodine therapy.
RIT schedule
Pre-RIT
RIT planning  
Thyroid hormone
withdrawal 
RIT and 
isolation
MBSR intervention schedule
Pre-
intervention
measures 
Sessions 1–3
Post-
intervention
measures 
Session 4 
Sessions 5–8
Week 4
Week 9
Table 1 Concise content of the 8-week MBsR program
Week 1
Content summary: MBsR theory, intervention process, and corresponding requirements were introduced to the patients in an easy-to-
understand manner. Mindful breathing training was explained and patients encouraged to practice it.
Week 2
Content summary: The meaning of sitting meditation, which emphasized breathing as a primary object of attention, was explained, and patients 
were guided to enter into and practice sitting meditation and nonjudgmental awareness of things with music being played at the same time.
Week 3
Content summary: Walking meditation and its key points were introduced to explore the relationship between motion and emotion. Patients 
were encouraged to expand their mindfulness practice to walking.
Week 4
Content summary: The meaning and requirements of body scan, which allows the body to experience the self-motion perception feedback of 
every part of the body, were explained, and patients were encouraged to practice it.
Week 5
Content summary: Yoga-based stretches, which included lying and standing postures, were taught. given that some patients’ upper limb 
movement might be compromised due to surgical brachial plexus damage, gentle and appropriate stretches were encouraged to suit their 
capability.
Week 6
Content summary: Mindfulness listening, thinking, and emotions were introduced, and patients were guided and encouraged to practice it.
Week 7
Content summary: nonjudgmental awareness was explained, and patients were encouraged to practice it with music played at the same time 
without being interrupted by the surrounding environment.
Week 8
Content summary: Patients were encouraged to internalize the practice sessions and develop a pattern suiting their personal situations. it was 
empathized that meditation was a useful method to maintain individual well-being and week 8 was the first week of being on their own to develop 
a lifetime program of MBsR.
Abbreviation: MBsR, mindfulness-based stress reduction.
functional scores and low symptom scores representing 
better functioning. It has been translated and validated in 
81 languages and is used in more than 3,000 studies world-
wide. It consists of five functional dimensions (eg, physical, 
emotional, cognitive, social, and role), three symptomatic 
dimensions (including pain, fatigue, and nausea), and other 
dimensions, such as insomnia, appetite, and economic bur-
den. The scoring has been linearly transformed to a 0–100 
scale according to the EORTC scoring manual.</paragraph></page><page number="4"><paragraph>Cancer Management and Research 2019:11
submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com
Dovepress 
Dovepress
470
liu et al
self-rating Depression scale (sDs) and 
self-rating anxiety scale (sas)
The level of depression and anxiety was assessed by the Zung 
SDS and the Zung SAS, respectively. Each scale contains 20 
items based on a 0–4 scale, with a higher score indicating a 
higher level of anxiety or depression. The possible range of 
scores was 0–80 for each scale.
statistical analyses
Statistical analysis was performed using MedCalc software 
(version 17.4.4; Broekstraat, Mariakerke, Belgium). Com-
parisons of categorical variables were performed with either 
chi-squared test or Fisher’s exact test as appropriate. Student’s 
t-test was used for normally distributed continuous variables, 
and the Mann–Whitney U test was used for non-normally 
distributed continuous variables. Linear mixed models were 
used to assess the interaction between patients’ assignment 
(UC group vs MBSR group) and time (T1, T2, and T3) in 
relation to QoL, SDS, and SAS scales, testing whether the 
rate of scale change varied by study assignment. Linear mixed 
models were also used to account for baseline differences. 
P&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate statistical significance 
for all analyses. Cohen’s d was calculated for the evaluation 
of effect size.
Results
Patients
Figure 2 shows an overview of the number of subjects who 
were randomized and retained. In total, 18 patients (15%) 
dropped out before the end of this study, resulting in 53 
patients in the UC group and 49 patients in the MBSR 
group for data analysis. The demographic information of the 
included patients is summarized in Table 2. There were no 
statistical differences in age, gender, marital status, residence, 
educational level, employment status, religion, TNM stage, 
and radioiodine dose between the two groups (all P&lt;0.05).
Linear mixed models were used to test the efficacy of 
MBSR on each QoL, SDS, and SAS. Descriptive data for 
each outcome are summarized in Table 3.
health-related Qol
Statistically significant QoL improvements were observed 
in patients in the MBSR group through the 3-month period. 
Patients randomly assigned to the MBSR group showed 
significantly greater improvements in emotional function 
(P=0.012, d=–0.03 for T2 and d=1.17 for T3), fatigue 
(P=0.037, d=1.00 for T2 and d=–0.69 for T3), and global 
QoL (P=0.015, d=1.61 for T2 and d=1.56 for T3).
sDs and sas
Patients randomly assigned to the MBSR group demonstrated 
greater scale improvement in depression (P=0.027, d=–1.19 
for T2 and d=–0.83 for T3) and anxiety (P=0.043, d=–1.00 
for T2 and d=–0.86 for T3).
Discussion
Our study was the first to explore the effects of MBSR on 
DTC patients receiving RIT. Important findings from this 
study include statistically significant improvements in emo-
tional function, fatigue, global QoL, depression, and anxiety 
scales after MBSR intervention compared with those after 
UC.
Usually several weeks ahead of RIT, DTC patients come 
to our department for RIT consultation and seek guidance 
Figure 2 Flow diagram of patient randomization and retention.
Abbreviations: MBsR, mindfulness-based stress reduction; UC, usual care.
Consenting participants were randomized (n=120)
Assigned to the UC group (n=60)
Assigned to the MBSR group (n=60)
Withdrawal from the study (n=3)
Withdrawal from the study (n=8)
Lost to follow-up at 3 months (n=4)
Lost to follow-up at 3 months (n=3)
Data analyzed (n=53)
Data analyzed (n=49)</paragraph></page><page number="5"><paragraph>Cancer Management and Research 2019:11
submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com
Dovepress 
Dovepress
471
MBsR in DTC patients receiving radioactive iodine therapy
Table 2 Comparison of demographic and clinical characteristics
 
MBSR intervention group (n=49)
UC group (n=53)
P-value
age, mean ± sD
43.32±10.99
42.38±12.60
0.6899
gender, n (%)
 
 
0.8307
Female
34
38
 
Male
15
15
 
Marital status, n (%)
 
 
0.7409
Married
35
37
 
single
4
6
 
Residence, n (%)
 
 
1.0000
Urban
34
37
 
Rural
15
16
 
educational level, n (%)
 
 
0.8354
Middle school or lower
16
19
 
high school or higher
33
34
 
employment status, n (%)
 
 
0.6960
employed
27
27
 
Unemployed
22
26
 
Religion, n (%)
 
 
0.6189
Yes
11
9
 
no
38
44
 
TnM stage, n (%)
 
 
0.7677
i
25
27
 
ii
8
7
 
iii
11
14
 
iV
5
6
 
Rai dose, mean ± sD
113.5±26.7
109.7±24.9
0.5870
Abbreviations: MBsR, mindfulness-based stress reduction; UC, usual care.
Table 3 Comparison of Qol, depression, and anxiety outcome across time points
Measurement
UC group
(n=53)
 
MBSR intervention  
group (n=49)
Between-groups effect size, 
adjusting for baseline
Mean
SD 
Mean
SD
Cohen’s d
Physical function
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
72.14
15.11
 
76.27
18.94
 
T2
67.34
11.65
 
74.61
17.96
0.21
T3
77.09
16.10
 
85.72
12.30
0.31
Role function
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
74.20
12.81
 
71.04
21.76
 
T2
58.55
11.86
 
68.40
12.79
1.17
T3
66.61
10.49
 
74.63
12.76
0.34
Emotional function
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
69.23
22.04
 
71.18
18.38
 
T2
51.93
14.62
 
63.49
13.78
–0.03
T3
56.57
16.10
 
74.12
9.50
1.17
P*
 
 
0.012
 
 
 
Cognitive function
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
71.00
19.62
 
73.69
16.30
 
T2
61.81
19.86
 
69.56
13.97
0.29
T3
70.62
18.25
 
77.81
16.30
0.26
Social function
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
65.22
23.71
 
63.77
24.95
 
T2
56.11
17.08
 
65.81
18.49
0.86
T3
62.05
14.34
 
74.35
17.68
0.63
(Continued)</paragraph></page><page number="6"><paragraph>Cancer Management and Research 2019:11
submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com
Dovepress 
Dovepress
472
liu et al
Measurement
UC group
(n=53)
 
MBSR intervention  
group (n=49)
Between-groups, effect size, 
adjusting for baseline
Mean
SD 
Mean
SD
Cohen’s d
Fatigue
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
18.67
12.24
 
20.51
11.32
 
T2
55.73
24.33
 
37.28
14.89
1.0
T3
30.99
20.45
 
22.95
12.01
–0.69
P*
 
 
0.037
 
 
 
Pain
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
21.67
19.15
 
23.10
17.08
 
T2
22.64
17.52
 
18.79
12.18
–0.35
T3
15.78
10.38
 
13.84
8.67
–0.55
Nausea and vomiting
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
4.83
6.77
 
5.04
6.80
 
T2
13.09
12.29
 
8.19
10.81
–0.44
T3
5.65
6.96
 
5.14
7.87
–0.09
Global QoL
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
69.54
15.27
 
66.61
10.85
 
T2
49.47
10.92
 
62.67
10.32
1.61
T3
56.95
10.03
 
72.33
13.36
1.56
P*
 
 
0.015
 
 
 
Dyspnea
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
16.64
16.25
 
15.87
13.00
 
T2
8.52
8.74
 
7.77
9.22
0.01
T3
7.97
8.02
 
7.91
6.93
0.10
Sleep disturbance
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
16.59
17.63
 
18.84
18.89
 
T2
43.55
19.60
 
26.34
15.91
–1.14
T3
19.28
16.40
 
13.30
11.76
–0.20
Appetite loss
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
11.74
15.21
 
10.27
13.56
 
T2
18.19
15.85
 
18.60
15.80
0.12
T3
19.31
19.34
 
16.07
9.80
–0.11
Constipation
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
18.24
16.01
 
19.18
13.83
 
T2
10.73
9.27
 
11.02
8.20
–0.07
T3
11.03
7.57
 
9.19
6.46
–0.39
Diarrhea
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
15.62
23.47
 
13.69
20.51
 
T2
15.73
20.14
 
10.44
12.96
–0.18
T3
7.94
8.06
 
5.77
5.60
–0.03
Finance impact
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
28.32
33.78
 
24.29
21.24
 
T2
38.26
30.75
 
33.23
21.64
0.03
T3
39.34
22.89
 
35.51
18.56
0.01
Self-rating depression
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
54.36
9.81
 
53.60
8.61
 
T2
73.64
11.22
 
60.52
9.73
–1.19
T3
62.64
12.27
 
46.31
8.05
–0.83
P*
 
 
0.027
 
 
 
Self-rating anxiety
 
 
 
 
 
 
T1 (baseline)
58.72
8.65
 
59.58
9.62
 
T2
77.37
14.50
 
65.24
11.08
–1.0
T3
60.44
10.83
 
48.97
9.82
–0.86
P*
 
 
0.043
 
 
 
Notes: *If the difference between UC group and MBSR intervention group is significant, the P value is provided in the middle column of the table. Ti, assessment immediately 
before the start of MBsR; T2, assessment immediately after RiT hospitalization is concluded; T3, assessment 3 months after RiT hospitalization.
Abbreviations: MBsR, mindfulness-based stress reduction; Qol, quality of life; UC, usual care.
Table 3 (Continued)</paragraph></page><page number="7"><paragraph>Cancer Management and Research 2019:11
submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com
Dovepress 
Dovepress
473
MBsR in DTC patients receiving radioactive iodine therapy
regarding thyroid hormone withdrawal, low iodine diet, and 
the time schedule. This leaves us plenty of time to communi-
cate with them. Recognizing the inadequacy of psychological 
support for these patients, we begin to think over what we 
could do to reduce their suffering in this period.
MBSR is now regarded as a well-established adjunctive 
treatment to assist well-being for medical patients in the USA. 
Since the introduction of this psychological intervention 
program to China, an increasing number of studies have been 
conducted to test its applicability in various patient groups 
such as breast cancer, chronic pain, and chronic insomnia. 
The results have been encouraging.13–15
In our study, most of the improvements in QoL, depres-
sion, and anxiety can be seen immediately after RIT hospi-
talization was concluded, when patients were experiencing 
the most negative impact of 4 weeks of thyroid hormone 
withdrawal, RIT-associated side effects, and isolation. Previ-
ous researchers have reported such changes in other types of 
cancers receiving MBSR program.9,16–19 However, we thought 
that the supportive interaction among the group members 
may also result in positive health effect. In this regard, future 
research might be needed to evaluate whether MBSR adds 
benefit over an active psychological treatment such as cog-
nitive behavior therapy (CBT), which could provide coping 
skills of a different type. Nonetheless, our results indicate 
that an 8-week schedule ahead of RIT hospitalization is 
applicable and effective for patients to cope with worsened 
QoL, depression, and anxiety in this period.
Three months after RIT, DTC patients began to recover 
from the panic and fear of the disease, as well as the damage 
caused by necessary medical treatment. However, we still 
observed significant benefits in the MBSR intervention group 
compared to the UC group at this time point. Parameters such 
as emotional function, fatigue, global QoL, depression, and 
anxiety were significantly better in the MBSR group than the 
UC group. The effect of MBSR on psychological aspect is 
more evident in this observation time point.
Two subscales (dyspnea and diarrhea) in QLQ-C30 recov-
ered significantly in both the UC and MBSR groups. This is 
due to the resumption of levothyroxine, which reverses the 
state of hypothyroidism and leads to less related symptoms. 
One subscale (appetite loss) continued to be high in the two 
observation time points in both the UC and MBSR groups. 
Appetite loss is a side effect from RIT. However, different 
from nausea and vomiting, which usually disappear 2 or 3 
days after RIT, it lasts for a very long period of time.20 Our 
results demonstrate that MBSR has no significant impact 
on this subscale within 3 months after RIT hospitalization.
There are some limitations to this study. First, although 
the study design is an RCT, this clinical trial was limited by a 
modest sample size. Further studies with larger study popula-
tion are required to confirm our results. Second, to understand 
the positive effect in patients receiving MBSR, 3-month point 
seems to be not enough and extended follow-up is needed. 
Third, because the study population was from one single hospi-
tal center, the results may not applicable to the general patients 
due to several DTC treatment strategies. Finally, we did not 
evaluate whether patients continuing practicing mindfulness 
after 3-month time point are benefitted. Because psychological 
intervention can improve the adherence of traditional treat-
ment, we anticipate that DTC patients might benefit from 
long-term MBSR, even in recurrence and survival. However, 
future studies are needed to confirm this assumption.
Conclusion
An 8-week MBSR program significantly improved a wide 
range of scales in health-related QoL and mitigated depres-
sion and anxiety among DTC patients receiving RIT.
Acknowledgment
We thank all the participating patients and the research nurses 
and staff for their efforts in completing this study.
Disclosure
The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.
References
 1. La Vecchia C, Malvezzi M, Bosetti C, et al. Thyroid cancer mortality 
and incidence: a global overview. Int J Cancer. 2015;136(9):2187–2195.
 2. Yang L, Zheng RS, Wang N, et al. Analysis of incidence and mortal-
ity of thyroid cancer in China, 2013. Zhonghua Zhong Liu Za Zhi. 
2017;39(11):862–867.
 3. Haugen BR, Alexander EK, Bible KC, et al. 2015 American thyroid 
association management guidelines for adult patients with thyroid 
nodules and differentiated thyroid cancer: the American Thyroid associa-
tion guidelines task force on thyroid nodules and differentiated thyroid 
cancer. Thyroid. 2016;26(1):1–133.
 4. Singer S, Lincke T, Gamper E, et al. Quality of life in patients with 
thyroid cancer compared with the general population. Thyroid. 
2012;22(2):117–124.
 5. Robbins RJ, Schlumberger MJ. The evolving role of (131)I for the treat-
ment of differentiated thyroid carcinoma. J Nucl Med. 2005;46(Suppl 
1):28S–37S.
 6. Lu L, Shan F, Li W, Lu H. Short-term side effects after radioiodine 
treatment in patients with differentiated thyroid cancer. Biomed Res 
Int. 2016;2016(9):1–5.
 7. Kabat-Zinn J. Mindfulness-based interventions in context: Past, 
present, and future. Clinical Psychology: Science and Practice. 
2006;10(2):144–156.
 8. Kabat-Zinn J. An outpatient program in behavioral medicine for chronic 
pain patients based on the practice of mindfulness meditation: theo-
retical considerations and preliminary results. Gen Hosp Psychiatry. 
1982;4(1):33–47.</paragraph></page><page number="8"><paragraph>Cancer Management and Research 2019:11
submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com
Dovepress 
Dovepress
Cancer Management and Research
Publish your work in this journal
Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/cancer-management-and-research-journal
Cancer Management and Research is an international, peer-reviewed 
open access journal focusing on cancer research and the optimal use of 
preventative and integrated treatment interventions to achieve improved 
outcomes, enhanced survival and quality of life for the cancer patient. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors.
Dovepress
474
liu et al
 9. Zhang MF, Wen YS, Liu WY, Peng LF, Wu XD, Liu QW. Effec-
tiveness of mindfulness-based therapy for reducing anxiety and 
depression in patients with cancer: A Meta-analysis. Medicine. 
2015;94(45):e0897–e0890.
 10. Anheyer D, Haller H, Barth J, Lauche R, Dobos G, Cramer H. Mind-
fulness-based stress reduction for treating low back pain: a systematic 
review and meta-analysis. Ann Intern Med. 2017;166(11):799–807.
 11. Lawrence M, Booth J, Mercer S, Crawford E. A systematic review of 
the benefits of mindfulness-based interventions following transient 
ischemic attack and stroke. Int J Stroke. 2013;8(6):465–474.
 12. Kabat-Zinn J. Bringing mindfulness to medicine: an interview with Jon 
Kabat-Zinn, PhD. Interview by Karolyn Gazella. Adv Mind Body Med. 
2005;21(2):22–27.
 13. Zhang JY, Zhou YQ, Feng ZW, Fan YN, Zeng GC, Wei L. Randomized 
controlled trial of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) on post-
traumatic growth of Chinese breast cancer survivors. Psychol Health 
Med. 2017;22(1):94–109.
 14. Zhang JX, Liu XH, Xie XH, et al. Mindfulness-based stress reduc-
tion for chronic insomnia in adults older than 75 years: a randomized, 
controlled, single-blind clinical trial. Explore. 2015;11(3):180–185.
 15. Wong SY. Effect of mindfulness-based stress reduction programme on 
pain and quality of life in chronic pain patients: a randomised controlled 
clinical trial. Hong Kong Med J. 2009;15(Suppl 6):13–14.
 16. Hoffman CJ, Ersser SJ, Hopkinson JB, Nicholls PG, Harrington JE, 
Thomas PW. Effectiveness of mindfulness-based stress reduction in 
mood, breast- and endocrine-related quality of life, and well-being in 
stage 0 to III breast cancer: a randomized, controlled trial. J Clin Oncol. 
2012;30(12):1335–1342.
 17. Pollard A, Burchell JL, Castle D, et al. Individualised mindfulness-
based stress reduction for head and neck cancer patients undergoing 
radiotherapy of curative intent: a descriptive pilot study. Eur J Cancer 
Care. 2017;26(2):e12474.
 18. Johns SA, Brown LF, Beck-Coon K, et al. Randomized controlled pilot 
trial of mindfulness-based stress reduction compared to psychoedu-
cational support for persistently fatigued breast and colorectal cancer 
survivors. Support Care Cancer. 2016;24(10):4085–4096.
 19. Schellekens MPJ, van den Hurk DGM, Prins JB, et al. Mindfulness-
based stress reduction added to care as usual for lung cancer patients 
and/or their partners: A multicentre randomized controlled trial. Psy-
chooncology. 2017;26(12):2118–2126.
 20. Florenzano P, Guarda FJ, Jaimovich R, Droppelmann N, González H, 
Domínguez JM. Radioactive iodine administration is associated with 
persistent related symptoms in patients with differentiated thyroid 
cancer. Int J Endocrinol. 2016;2016:1–6.</paragraph></page></document>