<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document><page number="1"><paragraph>227
© The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com
Japanese Journal of Clinical Oncology, 2022, 52(3)227–236
https://doi.org/10.1093/jjco/hyab198
Advance Access Publication Date: 28 January 2022
Original Article
Original Article
A randomized clinical trial of guided self-help
intervention based on mindfulness for patients
with hepatocellular carcinoma: effects and
mechanisms
Zengxia Liu1,2, Min Li3, Yong Jia1, Shuo Wang1, Lufang Zheng1,
Cong Wang1 and Li Chen
1,*
1School of Nursing, Jilin University, Changchun, 2School of Nursing, Changchun University of Chinese Medicine,
Changchun and 3Invasive Technology Department, The First Hospital of Jilin University, Changchun, China
*For reprints and all correspondence: Li Chen, Dean of School of Nursing, NO.965 Xinjiang Street, Changchun, Jilin 130021,
China. E-mail: chen_care@126.com
Received 12 August 2021; Editorial Decision 24 November 2021; Accepted 26 November 2021
Abstract
Background: Compared with face-to-face mindfulness-based interventions (MBIs), online mindful-
ness interventions may be more convenient for patients with limited resources and can provide self-
help mindfulness methods to improve the quality of life of cancer patients. This study investigated
the effects of guided self-help mindfulness-based interventions (GSH-MBIs) on psychological
distress, quality of life and sleep quality in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma and explored
the underlying mechanisms.
Methods: A total of 122 patients with hepatocellular carcinoma were randomly divided into the
intervention group or the conventional treatment group. Psychological distress, quality of life,
sleep quality, psychological ﬂexibility and perceived stress were evaluated in the groups before the
intervention at baseline, after the intervention, at 1-month follow-up and 3-month follow-up. The
intervention’s effects over time and the potential mediating effects were analysed using generalized
estimating equations (GEE).
Results: GEE results indicated signiﬁcant time–group interaction effects on psychological distress
(P &lt; 0.001) and sleep quality (P &lt; 0.001). The intervention signiﬁcantly improved psychological
ﬂexibility (β, −2.066; 95% CI, −3.631, −0.500) and reduced perceived stress (β, −2.639; 95%
CI, −4.110, −1.169). Psychological ﬂexibility and perceived stress played a mediating role in the
observed results.
Conclusion: GSH-MBIs can improve psychological distress and sleep quality via changing the
psychological ﬂexibility and perceived stress in hepatocellular carcinoma patients.
Key words: hepatocellular carcinoma, mindfulness-based intervention, self-help, psychological distress, sleep quality, quality of life
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page><page number="2"><paragraph>228
Mindfulness intervention for cancer patients
Introduction
Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the sixth most common cancer in
the world and the third leading cause of cancer-related death, after
lung cancer and colorectal cancer. HCC is characterized by severe
symptoms, rapid progression and poor prognosis (1). Approximately
900 000 new cases of HCC and ∼830 000 deaths related to HCC
were reported in 2020 worldwide (2). China is one of the countries
with the heaviest burden of HCC, as the number of HCC patients
in China accounts for more than half of the global HCC patients
(2). The level of distress is considerably increased in one-third of
HCC patients even in comparison to those with other kinds of
cancer (3). Anxiety and depression are two psychological distress
that are frequently reported by HCC patients (4,5). The combination
of psychological and physical issues reduce the quality of life of
HCC patients. Therefore, it is very important to reduce cancer-related
symptoms and improve mental health through effective psychologi-
cal interventions, but there is no clear knowledge about the effect
of psycho-oncological interventions in HCC patients (3). One study
included only a small number of HCC patients in the follow-up
assessment (6) The other study only reported clinically significant
trends in the intervention group (IG) of the study (7). Therefore, the
psycho-intervention effect on mental health of HCC patients is not
clearly clinically objectifiable.
Mindfulness is defined as the ability to observe thoughts, bodily
feelings or present feelings with an open and accepting attitude.
Mindfulness-based interventions (MBIs) teach participants to rec-
ognize habitual response patterns and focus more on their daily
lives (8,9). Several researchers have demonstrated the effectiveness of
MBIs in reducing psychological distress and improving the quality of
life of cancer patients (10,11). Most reviews demonstrated that mind-
fulness interventions can effectively reduce the psychological dis-
tress of cancer patients, including anxiety and depression symptoms
(12–14).
Although MBIs have potential benefits for relieving psychological
distress, cancer patients often cannot participate in psychotherapy
such as MBIs, as traditional MBIs require patients to participate in
classroom learning for several weeks (15,16). Physical fatigue and
discomfort caused by the side effects of anticancer treatments, the
stigma of cancer, limitations in transportation and the limited number
of professional psychotherapists makes cancer patient access to MBIs
difficult (17). MBIs delivered online have advantages as time-saving
and labour-saving interventions with privacy for patients. Therefore,
online MBIs are more popular with cancer patients compared with
face-to-face interventions (18). Some studies have also confirmed
the effectiveness of online MBIs. A meta-analysis by Spijkerman
et al. summarized 15 randomized clinical trials (RCTs) and found
that online MBIs have a positive impact on mental health out-
comes (19). However, some of these trials included non-clinical
participants, such as students or employees. A controlled trial of
64 cancer patients showed that online MBIs can effectively reduce
stress (20). Another uncontrolled trial of 167 cancer patients showed
that online MBIs significantly reduced fatigue and psychological
problems (21).
Guided self-help (GSH) is a form of self-managed and standard-
ized psychotherapy using books, manuals or media materials (such
as the Internet, audio or video) with which participants can conduct
psychotherapy independently at home. GSH can help participants
complete interventions through supportive or promotional methods,
which is different from other self-help methods (22,23). Some RCTs
have demonstrated the beneficial effects of GSH-based cognitive
behavioural therapy for psychological distress (24).
Several studies had investigated the efficacy of MBIs using self-
help approaches (25). A meta-analysis by Cavanagh et al. including
15 studies demonstrated that guided self-help mindfulness-based
interventions (GSH-MBIs) can benefit both healthy participants and
participants with physical and psychological distress. However, in
Cavanagh’s review, only four studies evaluated the effect of GSH-
MBIs, and no studies included cancer patients. Thus, the impact
of GSH-MBIs on cancer patients is still unclear (26). Fish et al.
conducted a systematic review of 10 studies on MBI support to
participants through technical platforms. However, a definitive con-
clusion on the effectiveness of online MBIs cannot be drawn due
to methodological differences in these studies (27). Toivonen et al.
summarized 16 studies in a systematic review and showed that online
MBIs are a practical choice for individuals with physical problems
(28). Shao et al. found that GSH-MBIs for patients with breast
cancer showed reductions in depression and sleep distress symptoms
compared with a wait-list control group (25).
To summarize, GSH-MBIs may have potential therapeutic effects
for cancer patients. The psycho-intervention effect on mental health
of HCC patients is not clearly. Further randomized controlled studies
of long-term intervention are needed to further investigate the effects
of psycho-oncological intervention on HCC patients (3). To date, no
study has evaluated the effects of GSH-MBIs on HCC patients. In
addition, the mechanism of GSH-MBIs is still poorly understood.
Psychological flexibility refers to the ability to fully accept present
thoughts, feelings and experiences with no evading, persisting or
change behaviour to align with goals and values (29). The therapeutic
activity of mindfulness is thought to occur through awareness and
attention. Meditation training increases the ability for self-regulation
of emotions and thoughts and improving psychological flexibility
(30). Previous research has shown that MBIs can improve psycholog-
ical flexibility and reduce perceived stress (31). However, the effect
of GSH-MBIs on psychological flexibility and perceived stress and
their role in reducing psychological distress are not yet clear.
In this study, we evaluated the impact of GSH-MBIs on the
psychological symptoms of HCC patients. The primary objective
was to investigate the effectiveness of 6-week GSH-MBIs on
HCC patients immediately after the intervention and at follow-
up timepoints. The first aim was to test the effectiveness of GSH-
MBIs on primary outcome of psychological distress and secondary
outcomes of quality of life and sleep quality. To better understand the
mechanism of GSH-MBI interventions, the secondary objective was
to investigate the mediator of psychological flexibility and perceived
stress on these outcomes.
Methods
Trial design
From November 2019 to May 2021, the RCT was conducted at the
First Hospital of Jilin University, China. Potential participants were
identified through patient medical records. Patients were evaluated
and screened; patients were invited to the study if they met the
inclusion criteria. After providing informed consent, the subjects
completed the baseline questionnaire (at T0) and then were randomly
assigned to the IG or the waiting control group. Participants com-
pleted a questionnaire after 6 weeks of intervention (T1) and at the
follow-ups at 1 month (T2) and 3 months (T3).
Randomization
After completing informed consent, screening, and baseline assess-
ments, eligible participants were then randomized by an independent
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page><page number="3"><paragraph>Jpn J Clin Oncol, 2022, Vol. 52, No. 3
229
research assistant who was not affiliated with the trial. Random-
ization was determined using Research Randomizer (version 4.0)
(32), which generated a list of random numbers representing the
participants and allocated them to the IG or the waiting control
group. The outcome assessors were masked to the participant’s group
allocation.
Participants
The inclusion criteria were as follows: (i) age ≥ 18 years; (ii) diagnosis
of HCC as an inpatient; (iii) no history of other malignancies; (iv)
able to operate a smartphone and frequent WeChat (a widely used
instant-messaging application in China) usage (&gt;5 times per week);
and (v) able to read, write and speak Chinese. The exclusion criteria
were as follows: (i) a concurrent diagnosis of other tumour types or
psychiatric distress; (ii) treatment with any psychotropic medications,
such as antidepressants, antipsychotics, mood stabilizers, narcotics
and benzodiazepines, any prescription for insomnia or any other
antidepressive therapies during the study period; and (iii) previously
received mindfulness intervention. The diagnosis of HCC was based
on the European Association for the Study of the Liver (EASL)
criteria and included histopathologic confirmation (33), positive
lesion detection by at least two different imaging techniques, or
positive lesion detection by one imaging technique combined with
α-fetoprotein (AFP) &gt; 400 ng/ml. The imaging techniques included
transabdominal ultrasonography, angiography, computed tomogra-
phy and magnetic resonance imaging.
Sample size
A sample size of 61 was selected to gain enough statistical power for
subsequent analyses. This was based on previous post-intervention
Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) scores of patients
with cancer who received online mindfulness intervention (mean,
11.87; standard deviation [SD], 6.16) compared with those who had
not received it (mean, 16.37; SD, 6.50). With 80% power and 5%
type I error, we estimated that at least 44 participants were required
in each group. To achieve these numbers, and allowing for a 27%
dropout, we calculated that 61 participants were needed for each
group (34).
Intervention
GSH-MBIs of 6-week duration were applied in the IG. The interven-
tions were based on Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction designed
by Kabat-Zinn et al. and Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy
designed by Segal et al. (35,36). and was adapted for patients
with HCC, which were developed by the research team. The team
consisted of four experienced clinical psychologists. Interventions
instructed principles and attitudes of mindfulness, guided the partici-
pants to focus on the present moment, and taught participants how to
practice non-judgement during intense experiences, which may come
from physical and psychological events or the external environment.
Both guidance and home practice were used in the GSH-MBIs. The
guidance included eight 20-minutes audio files. According to the
physical condition of HCC patients, the guidance retained the core
elements of mindfulness such as breath awareness, body scanning
and awareness of pleasant and unpleasant events. At the same time,
according to the main problems and demands of HCC patients, emo-
tion (depression, anxiety) and symptom management (pain, insom-
nia) were added into the guidance. Home practice included three key
exercises: breathing sense, body inspection and awareness of pleasant
and unpleasant moods. Participants were required to conduct home
practices based on the provided audio and practice 20 min each day
and 5 days weekly for six consecutive weeks.
Before the start of the intervention, the psychologist scheduled
a pre-intervention personal interview with each participant to intro-
duce this intervention, explain training recommendations and answer
any questions. Patients were asked to attempt this intervention before
discharge and provide feedback to the instructor so that they could
practice correctly. Each participant was provided with a manual
containing instruction and guidance of this intervention and was
asked to read it carefully to gain a better understanding of our
intervention.
Participants were supervised and reminded to practice by the ther-
apists everyday by WeChat, including personal guidance, answering
questions and family practice feedback. After intervention, the partic-
ipants completed one question: ‘How many days have you listened
to the audio and mindfulness practice during the intervention?’ If
participants had completed 20 days during the intervention period,
they were considered adherent.
Waiting list group
Patients in the control group were given routine care, including
health education and routine nursing guidance. After the study, these
participants were introduced to the program and were provided with
the audio and materials of the intervention.
Outcome measures
Demographics. Demographic and clinical characteristics, including
basic demographic sociological information (age, gender, residence
location, education level, occupation, spouse or absence, family
economic condition) and clinical diseases (hepatic function classifi-
cation) were collected.
Psychological distress. The HADS was used to measure psychological
distress. The HADS was developed by Zigmond et al. (37) and is
mainly used to assess the anxiety and depression of general patients.
The HADS has been extensively validated in clinical practice (38)
and is also suitable for cancer patients (39). The scale has 14 items,
including the anxiety subscale (7 items) and the depression subscale
(7 items). Each item is scored from 0 to 3 points, and the total score
ranges from 0 to 42 points. A higher score indicates a higher anxiety
and depression level. For the HADS scale, the test–retest reliability is
0.945, Cronbach’s α is 0.879, and the criterion validity and construct
validity are also good (P &lt; 0.001) (40).
Sleep quality. Sleep quality was assessed by the Pittsburgh Sleep
Quality Index (PSQI), which was compiled by Buysse et al. (41) and
is currently the most widely used method for assessing sleep quality
worldwide. The PSQI is used to assess the subjective sleep quality of
an individual in the past month. It contains 19 items and is divided
into seven dimensions: subjective sleep quality, time to fall asleep,
sleep time, sleep efficiency, sleep disturbance, sleep medication use
and daytime function. A higher score indicates a worse sleep quality.
A total score &gt;5 indicates poor sleep quality. For this scale, the test–
retest reliability is 0.994, Cronbach’s α is 0.845, and the discriminant
validity and construct validity are also good (P &lt; 0.001) (42).
Quality of life. Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Hepatobil-
iary Carcinoma (FACT-Hep) was used to measure quality of life.
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page><page number="4"><paragraph>230
Mindfulness intervention for cancer patients
The FACT-Hep is a targeted measurement of the quality of life of
patients with hepatobiliary carcinoma and is the most internationally
recognized, comprehensive and commonly used assessment tool for
the quality of life of patients with hepatobiliary cancer. It consists
of 46 items and five dimensions. A higher score indicates a better
quality of life of the patient. For this scale, the test–retest reliability
is 0.330–0.953, Cronbach’s α is 0.916, and the content validity and
construct validity are also good (P &lt; 0.001) (43).
Perceived stress. The Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) was used to assess
the level of perceived stress. The scale, developed by Cohen et al. (44),
includes 14 items to access the subjective stress of the individual;
each item uses a 5-level scoring method (0–4 points). The total score
is determined as the sum of the scores of each item. A higher score
indicates a greater perceived stress. For the PSS scale, the test–retest
reliability is 0.89, Cronbach’s α is 0.78, and the discriminant validity
and construct validity are also good (P &lt; 0.001) (45).
Psychological flexibility. Psychological flexibility in this study was
measured by the Acceptance and Action Questionnaire-second Edi-
tion (AAQ-II), with a total of seven items, that examined empirical
avoidance, a negative emotion regulation strategy. A higher score
indicated a higher empirical avoidance and lower psychological
flexibility. For the AAQ-II scale, the test–retest reliability is 0.80,
Cronbach’s α is 0.88, and the criterion validity and construct validity
are also good (P &lt; 0.01) (46).
Ethical considerations. The protocol and principles of this study were
conducted under the guidelines of the Declaration of Helsinki. This
study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the School of
Nursing of Jilin University (ID#2019112001) and was registered
in the Chinese Clinical Trial Registry (ChiCTR1900027976). All
patients provided written informed consent prior to the study and
were allowed to stop participating at any time.
Statistical analysis
The distribution of data was tested using the Shapiro–Wilk test,
where continuous variables that conformed to the normal distri-
bution were described with means and SD, and those that did not
conform to the normal distribution were described with medians
and quartiles. Frequency and percentage were used for categorical
variables. Baseline characteristics of the intervention and control
groups were compared using independent t-tests, nonparametric tests
or χ 2 test. To measure the outcomes over time, generalized estimated
equation (GEE) models with an unstructured correlation matrix were
fitted. The threshold for significance was set at α = 0.05. Intention-
to-treat analysis method was used to analyse the data so that all
randomly assigned subjects remained in the assigned corresponding
group; the data of the missing part were analysed by the last observa-
tion value carry forward method. Statistical analysis was conducted
using SPSS, version 22.0 for Windows (IBM Corporation).
Results
Baseline characteristics of participants
Among the 332 patients that were initially recruited, 122 patients
met the eligibility criteria and agreed to participate in the study.
Among the 122 patients, 61 patients were randomized into the IG
and 61 were randomized into the control group (CG) At the end of
the intervention, 15 were lost in the IG and 13 were lost in the CG,
leaving 93 participants that completed the assessment. There was no
statistically significant difference in the lost participants between the
two groups (P &gt; 0.05), as shown in Figure 1.
The age range of the participants in the overall group was 36–
70 years old (average ± SD, 55.69 ± 8.30 years). The demographic
and clinical data of the IG were not statistically different from those
of the CG (P &gt; 0.05), as shown in Table 1.
The effect of the intervention on outcomes
The home practice time in the IG ranged from 10 to 32 days
(22.35 ± 4.11 days). Participants that practiced for 21 days were
defined as showing persistence. The compliance rate of this study
was 74.2%. Comparisons of outcomes between the intervention and
CGs are presented in Table 2. Figure 2 shows a visual representation
of the changing trend. Regarding the results from the GEE analysis
results, the interaction effects of group-by-time were significant on
psychological distress and sleep quality (P &lt; 0.001). Regarding
the results of intragroup comparisons, we could see that in the
IG, the scores of HADS and PSQI were significantly lower at T1
(HADS: P &lt; 0.001; PSQI: P &lt; 0.001), T2 (HADS: P &lt; 0.001; PSQI:
P &lt; 0.001) as well as T3 (HADS: P &lt; 0.001; PSQI: P = 0.007)
compared with those at the baseline; the FACT-Hep scores were
markedly higher compared with baseline at T1 (P = 0.015) and T2
(P = 0.044); whereas in the CG, the scores at T1,T2 andT3 were not
significantly different from those at the baseline for all the outcomes
(P &gt; 0.051). Intergroup comparisons at T1, displayed a significantly
lower HADS score in the IG (11.97 ± 2.88) compared with the CG
(13.74 ± 4.73; P = 0.012), and PSQI score in IG (9.11 ± 2.85)
compared with CG (10.52 ± 3.02; P = 0.007). However, FACT-Hep
score (IG: 123.45 ± 12.91; CG: 121.29 ± 15.59; P = 0.402), was
not significantly different between the two groups. At T2, the trend
persisted with significantly lower HADS scores in IG compared with
CG (IG: 12.03 ± 2.73; CG: 13.85 ± 4.50; P = 0.006), and PSQI
scores in IG compared with CG (IG: 9.03 ± 2.83; CG: 10.54 ± 2.95;
P = 0.004). Like T1, at T2, FACT-Hep scores (IG: 123.38 ± 13.06;
CG: 120.62 ± 15.31; P = 0.281), were still remained insignificant
between the two groups at T2. At T3, the trend persisted with
significantly lower HADS scores in IG compared with CG (IG:
11.95 ± 2.85; CG: 14.11 ± 4.26; P = 0.001), and PSQI scores in IG
compared with CG (IG: 9.21 ± 2.67; CG: 10.56 ± 2.71; P = 0.005).
Like T1 and T2, at T3, FACT-Hep scores (IG: 123.18 ± 12.25;
CG: 120.18 ± 14.76; P = 0.218), were still remained insignificant
between the two groups at T3.
The effect of the intervention on mediators
The GEE model was used to analyse the influence of the intervention
on psychological flexibility and perceived stress. The differences of
scores at different times were significant (P &lt; 0.05). The results
showed that the intervention significantly improved psychological
flexibility (β, −2.639; 95% CI, −4.110, −1.169) and reduced per-
ceived stress (β, −2.066; 95% CI, −3.631, −0.500).
Mediation analysis
In this study the causal step model proposed by Baron and Kenny was
followed to test the mediation effect (47). Firstly, we tested whether
the effect of the intervention on the outcome variable (psychological
distress and sleep quality) was significant. GEE analysis showed
that the intervention reduced psychological distress as well as sleep
problems; then we tested whether the effect of the intervention
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page><page number="5"><paragraph>Jpn J Clin Oncol, 2022, Vol. 52, No. 3
231
Figure 1. Flowchart showing recruitment and dropout of participants.
on the mediating variable (psychological flexibility and perceived
stress) was significant, GEE analysis showed that the intervention
reduced empirical avoidance and perceived stress. Finally, the effect
of intervention and mediating variables on outcome variables was
considered in the model simultaneously, and we tested whether the
effect of the mediating variable on outcome variables was significant.
If it was significant, it indicated that the mediation effect is signif-
icant. At the same time, we tested whether the intervention has a
significant effect on the outcome variable after controlling for the
mediating variables.
We added time, group and their interaction, as well as mediator
variables, to the model, and the results showed that the effect
of psychological flexibility and perceived stress on psychological
distress was significant. The effect of intervention on psychological
distress was still significant after controlling for the mediating vari-
ables, indicating a mediating role for psychological flexibility and
perceived stress on psychological distress. The results also showed
that the effect of perceived stress on sleep quality was signifi-
cant. The effect of intervention on psychological distress was non-
significant after controlling for the mediating variables, indicating a
complete mediating role for perceived stress on psychological distress
(Table 3).
Discussion
To our knowledge, this is the first randomized controlled trial of
GSH-MBIs in HCC patients. Our results showed that GSH-MBIs sig-
nificantly reduced the severity of psychological distress and improved
sleep quality in HCC patients. The 1-month and 3-month follow-
up data showed that the improvements in terms of depression and
sleep quality in the IG was continued at 1 month and 3 months
after treatment. An improvement of the quality of life after the
intervention was observed, but without statistical significance, which
might be related to the changes of the quality of life of cancer patients
reported in the previous study (34). The mediation analysis revealed
the possible psychological mechanism of GSH-MBIs. The results
suggested that changes in psychological flexibility and perceived
stress in HCC patients mediate the changes in psychological distress
and sleep quality after the intervention.
The post-intervention effect sizes for psychological distress found
in our study are smaller than the effect in another previous study of
online MBIs in cancer patients (34). When comparing the results,
between study differences in participant selection procedures should
be noted. Although relatively high-distress level cutoffs were applied
in the previous study, HADS scores ≥11, the present study used a
lower cutoff, which could have introduced floor effects. One solution
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page><page number="6"><paragraph>232
Mindfulness intervention for cancer patients
Table 1. Demographics and medical characteristics of participants at baseline, n = 122
Variables
No.(%)
t-test or chi-square test
P
Intervention Group, n = 61
Control Group, n = 61
Age:
Mean ± SD, years
54.36 ± 8.46
57.02 ± 8.00
–1.78
0.077
Gender
Male
Female
46(75.4)
15(24.6)
48(78.7)
13(21.3)
0.19
0.67
Relationship status
Married
53(86.9)
55(90.2)
0.323
0.57
Divorced/widowed
8(13.1)
6(9.8)
Education
Primary school or below
Junior high school
Senior high school
College or higher
12(19.7)
28(45.9)
16(26.2)
5(8.2)
11(18.0)
28(45.9)
14(23.0)
8(13.1)
0.87
0.83
Residence
City
Noncity
32(52.5)
29(47.5)
36(59.0)
25(41.0)
0.53
0.466
Employment state
Employed
Unemployed
29(47.5)
32(52.5)
33(54.1)
28(45.9)
0.525
0.469
Average monthly income
≤4000yuan
4001–8000yuan
&gt;8000yuan
29(47.5)
24(39.3)
8(13.1)
22(36.1)
30(49.2)
9(14.8)
1.69
0.43
Child-Pugh
Class A
Class B
Class C
47(77.0)
13(21.3)
1(1.6)
40(65.6)
19(31.1)
2(3.3)
2.04
0.36
for including the patients most likely to benefit could be a more
comprehensive screening procedure or a higher cutoff when screening
patients.
Our research further verified the effects of GSH-MBIs on cancer
patients (17,25,34). To our knowledge, it is the first study to evaluate
the effects of GSH-MBIs on HCC patients. Approximately 50% of
HCC patients suffered from depression (48), and this study provides
a new method to reduce the depression of HCC patients. Compared
with traditional group-based MBIs, GSH-MBIs are more suitable
in developing countries with limited psychology resources. GSH-
MBIs can provide HCC patients with audio and files for mind-
fulness learning and practice through WeChat, and at the same
time, professionals can keep in touch with patients through online
platforms. Compared with face-to-face methods, GSH-MBIs greatly
reduce medical expenses (49). HCC cancer patients generally suffer
from physical symptoms such as fatigue and pain,HCC patients often
suffer from physical symptoms such as fatigue and pain, as well as
limited mobility (50), this method has increased the feasibility of
obtaining mental health care and ensured the privacy of patients.
The loss rate during follow-up in this study (34%) was higher
than other RCTs of face-to-face mindfulness interventions (34,51).
Among the study dropouts, 43% of the participants responded
having no time to complete courses and practice because of work
and housework, 24% did not give any reason, 14% did not continue
because of physical discomfort and fatigue, 10% of the drop-out
participants thought that the course content had no effects and 10%
thought that the evaluation was tedious. Based on these reasons,
we concluded that the obstacles to completing this study were
mainly from other daily tasks, physical discomfort and the burden
of assessment, rather than the course content or duration. These
observations suggest that GSH-MBIs are suitable for patients with
a higher willingness to participate, free time and relatively mild
disease.
We also investigated the mediating role of GSH-MBIs and showed
that psychological flexibility and perceived stress influenced the
symptoms of psychological distress and sleep quality. The findings
demonstrated that psychological flexibility was an important media-
tor of stress and emotion in cancer patients (31,52). There is empirical
avoidance with low psychological flexibility, which is character-
ized by trying to change or avoid unwanted thoughts and feelings.
The usual response to negative thoughts and feelings is avoidance
(53). Mindfulness practice improves participants’ concentration and
awareness, self-regulation of pain, mental flexibility and reduced
psychological pressure (54).
Limitations
This study has several limitations, First, the collected data are all
self-reports, and the accuracy of reports could not be confirmed. In
future studies, more advanced techniques will be used to record the
practice time of participants. Second, these samples were recruited
in a tertiary hospital, which limited the conclusions on the effects
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page><page number="7"><paragraph>Jpn J Clin Oncol, 2022, Vol. 52, No. 3
233
Table 2. Model effect estimation using generalized estimated equations based on the intention-to-treat sample, n = 122
Out-
come
Inter-
ven-
tion
Group
Con-
trol
Group
Intergroup comparisons
Linear mixed-effects model (P-value)
Change from baseline (95% CI)
Effect Size
95% CI
Group
Time
Group×time
Intervention Group
Control Group
HADS
0.039∗
0.009∗∗
&lt;0.001∗∗∗
T0
13.89 ± 4.67
13.64 ± 4.65
0.05
0.25(−1.39, 1.89)
—
—
T1
11.97 ± 2.88
13.74 ± 4.73
–0.45
−1.77(−3.15, −0.39)∗
−1.92(−2.82, −1.02)∗∗∗
0.10(−0.44, 0.64)
T2
12.03 ± 2.73
13.85 ± 4.50
–0.49
−1.82(−3.13, −0.51)∗∗
−1.85(−2.82, −0.89)∗∗∗
0.21(−0.28, 0.71)
T3
11.95 ± 2.85
14.11 ± 4.26
–0.60
−2.16(−3.44, −0.89)∗∗
−1.93(−2.82, −1.04)∗∗∗
0.48(−0.05, 1.00)
FACT-Hep
0.393
0.054
0.214
T0
121.57 ± 16.16
120.78 ± 15.53
0.05
0.79(−4.79, 6.37)
—
—
T1
123.45 ± 12.91
121.29 ± 15.59
0.15
2.15(−2.88, 7.19)
1.88(0.36, 3.39)∗
0.51(−0.47, 1.49)
T2
123.38 ± 13.06
120.62 ± 15.31
0.19
2.75(−2.25, 7.76)
1.80(0.05, 3.56)∗
−0.16(−1.09, 0.77)
T3
123.18 ± 12.25
120.18 ± 14.76
0.22
3.00(−1.77, 7.78)
1.61(−0.17, 3.39)
0.0.60(−1.80, 0.60)
PSQI
0.019∗
0.005∗∗
&lt;0.001∗∗∗
T0
9.74 ± 3.31
10.36 ± 3.29
–0.19
−0.63(−1.79, 0.53)
—
—
T1
9.11 ± 2.85
10.52 ± 3.02
–0.55
−1.41(−2.44, −0.38)∗∗
−0.62(−0.88, −0.36)∗∗∗
0.16(0.00, 0.32)
T2
9.03 ± 2.83
10.54 ± 2.95
–0.60
−1.51(−2.52, −0.49)∗∗
−0.70(−0.97, −0.44)∗∗∗
0.18(−0.06, 0.41)
T3
9.21 ± 2.67
10.56 ± 2.71
–0.57
−1.34(−2.29, −0.40)∗∗
−.52(−0.91, −0.14)∗∗
0.19(−0.16, 0.55)
Note: The scores of scales were presented as means ± standard deviations.
∗P &lt; 0.05.
∗∗P &lt; 0.01.
∗∗∗P &lt; 0.001.
Abbreviations: HADS, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale; FACT-Hep, Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Hepatobiliary Carcinoma; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; T0, time 0 (baseline); T1, time 1
(post-intervention); T2, time 2 (1-month follow-up); T3, time 3 (3-month follow-up).
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page><page number="8"><paragraph>234
Mindfulness intervention for cancer patients
Figure 2. The change trends of outcomes in intervention and control groups over time. Abbreviations: CG, Control Group; IG, Intervention Group; HADS, Hospital
Anxiety and Depression Scale; FACT-Hep, Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Hepatobiliary Carcinoma; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index. T0, time 0
(baseline); T1, time 1 (post-intervention); T2, time 2 (1-month follow-up); T3, time 3 (3-month follow-up). Error bars represent 95% conﬁdence intervals.
Table 3. Model effect estimation using generalized estimated equations, n = 122
Outcome
waldχ2
Degree of freedom
P
Difference of marginal means (95% CI)
HADS
Group
0.01
1
0.918
0.04(−0.71, 0.79)
Time
0.59
1
0.443
0.20(−0.31, 0.71)
Time×group
10.05
1
0.002
−1.66(−2.68, −0.63)
Psychological flexibility
13.53
1
&lt;0.001
0.15(0.07, 0.23)
Perceived stress
64.01
1
&lt;0.001
0.28(0.21, 0.35)
PSQI
Group
2.30
1
.129
0.67(−0.20, 1.54)
Time
0.09
1
0.763
0.03(−0.17, 0.23)
Time×group
2.13
1
0.144
−0.29 (−0.69, 0.10)
Psychological flexibility
3.09
1
0.079
0.07(−0.01, 0.14)
Perceived stress
20.103
1
&lt;0.001
0.15(0.09, 0.22)
Abbreviations: HADS, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.
and mechanisms of the intervention. Third, this study did not col-
lect information on the time that the participants were in contact
with researchers and with social exposure. Future research should
consider social support and other factors. Finally, a high drop-
out rate was observed in this study, especially at the beginning
of intervention, which could indicate insufficient recruitment and
information procedures. It could be that this type of intervention
does not fully meet the needs, expectations and skills of the target
population. Participants completed baseline assessments prior to
randomization, but additional in-depth assessment of motivation and
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page><page number="9"><paragraph>Jpn J Clin Oncol, 2022, Vol. 52, No. 3
235
internet literacy prior to intervention start could have been relevant.
Intervention dropout could possibly be improved by the delivery
mode of GSH-MBIs.
Conclusion
In summary, GSH-MBIs can significantly improve the psychological
distress of HCC patients, which was mediated by psychological
flexibility and perceived stress. Simultaneously, we also found that
GSH-MBIs can improve the sleep quality of HCC patients. Using
easy and innovative technology, participants can easily learn and
practice, and professionals can provide support. The study verified
the advantages of GSH-MBIs, such as high efficiency, low cost, low
intensity, easy access and anonymity, and also proved its effects on
HCC patients, and provided for larger scale experimental research
on GSH-MBIs in the treatment of HCC patients.
Acknowledgements
We would like to thank all participants and researchers for their cooperation.
No funding was received for this study.
Conﬂicts of interest statement
None declared.
References
1. Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, Laversanne M, Soerjomataram I, Jemal A, Bray
F. Global cancer statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and
mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin
2021;71:209–49.
2. Llovet JM, Kelley RK, Villanueva A, et al. Hepatocellular carcinoma. Nat
Rev Dis Primers 2021;7:6.
3. Graf J, Stengel A. Psychological burden and psycho-oncological interven-
tions for patients with hepatobiliary cancers-a systematic review. Front
Psychol 2021;12:662777.
4. Zhong GC, Liu Y, Chen N, et al. Reproductive factors, menopausal
hormone therapies and primary liver cancer risk: a systematic review
and dose-response meta-analysis of observational studies. Hum Reprod
Update 2016;23:126–38.
5. Wang Y, O’Connor M, Xu Y, Liu X. Symptom clusters in Chinese patients
with primary liver cancer. Oncol Nurs Forum 2012;39:E468–79.
6. Küchler T, Bestmann B, Rappat S, Henne-Bruns D, Wood-Dauphinee S.
Impact of psychotherapeutic support for patients with gastrointestinal
cancer undergoing surgery: 10-year survival results of a randomized trial.
J Clin Oncol 2007;25:2702–8.
7. Steel JL, Nadeau K, Olek M, Carr BI. Preliminary results of an individually
tailored psychosocial intervention for patients with advanced hepatobil-
iary carcinoma. J Psychosoc Oncol 2007;25:19–42.
8. Deng G, Cassileth B. Complementary or alternative medicine in cancer
care-myths and realities. Nat Rev Clin Oncol 2013;10:656–64.
9. Elkins G, Fisher W, Johnson A. Mind-body therapies in integrative oncol-
ogy. Curr Treat Options Oncol 2010;11:128–40.
10. Zainal NZ, Booth S, Huppert FA. The efficacy of mindfulness-based stress
reduction on mental health of breast cancer patients: a meta-analysis.
Psychooncology 2013;22:1457–65.
11. Rouleau CR, Garland SN, Carlson LE. The impact of mindfulness-based
interventions on symptom burden, positive psychological outcomes, and
biomarkers in cancer patients. Cancer Manag Res 2015;7:121–31.
12. Cillessen L, Johannsen M, Speckens AEM, Zachariae R. Mindfulness-
based interventions for psychological and physical health outcomes in
cancer patients and survivors: a systematic review and meta-analysis of
randomized controlled trials. Psychooncology 2019;28:2257–69.
13. Xunlin NG, Lau Y, Klainin-Yobas P. The effectiveness of mindfulness-
based interventions among cancer patients and survivors: a systematic
review and meta-analysis. Support Care Cancer 2020;28:1563–78.
14. Piet J, Würtzen H, Zachariae R. The effect of mindfulness-based therapy
on symptoms of anxiety and depression in adult cancer patients and
survivors: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Consult Clin Psychol
2012;80:1007–20.
15. Wang JW, Shen Q, Ding N, et al. A qualitative exploration of the
unmet psychosocial rehabilitation needs of cancer survivors in China.
Psychooncology 2016;25:905–12.
16. Jacobsen PB, Jim HS. Psychosocial interventions for anxiety and depres-
sion in adult cancer patients: achievements and challenges. CA Cancer J
Clin 2008;58:214–30.
17. Zernicke KA, Campbell TS, Speca M, McCabe-Ruff K, Flowers S, Carlson
LE. A randomized wait-list controlled trial of feasibility and efficacy of
an online mindfulness-based cancer recovery program: the eTherapy for
cancer applying mindfulness trial. Psychosom Med 2014;76:257–67.
18. Brebach R, Sharpe L, Costa DS, Rhodes P, Butow P. Psychologi-
cal intervention targeting distress for cancer patients: a meta-analytic
study investigating uptake and adherence. Psychooncology 2016;25:
882–90.
19. Spijkerman MP, Pots WT, Bohlmeijer ET. Effectiveness of online
mindfulness-based interventions in improving mental health: a review
and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. Clin Psychol Rev
2016;45:102–14.
20. Zernicke KA, Campbell TS, Speca M, McCabe-Ruff K, Flowers S, Dirkse
DA, Carlson LE. The eCALM trial-eTherapy for cancer appLying mindful-
ness: online mindfulness-based cancer recovery program for underserved
individuals living with cancer in Alberta: protocol development for a
randomized wait-list controlled clinical trial. BMC Complement Altern
Med 2013;13:34.
21. Bruggeman-Everts FZ, Wolvers MDJ, van de Schoot R, Vollenbroek-
Hutten MMR, van der Lee ML. Effectiveness of two web-based inter-
ventions for chronic cancer-related fatigue compared to an active control
condition: results of the "fitter na Kanker" randomized controlled trial. J
Med Internet Res 2017;19:e336.
22. Delgadillo J. Guided self-help in a brave new world. Br J Psychiatry
2018;212:65–6.
23. Cuijpers P, Donker T, van Straten A, Li J, Andersson G. Is guided self-
help as effective as face-to-face psychotherapy for depression and anxiety
distresss? A systematic review and meta-analysis of comparative outcome
studies. Psychol Med 2010;40:1943–57.
24. Coull G, Morris PG. The clinical effectiveness of CBT-based guided self-
help interventions for anxiety and depressive distresss: a systematic review.
Psychol Med 2011;41:2239–52.
25. Shao D, Zhang H, Cui N, Sun J, Li J, Cao F. The efficacy and mechanisms
of a guided self-help intervention based on mindfulness in patients with
breast cancer: a randomized controlled trial. Cancer 2021;127:1377–86.
26. Cavanagh K, Strauss C, Forder L, Jones F. Can mindfulness and accep-
tance be learnt by self-help?: a systematic review and meta-analysis of
mindfulness and acceptance-based self-help interventions. Clin Psychol
Rev 2014;34:118–29.
27. Fish J, Brimson J, Lynch S. Mindfulness interventions delivered by tech-
nology without facilitator involvement: what research exists and what are
the clinical outcomes? Mindfulness (N Y) 2016;7:1011–23.
28. Toivonen KI, Zernicke K, Carlson LE. Web-based mindfulness interven-
tions for people with physical health conditions: systematic review. J Med
Internet Res 2017;19:e303.
29. Hayes SC, Luoma JB, Bond FW, Masuda A, Lillis J. Acceptance and
commitment therapy: model, processes and outcomes. Behav Res Ther
2006;44:1–25.
30. Bishop SR. What do we really know about mindfulness-based stress
reduction? Psychosom Med 2002;64:71–83.
31. Lengacher CA, Gruss LF, Kip KE, et al. Mindfulness-based stress reduction
for breast cancer survivors (MBSR(BC)): evaluating mediators of psycho-
logical and physical outcomes in a large randomized controlled trial. J
Behav Med 2021;44:591–604.
32. Urbaniak GC, Plous S. Research Randomizer, version 4.0 [software pro-
gram]. andomizer.org, 2013. http://www.randomizer.org/ (6 March 2016,
date last accessed).
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page><page number="10"><paragraph>236
Mindfulness intervention for cancer patients
33. Bruix J, Sherman M, Llovet JM, et al. Clinical management of hepatocellu-
lar carcinoma. Conclusions of the Barcelona-2000 EASL conference. Euro-
pean Association for the Study of the liver. J Hepatol 2001;35:421–30.
34. Compen F, Bisseling E, Schellekens M, Donders R, Carlson L, van der Lee
M, Speckens A. Face-to-face and internet-based mindfulness-based cogni-
tive therapy compared with treatment as usual in reducing psychological
distress in patients with cancer: a Multicenter randomized controlled trial.
J Clin Oncol 2018;36:2413–21.
35. Kabat-Zinn J, Massion AO, Kristeller J, et al. Effectiveness of a meditation-
based stress reduction program in the treatment of anxiety distresss. Am
J Psychiatry 1992;149:936–43.
36. Teasdale JD, Segal ZV, Williams JM, Ridgeway VA, Soulsby JM, Lau
MA. Prevention of relapse/recurrence in major depression by mindfulness-
based cognitive therapy. J Consult Clin Psychol 2000;68:615–23.
37. Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta
Psychiatr Scand 1983;67:361–70.
38. Edmondson D, Gamboa C, Cohen A, et al. Association of posttraumatic
stress distress and depression with all-cause and cardiovascular disease
mortality and hospitalization among Hurricane Katrina survivors with
end-stage renal disease. Am J Public Health 2013;103:e130–7.
39. Akechi T, Okuyama T, Sugawara Y, Shima Y, Furukawa TA, Uchitomi Y.
Screening for depression in terminally ill cancer patients in Japan. J Pain
Symptom Manage 2006;31:5–12.
40. Zhenxiao S, Huaxue L, Linying J, et al. Reliability and validity of hospital
anxiety and depression scale. Chin J Clin 2017;11:198–201.
41. Buysse DJ, Reynolds CF 3rd, Monk TH, et al. The Pittsburgh sleep quality
index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research. Psychiatry
Res 1989;28:193–213.
42. Taoying L, Yan L, Ping X, et al. Analysis on reliability and validity of the
Pittsburgh sleep quality index. Chongqing Med 2014;43:260–3.
43. Zhu Z, Lang Q, Chen Z, Li DT, Ling CQ. Evaluation of Chinese version of
the functional assessment of cancer therapy-hepatobiliary questionnaire.
J Chin Integr Med 2008;6:341–5.
44. Cohen S, Kamarck T, Mermelstein R. A global measure of perceived stress.
J Health Soc Behav 1983;24:385–96.
45. Qinglong D, Ruoyu H, Jiwei W, et al. Validity and reliability of the
perceived stress scale among cancer survivors. Chin Ment Health J
2018;32:15–20.
46. Jing C, Yang J, Zhuo-Hong Z. Reliability and validity of the Chinese
version of the acceptance and action questionnaire-second edition (AAQ-
II) in college students. Chin Ment Health J 2013;27:873–7.
47. Baron RM, Kenny DA. The moderator-mediator variable distinction in
social psychological research: conceptual, strategic, and statistical consid-
erations. J Pers Soc Psychol 1986;51:1173–82.
48. Jia Y, Zhang W, You S, Li M, Lei L, Chen L. A nomogram for predicting
depression in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma: an observational
cross-sectional study. Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract 2019;23:273–80.
49. Russell L, Ugalde A, Milne D, Austin D, Livingston PM. Digital char-
acteristics and dissemination indicators to optimize delivery of internet-
supported mindfulness-based interventions for people with a chronic
condition: systematic review. JMIR Ment Health 2018;5:e53.
50. Patel N, Maher J, Lie X, et al. Understanding the patient experience in
hepatocellular carcinoma: a qualitative patient interview study. Qual Life
Res 2021. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11136-021-02903-4.
51. Zernicke KA, Campbell TS, Blustein PK, Fung TS, Johnson JA, Bacon
SL, Carlson LE. Mindfulness-based stress reduction for the treatment of
irritable bowel syndrome symptoms: a randomized wait-list controlled
trial. Int J Behav Med 2013;20:385–96.
52. Labelle LE, Campbell TS, Faris P, Carlson LE. Mediators of mindfulness-
based stress reduction (MBSR): assessing the timing and sequence of
change in cancer patients. J Clin Psychol 2015;71:21–40.
53. Hayes SC, Wilson KG, Gifford EV, Follette VM, Strosahl K. Experiential
avoidance and behavioral disorders: a functional dimensional approach
to diagnosis and treatment. J Consult Clin Psychol 1996;64:1152–68.
54. Lindsay EK, Creswell JD. Mechanisms of mindfulness training: monitor
and acceptance theory (MAT). Clin Psychol Rev 2017;51:48–59.
Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jjco/article/52/3/227/6516222 by guest on 18 July 2024</paragraph></page></document>