<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document><page number="1"><paragraph>P A P E R
Internet‐delivered mindfulness‐based cognitive therapy for
anxiety and depression in cancer survivors: A randomized
controlled trial
Eva Rames Nissen1
| Maja O'Connor1
| Viktor Kaldo2,3
| Inger Højris4 |
Michael Borre5 | Robert Zachariae1,4
| Mimi Mehlsen1
1Department of Psychology and Behavioural
Sciences, Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark
2Centre for Psychiatry Research, Department
of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska Institutet,
and Stockholm Health Care Services,
Stockholm, Sweden
3Department of Psychology, Linnaeus
University, Växjö, Sweden
4Department of Oncology, Aarhus University
Hospital, Aarhus, Denmark
5Department of Urology, Aarhus University
Hospital, Aarhus, Denmark
Correspondence
Eva Rames Nissen, Department of Psychology,
Aarhus University, Bartholins Allé 11, DK‐8000
Aarhus. Denmark.
Email: enissen@psy.au.dk
Funding information
Danish Cancer Society, Grant/Award Number:
R113‐A7015‐14‐S34; TrygFonden, Grant/
Award Number: 7‐12.0736
Abstract
Objective:
Internet‐delivered interventions may alleviate distress in cancer survi-
vors with limited access to psychological face‐to‐face treatment. In collaboration with
a group of cancer survivors, we developed and tested the efficacy of a therapist‐
assisted internet‐delivered mindfulness‐based cognitive therapy (iMBCT) program
for anxiety and depression in cancer survivors.
Methods:
A total of 1282 cancer survivors were screened for anxiety and depres-
sion during their routine oncology follow‐up; eligible breast (n = 137) and prostate
cancer (n = 13) survivors were randomized to iMBCT or care‐as‐usual (CAU) wait‐list.
Primary outcomes of anxiety and depression were assessed at baseline, 5 weeks,
10 weeks (post intervention), and 6 months.
Results:
Significant effects were found for both anxiety (Cohen's d = 0.45; P = .017)
and depressive symptoms (d = 0.42; P = .024) post intervention. The effects were
maintained at follow‐up for anxiety (d = 0.40; P = .029), but not for depressive symp-
toms (d = 0.28; P = .131).
Conclusions:
Our preliminary findings suggest iMBCT to be a helpful intervention
for cancer survivors suffering from symptoms of anxiety. Further studies on the effi-
cacy for symptoms of depression are needed.
KEYWORDS
anxiety, breast cancer, cancer, cancer survivors, cognitive therapy, depressive symptoms, internet,
mindfulness, oncology, prostate cancer
1
|
BACKGROUND
The number of cancer survivors is increasing because of improved
diagnosis and treatment. In North America and Europe combined,
almost 1 500 000 new cases of breast and prostate cancer were
diagnosed in 2018.1,2 Since 5‐year survival rates for these cancer
types are above 85%,3 a significant number of former breast and
prostate cancer patients must cope with cancer survivorship.
Anxiety and depression are prevalent among cancer survivors,
even several years after successful treatment,4-6 with 2 to 4 times
higher prevalence of mood disorders compared with the general
population.5,7 High levels of distress are associated with impaired
- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution‐NonCommercial‐NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any
medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non‐commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.
© 2019 The Authors. Psycho‐Oncology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd
Received: 1 May 2019
Revised: 12 September 2019
Accepted: 12 September 2019
DOI: 10.1002/pon.5237
68
Psycho‐Oncology. 2020;29:68–75.
wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/pon</paragraph></page><page number="2"><paragraph>quality of life, poorer daily function, and—possibly—poorer cancer
prognosis.8,9
Meta‐analyses have shown mindfulness‐based interventions (MBIs)
to be efficacious for anxiety and depression with effect sizes (Hedges's
g) up to 0.97 and 0.95 in patients with mood disorders10 and 0.39 and
0.44 with cancer patients and survivors.11 Despite documented effi-
cacy, challenges remain to make MBIs available to patients in need
because of limited number of trained therapists, costs, and restricted
mobility and time constraints among cancer patients and survivors.12-15
Delivering interventions over the internet is an increasingly popular
approach to overcome these challenges. A systematic review of
eHealth interventions aimed at breast cancer patients and survivors
supports the general feasibility and acceptability of internet‐delivered
interventions within this group,16 and two previous studies of inter-
net‐delivered MBIs for psychological distress in cancer patients show
promising results.17,18 One study of cancer patients participating in
an online “Mindfulness‐Based Cancer Recovery program” found an
effect at post intervention on mood disturbance (d = 0.44) when com-
pared with a wait‐list control.17 The second study explored mindful-
ness‐based cognitive therapy (MBCT) for psychological distress in
cancer patients and found relatively comparable post‐intervention
effects of internet‐delivered (d = 0.71) and face‐to‐face–delivered
MBCT (d = 0.45) compared with care‐as‐usual (CAU).18 However, in
both studies, long‐term effects went uninvestigated and participants
were recruited through self‐referral, possibly introducing self‐selection
bias. Offering the intervention to patients identified through a system-
atic screening for distress during follow‐up will add knowledge about
the need for intervention and acceptability of internet delivery of such
interventions.
Our aim was therefore to evaluate the efficacy of internet‐deliv-
ered MBCT (iMBCT) offered as part of routine follow‐up care to breast
and prostate cancer survivors experiencing symptoms of anxiety and
depression. Breast and prostate cancer were chosen as they are prev-
alent cancer types with high long‐term survival rates.19 We chose
iMBCT as our group has previously found MBCT to be well‐accepted
and efficacious for treating persistent pain in breast cancer survi-
vors.20,21 We compared iMBCT with waitlist CAU controls at post
intervention and 6 months follow‐up.
2
|
METHODS
2.1
|
Participants
A total of 150 breast and prostate cancer survivors were randomized
to iMBCT (70%) or wait‐list control (30%). Inclusion criteria were as
follows: scoring greater than or equal to 3 when screened for symp-
toms of anxiety or depression on a 0‐ to 10‐point numeric rating scale,
more than or equal to 3 months and less than or equal to 5 years after
completed primary treatment for primary breast or prostate cancer,
age 18 years and older, ability to understand and read Danish, internet
access, and mobile phone ownership. Exclusion criteria are as follows:
cancer recurrence or active cancer treatment (except adjuvant
endocrine treatment), insufficient IT skills (self‐reported), and severe
mental illness. The study was approved by the regional Science Ethics
Committee
(registration
no:
1‐10‐72‐16‐16)
and
registered
at
ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT03100981).
2.2
|
Sample size and randomization
The study was designed to include 155 participants. Randomization
was conducted in blocks of 10, with seven blocks allocated to inter-
vention and three to control. The unbalanced allocation aimed at
increasing power for subsequent mediation analyses. On the basis of
previous reports, we expected an uneven attrition rate of 25% in the
intervention group and 15% in the control group,22 leading to a final
80 and 41 participants in intervention and control, respectively. This
would allow the detection of a statistical significant (P &lt; .05)
Time × Group interaction corresponding to an effect size (Hedge's g)
of 0.60 with a statistical power of 83%. While larger than previously
found for cancer patients and survivors,11 the effect size is more con-
servative than those found for face‐to‐face MBIs with patients
screened for mood disorders.10 Because of resource and time con-
straints, recruitment was terminated after inclusion of 150 partici-
pants. Expecting an uneven number of eligible breast and prostate
cancer survivors, computerized randomization was stratified according
to cancer type.23 The allocation sequence was generated by the pri-
mary investigator. Research assistants handling recruitment were
unaware of group allocation until after the participant was included.
2.3
|
Procedure
Participants were recruited between February 24, 2016 and August
28, 2017 at the Departments of Oncology and Urology, Aarhus Uni-
versity Hospital. Oncologists or nurses screened all breast and prostate
cancer patients for anxiety and depressive symptoms during routine
control visits after primary treatment. Eligible interested patients were
contacted by telephone for further information about the study. After
completing a consent form and online baseline questionnaires (T1),
participants were randomly assigned to intervention or wait‐list con-
trol. Additional online questionnaires were completed after 5 (T2/mid-
way), 10 (T3/post treatment), and 34 weeks (T4/6 months follow‐up).
Follow‐up data collection was finalized on June 27, 2018.
The iMBCT program was developed in collaboration with cancer
survivor representatives who recommended program adjustments to
meet cancer survivorship needs. For details on this process, see Nissen
et al.24 Program content, including the incorporation of cancer‐specific
adjustments,20 was adapted from the original face‐to‐face MBCT man-
ual25 by clinical psychologists (M.O.C. and E.R.N.) trained at Oxford
Mindfulness Centre with experience of MBCT with cancer survivors.26
Each of the eight 1 week modules included written material, audio
exercises, writing tasks, cancer‐specific patient examples, and videos
with patients and experts. Participants completed a weekly training
diary and mailed it to their therapist who gave written, asynchronous
feedback on a prearranged day of the week. Participants were given
access to the next module after submitting the tasks of the week
NISSEN ET AL.
69</paragraph></page><page number="3"><paragraph>(See Data S1 for an overview of intervention content). After complet-
ing the program, which included an optional 1 week break, participants
had access to treatment materials for 6 months. The secure and
encrypted intervention platform was provided by the Department of
Internet Psychiatry, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden27 (See
Data S2 for screen dump examples). A smartphone‐compliant website
with login provided access to daily exercises to participants. Nine ther-
apists, including eight Master's level psychology students trained in
MBCT,28 and one experienced psychologist trained in MBCT (E.R.N.)
provided the therapist feedback. The student therapists, supervised
by two authors (M.O.C., E.R.N.), based their written feedback to partic-
ipants on a manual‐consistent guide developed for the present study.
Wait‐list controls received auto generated emails asking them to
complete online questionnaires at times T2, T3, and T4. If question-
naires were not completed within 1 week, participants received up to
three reminder emails. If participants did not respond to reminders, they
received a telephone call from a research assistant. The reminder proce-
dures were identical for the intervention and control group. After com-
pleting the T4 follow‐up questionnaire, controls were offered iMBCT.
2.4
|
Measures
2.4.1
|
Screening
Eligible participants were screened for symptoms of depression and
anxiety. Because routine care only allowed a brief screening procedure,
a short two‐item measure was used. Patients indicated on 11‐point
numerical rating scales (0 = not at all, 10 = very much) “Within the past
week, how depressed and sad have you been?” and “Within the past
week, how worried and anxious have you been?”. The 3‐point cut‐off
was based on our experiences with similar recruitment procedures.21
2.4.2
|
Participant characteristics
At T1, participants provided sociodemographic and clinical information
on gender, date of birth, marital status, educational level, occupation,
cancer type, time of diagnosis, and comorbidities.29
2.4.3
|
Outcomes
The primary outcomes of anxiety and depression were assessed at T1,
T2, T3, and T4 with the state subscale of the State‐Trait Anxiety
Inventory Y‐Form (STAI‐Y)30 and the Beck Depression Inventory
(BDI‐II).31 Internal consistencies (Cronbach's α) in the present sample
were .94 and .85, respectively. Secondary outcomes included per-
ceived stress measured at T1, T2, T3, and T4 with the Perceived Stress
Scale (PSS‐10)32; well‐being assessed at T1, T3, and T4 with the World
Health Organization Well‐Being Index (WHO‐5)33; and sleep distur-
bance measured at T1, T3, and T4 with the Insomnia Severity Index
(ISI).34 Internal consistencies in the present sample ranged from 0.85
to 0.87. Therapist time spent was recorded for each module and par-
ticipant adherence to the intervention was assessed as total login
times for the intervention platform and training website and the
number of completed modules. A module was considered completed
if the participant had returned a completed “tasks of the week” work-
ing sheet to the therapist. Additional variables, not reported on in the
present paper, included measures of mindfulness, self‐compassion,
weekly distress, and therapeutic alliance.
2.5
|
Statistical methods
Data were analysed using IBM SPSS Statistics, version 25. Baseline dif-
ferences were explored with t‐ and chi2 tests. Main intention‐to‐treat
analyses were conducted with two‐level multilevel modelling (MLM),
with assessments at time points at level 1 nested within individuals
at level 2. To compare endpoint effects between groups, a linear func-
tion of time was estimated from T1 (baseline) through T3 (post‐assess-
ment) and from T1 through T4 (6‐month follow‐up). Effect sizes
(Cohen's d) were derived from the Group × Time F test and calculated
as d ¼ 2*
ﬃﬃﬃﬃﬃﬃﬃﬃﬃﬃ
F=df
p
,35 with magnitudes of 0.2, 0.5, and 0.8 considered
small, medium, and large, respectively. MLMs were furthermore
employed to evaluate the best fit of time (T1‐T4), including a linear
effect (continued improvement), a log‐linear effect (improvement and
then maintenance of effect), and a quadratic effect (worsening). This
evaluation was based on log likelihood fit statistics (‐2LL), taking into
account the number of parameters in the model. The moderating
effect of cancer type was analysed with the three‐way MLM interac-
tion term (Time × Group × Cancer type). Because of uneven attrition
in the intervention and control group, sensitivity analyses were con-
ducted by repeating analyses for primary outcomes with imputed data
for missing responses with the “zero‐effect from baseline”(ZEFB)
method, which assumes that participants with missing data do not
experience any change during the study period. Adherence‐related
effects for participants in the intervention group were explored with
two‐way MLM interaction terms (Time × Moderator).
3
|
RESULTS
3.1
|
Participant characteristics
A total of 1282 cancer survivors were screened to obtain the final
sample of 150 participants (Figure 1). Of these, 137 had been treated
for breast cancer (mean age 54.55) and 13 for prostate cancer (mean
age = 64.94). The screened patients (n = 1282) had an average score
of 1.64 (SD = 2.39) on the depression screening item and 1.85
(SD = 2.55) on the anxiety screening item. Among the included partic-
ipants, 21 (14.0%) scored greater than or equal to 3 on the anxiety
item only, 10 (6.7%) scored greater than or equal to 3 on the depres-
sion item only, and 119 (79.3%) scored greater than or equal to 3 on
both items. The mean scores of the included participants were 5.5
(SD = 2.1) for anxiety and 4.9 (SD = 2.2) for depression. No baseline
differences between the intervention and control groups were found
for any sociodemographic, clinical, or outcome variables (Table S3).
Participants treated for prostate cancer were significantly older,
had shorter time since diagnosis, and used less prescription medication
NISSEN ET AL.
70</paragraph></page><page number="4"><paragraph>than participants treated for breast cancer. Breast cancer survivors had
higher baseline scores on stress (P = .015) and well‐being (P = .033)
compared with prostate cancer survivors. Attrition rates were higher
in the intervention group (26.0% [T2], 30.8% [T3], and 28.8% [T4])
compared with controls (17.4% [T2 and T3] and 19.6%[T4]). Attrition
was associated with older age (P = .025) and being a woman/breast
cancer survivor (P = .028). When comparing adherent (more than four
completed modules) and non‐adherent participants (less than or equal
to four completed modules), no statistically significant differences
were found for any of the participant characteristics assessed.
3.2
|
Primary outcomes
Statistically significant Time × Group interactions corresponding to
small‐to‐medium effect sizes were found for both anxiety and depres-
sion at post intervention (T3). At follow‐up (T4), the Time × Group
interaction reached statistical significance for anxiety, but not for
depression (Table 1) (separate results for cancer type are shown in
Table S4). Model‐fit analyses revealed that for anxiety linear and log‐
linear models showed comparable fits, whereas a log‐linear model pro-
vided the best fit of the data for depression (Figure S5).
No moderating effects of cancer type were found for anxiety or
depression at any time point (d = 0.07‐0.15; P = .393‐.697). The ZEFB
sensitivity analyses showed that the effects remained statistically sig-
nificant for anxiety at both post intervention (T3) (d = 0.39; P = .019)
and follow‐up (T4) (d = 0.35; P = .033), whereas the post‐intervention
(T3) effect for depression no longer reached statistical significance
(d = 0.29, P = .073).
3.3
|
Secondary outcomes
A statistically significant Time × Group interaction corresponding to a
medium effect size was found for changes in well‐being (d = 0.48) from
baseline to follow‐up (T4). The effect on well‐being at post interven-
tion
(T3)
failed
to
reach
statistical
significance.
Likewise,
no
Time × Group interactions for perceived stress and insomnia severity
reached statistical significance at any time point (Table 1).
3.4
|
Treatment adherence
Of the 104 participants randomized to intervention, 82 (79%) started
iMBCT. Participants completed an average of 5.7 out of eight modules,
with 46 (56%) completing all eight modules. The reported reasons for
not starting or discontinuing iMBCT during the first 4 weeks (n = 51,
49.0%) were lack of motivation (n = 30, 28.8%), insufficient IT skills
(n = 13, 12.5%), and cancer relapse or other physical problems
FIGURE 1
Participant flow diagram
NISSEN ET AL.
71</paragraph></page><page number="5"><paragraph>TABLE 1
Anxiety, depression, stress, well‐being, and insomnia severity at baseline, mid‐intervention, post‐intervention, and follow‐up
Outcome
T1: Baseline
T2: Mid‐
Intervention
T3: Post‐Intervention
T4: 6 Month Follow‐
Up
Effects Time × Group
iMBCT
Control
iMBCT
Control
iMBCT
Control
iMBCT
Control
T1‐T3: Baseline–post intervention, Cohen d
(95%CI); P
T1‐T4: Baseline–follow‐up (6 months), Cohen d
(95% CI); P
N
104
46
77
38
73
38
74
37
Primary outcomes (means and SDs)
STAI‐Y
41.7 (10.2)
42.7 (9.8)
40.2 (9.2)
42.7 (9.6)
37.5 (8.9)
41.8 (11.9)
36.3 (9.9)
40.5 (11.9)
0.45 (0.26‐0.64); .017
0.40 (0.00‐0.80); .029
BDI‐II
15.1 (7.4)
17.6 (7.5)
11.9 (8.3)
15.0 (8.4)
10.7 (6.6)
15.6 (9.2)
10.2 (7.9)
14.2 (9.7)
0.42 (0.23‐0.61); .024
0.28 (0.09‐0.47); .131
Secondary outcomes (means and SDs)
PSS
18.5 (5.7)
18.9 (6.2)
16.7 (6.0)
17.5 (6.1)
15.7 (5.9)
17.0 (6.3)
15.0 (6.6)
17.1 (6.8)
0.18 (−0.21 to 0.57); .331
0.29 (−0.11 to 0.69); .125
WHO‐
5
17.6 (4.8)
17.8 (5.4)
N/A
15.6 (4.7)
16.5 (5.0)
15.0 (5.2)
17.1 (5.6)
0.25 (−0.14 to 0.64); .173
0.48 (0.08‐0.88); .010
ISI
11.7 (5.5)
11.8 (6.3)
N/A
10.3 (6.0)
10.1 (6.9)
10.1 (6.3)
10.0 (6.3)
0.06 (−0.33 to 0.45); .759
0.04 (−0.36 to 0.44); .847
Note. N = number of participants who filled out questionnaires at the given time point.
Abbreviations: BDI, Beck's Depression Inventory31; iMBCT, internet‐delivered mindfulness‐based cognitive therapy; ISI: Insomnia Severity Index34; PSS, Perceived Stress Scale32; STAI‐Y, State‐Trait Anxiety
Inventory Y‐form30; WHO‐5: World Health Organization 5‐item Well‐Being Index.33
NISSEN ET AL.
72</paragraph></page><page number="6"><paragraph>(n = 3, 2.9%). Reasons are unknown for four participants (3.8%). Rea-
sons for discontinuing treatment later than module four (n = 7, 6.7%)
were lack of motivation (n = 6, 5.8%) and cancer relapse or other phys-
ical problems (n = 1, 1.0%). Login data showed that participants spent
on average 39 hours and 15 minutes using the program, corresponding
to 6 hours and 38 minutes per completed module. Therapists used an
average of 117.7 minutes per participant providing feedback, corre-
sponding to 20.3 minutes per completed module. No statistically sig-
nificant associations were found between improvements in anxiety
or depression and number of modules completed, total login time, or
therapist time spent (d = 0.06‐0.16; P &gt; .2).
4
|
DISCUSSION
The present study adds to the few available studies of effects of inter-
net‐delivered MBIs in cancer survivors17,18 and is the first to evaluate
longer‐term effects. The primary outcomes of anxiety and depression
were improved immediately after the intervention with between‐
group effects largely maintained at the 6‐month follow‐up for anxiety,
but not depression. Model fit analyses showed that the depression
data fitted a log‐linear curve, suggesting that the improvement in the
intervention group occurred in the beginning of the study period and
was maintained over time. However, as controls also experienced
improvement over time, the between‐group difference diminished at
follow‐up. Significant between‐group effects were found for well‐
being at the 6‐month follow‐up assessment (d = 0.48). No effects were
found for any of the remaining secondary outcomes (stress and insom-
nia) at any time point.
The effect on symptoms of anxiety remained statistically significant
in the sensitivity analysis, suggesting that iMBCT may have a robust,
durable effect on anxiety symptoms in breast and prostate cancer sur-
vivors. The effect on depression, however, appeared less robust. One
possible reason for this could be that the baseline scores were within
the range of “mild depression,”36 and could thus indicate a floor effect.
One solution for including the patients most likely to benefit could be
a more comprehensive screening procedure or a higher cut‐off when
screening patients.
While the post‐intervention effect sizes for anxiety and depression
found in our study (0.45 and 0.42) are within the same range as those
reported in a meta‐analysis of face‐to‐face group MBIs with cancer
patients (0.37 and 0.44)11,18 and the effect found on mood distur-
bance in the feasibility study of online mindfulness‐based cancer
recovery (0.44),17 they are smaller than the effect found on distress
in another previous study of iMBCT in cancer patients (0.71). When
comparing the results, between‐study differences in participant selec-
tion procedures should be noted. While relatively high distress level
cut‐offs were applied in the previous studies, ie, HADS scores greater
than or equal to 1118 and distress thermometer scores greater than or
equal to 4,17 the present study used a lower cut‐off, which could have
introduced floor effects. In addition, the previous studies recruited
patients through self‐referral, yielding higher inclusion rates, ie,
56%18 and 48%.17 In the present study, only 39% of eligible patients
were enrolled, and one third of those who gave consent to be
contacted about the study declined after receiving oral information.
Thus, while many cancer survivors experience distress, all eligible
patients may not find iMBCT equally attractive, and providing iMBCT
as a routine offer based on a screening procedure may have included
less motivated participants in the present study compared with studies
with self‐referral.
Older age emerged a significant predictor of study attrition, i.e.,
failing to return questionnaires. Age was, however, not associated with
intervention drop‐out, i.e., discontinuation of the iMBCT program. This
result may be important to consider when offering internet‐delivered
therapy to an ageing population in a study setting. Self‐reported rea-
sons for dropping out of the intervention were lack of motivation
and insufficient IT skills, and it has previously been found that cancer
patients prefer face‐to‐face therapy when asked about preferences.37
With respect to intervention adherence, the number of modules
completed did not appear to be associated with the magnitude of
effects. One possible explanation for this somewhat counter‐intuitive
result could be that adherence to mindfulness is not necessarily
reflected in the number of modules completed or time spent on the
platform. Furthermore, dropouts may have different reasons for
discontinuing the intervention. Some may discontinue because they
dislike the intervention, whereas others may discontinue when they
have reached what they experience as sufficient improvement. Such
reasons are consistent with reports of adherence‐related effects of
internet‐delivered interventions in various clinical populations.38-40
Participants spent on average 6 hours and 38 minutes on each com-
pleted module, which would correspond to 2 hours for the session
and 39 minutes of practice per day. This is comparable with face‐to‐
face MBCT with weekly 2‐hour sessions and the required 45 daily
minutes of practice.
The present study has several strengths, including the involvement
of patient representatives in the study development, a relatively large
sample, a randomized design, and 6 months follow‐up data. In addition,
participant recruitment was based on systematic screening of breast
and prostate cancer survivors in routine follow‐up care settings.
Study limitations
The present study has a number of limitations that should be noted.
First, although the sample size was relatively large, we only nearly
achieved the intended inclusion rate. Second, the control condition
was a wait‐list CAU condition, which enables the initial evaluation of
the relevance of the intervention in the clinical setting. This may be
insufficient when assessing the efficacy of the intervention, where
an active control condition could have been relevant. Likewise, evalu-
ating non‐inferiority by directly comparing iMBCT with face‐to‐face
MBCT, as discussed in Compen et al,18 is highly relevant. We had orig-
inally planned to include a third face‐to‐face MBCT arm, but were
forced to abandon this approach because of insufficient resources
and too few patients available for the study. Third, the distribution
of breast and prostate cancer participants in our study sample was
uneven. Between‐cancer type differences in follow‐up procedures
NISSEN ET AL.
73</paragraph></page><page number="7"><paragraph>provided fewer eligible prostate cancer survivors. The follow‐up
period for breast cancer is 5 years compared with only 1 year for pros-
tate cancer. Because of the nature of their disease, the two patient
groups also differ on several parameters, including gender, age, late
effects, and prescription medicine used. While it appears that both
breast and prostate cancer survivors may benefit from iMBCT (Table
S4), our study is likely underpowered to discern to which degree such
cancer type‐related differences influence acceptance and efficacy of
iMBCT. Finally, a high attrition rate was observed in the intervention
group, especially at the beginning of intervention, which could indicate
insufficient recruitment and information procedures. It could be that
this type of intervention does not fully meet the needs, expectations,
and skills of the target population. Participants completed online ques-
tionnaires covering these aspects prior to randomization, but addi-
tional in‐depth assessment of motivation and computer literacy prior
to intervention start could have been relevant.
Clinical implications
iMBCT appears to be a feasible and flexible intervention for cancer
survivors experiencing distress, with promising effects on anxiety and
possibly depressive symptoms. Participants attend the programme
from their homes, which may be attractive to groups of patients who
do not typically seek psychological treatment. We find, in particular,
the completion rate and effect among older men treated for prostate
cancer encouraging.
5
|
CONCLUSION
Taken together, iMBCT showed positive effects for anxiety and
depression immediately after treatment and for anxiety and well‐being
at the 6‐month follow‐up. Despite our intention of maximizing access
to treatment by reducing practical barriers for attending face‐to‐face
treatment, a substantial percentage of distressed cancer survivors
were not interested in an iMBCT intervention when offered as a part
of routine follow‐up care.
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
We wish to thank the participating patients, the staff at the Depart-
ments of Oncology and Urology at Aarhus University Hospital, the stu-
dent‐therapists, Nina Bennet Kjær Boisen for helping develop the
program, and Mia Skytte O'Toole for statistical advice.
TrygFonden (Grant: 7‐12.0736) and the Danish Cancer Society
(Grant: R113‐A7015‐14‐S34) funded the study.
CONFLICT OF INTEREST
The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.
DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT
The data on which the present results are based are available upon
request from the corresponding author. The data are not publicly avail-
able due to privacy or ethical restrictions.
ORCID
Eva Rames Nissen
https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9773-6772
Maja O'Connor
https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7288-8633
Viktor Kaldo
https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6443-5279
Robert Zachariae
https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9076-3068
Mimi Mehlsen
https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5820-8937
REFERENCES
1. International Agency for Research on Cancer. Population Fact Sheet:
Europe. Vol 513. 2018.
2. International Agency for Research on Cancer. Population Fact Sheet:
North America. Vol. 347. 2018.
3. Danish Cancer Society [Internet]. [cited 2019 Aug 10]. Available from:
www.cancer.dk
4. Honda K, Goodwin RD. Cancer and mental disorders in a national com-
munity
sample:
findings
from
the
national
comorbidity
survey.
Psychother Psychosom. 2004;73(4):235‐242.
5. Mitchell AJ, Ferguson DW, Gill J, Paul J, Symonds P. Depression and
anxiety in long‐term cancer survivors compared with spouses and
healthy controls: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. Lancet Oncol.
2013;14(8):721‐732.
6. Dalton SO, Laursen TM, Ross L, Mortensen PB, Johansen C. Risk for
hospitalization with depression after a cancer diagnosis: a nationwide,
population‐based study of cancer patients in Denmark from 1973 to
2003. J Clin Oncol. 2009;27(9):1440‐1445.
7. Mitchell AJ, Chan M, Bhatti H, et al. Prevalence of depression, anxiety,
and adjustment disorder in oncological, haematological, and palliative‐
care settings: a meta‐analysis of 94 interview‐based studies. Lancet
Oncol. 2011;12(2):160‐174.
8. Reich M, Lesur A, Perdrizet‐Chevallier C. Depression, quality of life and
breast cancer: a review of the literature. Breast Cancer Res Treat.
2008;110(1):9‐17.
9. Prieto JM, Blanch J, Atala J, et al. Psychiatric morbidity and impact
on hospital length of stay among hematologic cancer patients
receiving
stem‐cell
transplantation.
J
Clin
Oncol.
2002;20(7):
1907‐1917.
10. Hofmann SG, Sawyer AT, Witt A, Oh D. The effect of mindfulness‐
based therapy on anxiety and depression: a meta‐analytic review. J
Consult Clin Psychol. 2010;78(2):169‐183.
11. Piet J, Würtzen H, Zachariae R. The effect of mindfulness‐based ther-
apy on symptoms of anxiety and depression in adult cancer patients
and survivors: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. J Consult Clin
Psychol. 2012;80(6):1007‐1020.
12. Holm LV, Hansen DG, Johansen C, et al. Participation in cancer rehabil-
itation and unmet needs: a population‐based cohort study. Support
Care Cancer. 2012/03/15. 2012;20(11):2913‐2924.
13. Barak A, Hen L, Boniel‐nissim M, Shapira NA. Comprehensive review
and a meta‐analysis of the effectiveness of internet‐based psychother-
apeutic interventions a comprehensive review and a meta‐analysis of
the effectiveness of internet‐based psychotherapeutic interventions. J
Technol Hum Serv. 2008;26(2–4):109‐160.
NISSEN ET AL.
74</paragraph></page><page number="8"><paragraph>14. Griffiths KM, Christensen H. Review article internet‐based mental
health programs: a powerful tool in the rural medical kit. Aust J Rural
Health. 2007;15:81‐87.
15. Stanton AL. Psychosocial concerns and interventions for cancer survi-
vors. J Clin Oncol. 2006;24(32):5132‐5137.
16. Triberti S, Savioni L, Sebri V, Pravettoni G. eHealth for improving qual-
ity of life in breast cancer patients: a systematic review. Cancer Treat
Rev. 2019;74(2018):1‐14.
17. Zernicke KA, Campbell TS, Speca M, McCabe‐Ruff K, Flowers S,
Carlson LE. A randomized wait‐list controlled trial of feasibility and effi-
cacy of an online mindfulness‐based cancer recovery program: the
eTherapy for cancer applying mindfulness trial. Psychosom Med.
2014;76(4):257‐267.
18. Compen F, Bisseling E, Schellekens M, et al. Face‐to‐face and internet‐
based mindfulness‐based cognitive therapy compared with treatment
as usual in reducing psychological distress in patients with cancer: a
multicenter
randomized
controlled
trial.
J
Clin
Oncol.
2018;36
(23):2413‐2421.
19. National Cancer Institute. Cancer Stat Facts. Surveillance, Epidemiol-
ogy, and End Results Program. 2019.
20. Johannsen M, O'Connor M, O'Toole MS, Jensen AB, Højris I, Zachariae
R. Efficacy of mindfulness‐based cognitive therapy on late post‐treat-
ment pain in women treated for primary breast cancer: a randomized
controlled trial. J Clin Oncol. 2016;34(28):3390‐3399.
21. Johannsen M, O'Connor M, O'Toole MS, Jensen AB, Zachariae R.
Mindfulness‐based cognitive therapy and persistent pain in women
treated for primary breast cancer. Clin J Pain. 2018;34(1):59‐67.
22. Cuijpers P, van Straten A, Andersson G. Internet‐administered cogni-
tive behavior therapy for health problems: a systematic review. J
Behav Med. 2008;31(2):169‐177.
23. Haahr M, Haahr S. https://www.random.org. 2015.
24. Nissen ER, Bregnballe V, Mehlsen MY, et al. Patient involvement in the
development of a psychosocial cancer rehabilitation intervention: eval-
uation of a shared working group with patients and researchers. Res
Involv Engagem. 2018;4(24):24.
25. Segal ZV, Williams JMG, Teasdale JD. Mindfulness‐Based Cognitive
Therapy for Depression. 2nd ed. New York: The Guilford Press;
2013:449.
26. Bartley T. Mindfulness‐Based Cognitive Therapy for Cancer. 1st ed.
Oxford: Wiley‐Blackwell; 2012:400.
27. Titov N, Dear B, Nielssen O, et al. ICBT in routine care: a descriptive
analysis
of
successful
clinics
in
five
countries.
Internet
Interv.
2018;13:108‐115.
28. Farver‐Vestergaard I, Johannsen M, Nissen ER, O'Connor M. Mindful-
ness‐Baseret Kognitiv Terapi i en sundhedspsykologisk kontekst:
Effektstudier og kliniske betragtninger fra Enhed for Psykoonkologi
og Sundhedspsykologi. Psyke &amp; Logos. 2016;37:12‐29.
29. Katz J, Chang L, Sangha O. Can comorbidity be measured by question-
naire rather than medical record review? Med Care. 1996;34(1):73‐84.
30. Spielberger D, Gorsuch RL, Lushene PR, Vagg PR, Jacobs GA. State‐
trait anxiety inventory for adults 1983;76.
31. Beck AT, Steere RA, Brown GK. Manual for the Beck Depression Inven-
tory‐II. San Antonio. TX: The Psychological Corporation; 1996.
32. Cohen S, Williamson G. Perceived stress in a probability sample of the
United States. In: Spacapan S, Oskamp S, eds. The Social Psychology of
Health. Newbury Park, CA: Sage; 1988:31‐67.
33. Bonsignore M, Barkow K, Jessen F, Heun R. Validity of the five‐item
WHO Well‐Being Index (WHO‐5) in an elderly population. Eur Arch
Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2001;251(Suppl):II27‐II31.
34. Bastien CH, Vallieres A, Morin CM. Validation of the Insomnia Severity
Index as an outcome measure for insomnia research. Sleep Med. 2001;2
(4):297‐307.
35. Verbeke G, Molenberghs G. Linear Mixed Models for Longitudinal Data.
New York: Springer; 2000.
36. Beck AT, Ward CH, Mendelson M, Mock J, Erbaugh J. An inventory for
measuring depression. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1961;4:561‐571.
37. Wallin EEK, Mattsson S, Olsson EMG. The preference for internet‐
based psychological interventions by individuals without past or cur-
rent use of mental health treatment delivered online: a survey study
with mixed‐methods analysis. JMIR Ment Heal. 2016;3(2):e25.
38. Donkin L, Christensen H, Naismith SL, Neal B, Hickie IB, Glozier N. A
systematic review of the impact of adherence on the effectiveness of
e‐therapies. J Med Internet Res. 2011;13(3):1‐12.
39. Donkin L, Hickie IB, Christensen H, et al. Rethinking the dose‐response
relationship between usage and outcome in an online intervention for
depression: randomized controlled trial. J Med Internet Res. 2013;15
(10):e231.
40. Arndt A, Lutz W, Rubel J, et al. Identifying change‐dropout patterns
during an internet‐based intervention for depression by applying the
Muthen‐Roy model. Cogn Behav Ther. 2019.
SUPPORTING INFORMATION
Additional supporting information may be found online in the
Supporting Information section at the end of the article.
How to cite this article: Nissen ER, O'Connor M, Kaldo V,
et al. Internet‐delivered mindfulness‐based cognitive therapy
for anxiety and depression in cancer survivors: A randomized
controlled trial. Psycho‐Oncology. 2020;29:68‐75. https://doi.
org/10.1002/pon.5237
NISSEN ET AL.
75</paragraph></page></document>