<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document><page number="1"><paragraph>Vol.:(0123456789)
1 3
Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00520-023-07904-2
CORRESPONDENCE
Effect of mindfulness‑based therapy on spiritual well‑being in breast 
cancer patients: a randomized controlled study
Hatice Oner Cengiz1 · Berna Bayir2 · Serap Sayar2 · Mehmet Demirtas3
Received: 4 October 2022 / Accepted: 23 June 2023 / Published online: 3 July 2023 
© The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2023
Abstract
Background Spiritual well-being is directly related to the quality of life in breast cancer patients. Mindfulness-based therapy 
interventions can decrease distress levels in women with breast cancer, while improving spiritual well-being.
Objective To investigate the effect of mindfulness-based therapy on spiritual well-being in breast cancer patients.
Methods This randomized controlled clinical trial was conducted in accordance with the Consolidated Standards of Report-
ing Trials. A total of 70 participants were enrolled from September, 2021 to July, 2022. Primary outcome included spiritual 
well-being, and secondary outcome included quality of life. The data were collected using the Patient Sociodemographic 
and Medical Data Form and Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Spiritual Well-Being (SpWB) (FACIT-
Sp Version 4). In the statistical analysis, the independent sample t test and paired sample t test were used to examine the 
intervention effect on primary and secondary outcomes, according to numbers, percentage, mean, standard deviation, and 
conformity to normal distribution.
Results The average age of the therapy group was 42.22 ± 6.86, and the control group was 41.64 ±  6.04. The average score 
of meaning (12.25 ±  3.03), overall score average of the spiritual well-being (31.56 ±  8.90), the emotional well-being 
(13.46 ±  5.78) and physical well-being (16.71 ±  5.59), and overall average score of the quality of life (66.98 ±  17.72) of 
the therapy group was statistically significantly higher (p &lt; 0.05).
Conclusion The mindfulness-based training may enhance the spiritual well-being and quality of life of breast cancer patients. 
Nurses should be encouraged for mindfulness-based training sessions to make it a widespread practice, and to regularly 
evaluate the results.
Trial registration NCT05057078 (date: September 27, 2021).
Keywords Breast cancer · Mindfulness · Nursing · Spirituality
Introduction
Due to advances in early diagnosis and treatment methods in 
breast cancer, the mortality and morbidity rate has decreased 
[1–3]. Depending on surgical intervention or adjuvant 
therapy, patients with breast cancer may experience physi-
cal symptoms [1, 4, 5] such as fatigue [6], hot flashes [4], 
arm discomfort due to mastectomy [4], vaginal dryness [4] 
pain [4, 6], nausea and vomiting [4] as well as psychological 
symptoms [1, 4, 7], such as deterioration of sexuality [4], 
depression [6, 8], anxiety [6, 8], and fear of recurrence of the 
disease [4]. In addition to these symptoms, the perception of 
the disease posing a life-threatening risk may cause patients 
to experience crisis since it influences them in physical, psy-
chosocial, behavioral, and spiritual aspects [9]. It is empha-
sized that patients with breast cancer have a lower level of 
 * Hatice Oner Cengiz 
 
htcnr8878@gmail.com
 
Berna Bayir 
 
berna.bayir@karatay.edu.tr
 
Serap Sayar 
 
oranserap@gmail.com
 
Mehmet Demirtas 
 
mehmet-4489@hotmail.com
1 
Faculty of Nursing, Department of Nursing, Department 
of Surgical Diseases Nursing, Ankara University, Ankara, 
Turkey
2 
KTO Karatay University School of Health Sciences 
Department of Nursing, Konya, Turkey
3 
Malatya Turgut Ozal Medical Center Radiation Oncology 
Clinic, Malatya, Turkey</paragraph></page><page number="2"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438
1 3
438 
Page 2 of 12
religious activity due to feelings of emptiness, anger, pow-
erlessness, and abandonment by God [10]. Therefore, after 
diagnosis, individuals have difficulty finding the meaning 
and purpose of life. Such condition causes them to question 
their beliefs, increase their concerns about spirituality both 
existentially and religiously, and thus experience spiritual 
distress. But on the other hand, there is a growing interest 
in the role of spirituality as a component of quality of life of 
cancer survivors [11]. Spirituality is defined as the dynamic 
and intrinsic dimension of human life that relates to the way 
persons experience, express, and/or seek meaning, purpose, 
and transcendence, and the way they connect to the moment, 
to self, to others, to nature, and to the significant and/or the 
sacred [9]. Spirituality can play a vital role in healing and 
well-being, as spirituality confers inner strength and peace 
serves as a means of coping with cancer [11]. The spiritual 
and religious dimensions, which are important components 
of the patient’s quality of life, should be considered as an 
integral part of patient care [11]. That is because of the fact 
that an individual can adapt spiritual coping methods by tend-
ing to spirituality while facing a life-threatening and painful 
illness [10, 12]. Spirituality, used in breast cancer patients to 
cope with physical and psychological symptoms of the dis-
ease [13] is one of the strategies that help them find hope and 
gratitude, and become positive [14] since it provides inner 
strength, peace, comfort, and integrity, and plays an impor-
tant role in healing and increasing spiritual well-being [11]. 
Increasing the spiritual well-being of women with breast 
cancer can improve the quality of life depending on coping 
with the symptoms of the disease and treatment [5, 15]. The 
spirituality, which is an important strategy for coping with 
daily life problems and diseases, has positive effects on indi-
viduals’ mental and physical health [16]. In previous studies, 
it has been determined that the quality of life is also higher 
in those with high spiritual well-being [17, 18]. In a system-
atic review, it was found that religion/spirituality is associ-
ated with pain and physical symptoms, and a high state of 
spiritual well-being contributes to psychological well-being 
[19]. Therefore, interventions that will increase spiritual 
well-being in patients with breast cancer can also contribute 
to improving their quality of life. One of these interventions 
is mindfulness-based therapy (MBT). MBT represents a 
unique form of psychotherapeutic and/or supportive inter-
vention that warrants attention for cancer patients, includ-
ing those diagnosed with breast cancer [3]. The concept of 
mindfulness was first defined as the ability to be aware of the 
moment of resentment consciously and without judgment [5]. 
Through non-judgmental/reactive mindfulness, being present 
in the “moment” may increase self-regulation of feelings and 
thoughts, while decreasing deep thinking and detailing on 
past or future experiences [16, 20]. Therefore, mindfulness 
is considered a way of improving physical and psychologi-
cal well-being in individuals, increasing the quality of life, 
relieving pain, reducing stress in the short and long term, and 
making life meaningful [16]. In studies examined the effect 
of MBT in patients with breast cancer, it was found that anxi-
ety [3, 6, 7, 20], depression [3, 6, 7], and fatigue [3] levels 
of the patients decreased, while quality of sleep [3], social 
engagement [8], quality of life [3, 21, 22], and physical activ-
ity [23] increased. However, different results were obtained 
in the studies examining its effect on spiritual well-being. In 
a study, MBT was found to have no effect on spiritual well-
being [7], while some indicated that it increased the levels 
[24, 25]. The results of these relatively few studies may be 
affected by factors such as sampling selection criteria and 
sample size. Therefore, the information in the literature that 
it reduces anxiety, fatigue, and depression levels promises 
a positive effect on spiritual well-being. In the light of this 
information, the aim of this study was to determine the effect 
of MBT on spiritual well-being in breast cancer patients.
Research hypotheses
H1: In patients with breast cancer who receive the mindful-
ness-based therapy, the overall score average of the SP-12, 
measured using the FACIT-Sp Version 4 scale, will be sig-
nificantly higher than those who will not receive the therapy.
H2: In patients with breast cancer who receive the 
mindfulness-based therapy, the overall score average of the 
FACIT-G quality of life, measured using the FACIT-Sp Ver-
sion 4 scale, will be significantly higher than those who will 
not receive the therapy.
Methods
Design and ethical considerations
This study was conducted as a two-group (therapy group 
and control group) randomized controlled trial evaluating 
the effect of MBT on patients with breast cancer. Ethical 
approval was obtained from the ethics committee (KTO 
Karatay University Non-pharmaceutical and Non-medical 
Device Research Ethics Committee Chairmanship. Date Sep-
tember 07, 2021 registration number E-41901325–050.99–14
,950/2021/029). In the study, the articles in the Declaration of 
Helsinki were complied with. This study was registered in the 
Clinical Trial Registry (registration number NCT05057078) 
prior to data collection process. All participants were thor-
oughly briefed on the research process before providing their 
consent, and all were ensured that there would be no conse-
quences in case they choose to withdraw at any stage. Verbal 
and written consent was obtained from all participants. The 
study was conducted in accordance with the Consolidated 
Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) 2010 guidelines.</paragraph></page><page number="3"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438 
1 3
Page 3 of 12 
438
Sample and settings
The study was conducted at a training and research hospital, 
from September, 2021 to July, 2022.
Inclusion criteria (a) being aged between &gt; 18 and &lt; 65 with 
breast cancer, (b) being diagnosed at least 6 months ago, 
(c) being able to understand and write Turkish and com-
municate effectively with researchers and other patients, (d) 
receiving outpatient treatment, and (e) having a computer or 
smartphone.
Exclusion criteria (a) having another type of cancer, (b) hav-
ing a stage IV breast cancer, and (c) having a psychiatric 
disorder.
Removal criteria  (a) not regularly participating in the ther-
apy program, (b) being diagnosed with a psychiatric disorder 
during the research process, and (c) beginning to receive 
inpatient treatment during the research process.
Sample size and randomization
The G*Power software version 3.1.9.4 (Franz Faul, Univer-
sitat Kiel, Germany) test was used to determine the sample 
size [26] In the analysis performed as a priori, the article 
published by Park et al. FACIT-Sp mean was referenced [25]. 
Prior analyses were performed based on the t tests (mean 
values: difference between two independent mean values 
(two groups)). Accordingly, it was determined that the sample 
should consist of a total of 66 patients, including 33 patients 
in each group with a margin of error of 0.05, statistical power 
of 95%, and effect size of 0.90. The dropout rate was found to 
be 7.8%. Given the likelihood of withdrawals, 35 participants 
were assigned to each group, with a total of 70. The study 
flowchart was shown in Fig. 1. The participants were assigned 
randomly to the therapy group that received MBT and the 
control group that received routine care. Group assignments 
were performed randomly using the simple full randomiza-
tion method. In order to determine the order of application, 
the names of the study groups (mindfulness program group 
Assessed for eligibility (n=112)
Excluded  (n=42)
Not meeting inclusion criteria (n=42)
Analysed (n=32)
Discontinued intervention 
The patient did not continue therapy 
regularly (n=1)
The patient could not adapt to therapy 
(n=1)
The 
patient 
left 
the 
study 
voluntarily(n=1)
Allocated to therapy group (n=35)
 usual care and Mindfulness-Based Therapy
Discontinued intervention 
the patient did not complete the 
questionnaires (n=2)
Allocated to control group (n=35)
Usual care 
Analysed (n=33)
Allocation
Analysis
Follow-Up
Randomized (n=70)
Enrollment
Fig. 1  The study flowchart according to CONSORT 2010</paragraph></page><page number="4"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438
1 3
438 
Page 4 of 12
and control group) were written on a paper 35 times by the 
researcher, and the participants were selected randomly by 
drawing lots. Therefore, the researcher could not be blinded. 
The data entry was performed by the author, who was not 
involved in data collection and had no conflict of interest.
Intervention
Therapy group
Prior to the study, the researcher obtained a certificate after 
receiving training on mindfulness-based therapy. Since the 
COVID-19 measures were still in practice during data collec-
tion process and cancer patients were considered to be in the risk 
group, therapy sessions and data collection process were carried 
out online. MBT was performed via Zoom Cloud Meeting 5.9.3 
(3169). The patients themselves (who could) or their relatives 
were allowed to install the program on their computers or smart-
phones. They were guided in this regard. Those who met the 
inclusion criteria were informed about the objective and signifi-
cance of the study. The sessions were scheduled on appropriate 
days for the patients included in the therapy group. The days 
were determined by contacting the therapy group at the begin-
ning of each week to ensure compliance with their schedules.
The therapy group was divided into 4 groups. The num-
ber of patients in the groups was between 8 and 10. A group 
was created for each group via WhatsApp. Throughout the 
week, a reminder message was sent by the trainer periodically 
including voice records and required tasks. The MBT was 
conducted within eight sessions, as once a week for 8 weeks. 
Each session lasted approximately 45 to 60 min. The inter-
vention followed the standard MBT protocol with minor 
modifications (e.g., different mindful movement practices; 
focus on clarifying personal values). The therapy was applied 
for eight sessions after the preparatory session. There were 
no side effects related to MBT in the therapy group patients. 
The subject of therapy group sessions is given in Table 1.
Control group
The patients included in the control group were not applied 
any intervention. After the data collection process was 
completed, the patients in the control group were sent audio 
recordings used for exercises with an explanation about 
MBT via WhatsApp.
Observation indicators
Primary outcome Spiritual well-being.
Secondary outcome Quality of life.
Data collection
The data were collected online by the researchers using the 
Patient Sociodemographic and Medical Data Form and the 
Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Spiritual 
Well-Being (SpWB) (FACIT-Sp Version 4). The forms were 
prepared online using Google Form and shared with the patients.
The patient sociodemographic and medical data form The 
form, consisting of 11 questions about age, gender, marital 
status, educational status, income status, employment status, 
number of children, time of diagnosis, time of treatment, 
treatment type and stage of breast cancer, was prepared by 
the researchers.
Functional assessment of chronic illness therapy‑spiritual 
well‑being (SpWB) (FACIT‑Sp version 4 The scale was devel-
oped by Peterman et al. (2002) to determine spiritual well-
being in chronic patients and cancer patients. Validity and 
reliability for Turkish society were done by Aktürk et al. 
(2017). The scale is used to measure spiritual well-being in 
patients with chronic diseases. All questions in the FACIT-
Sp are rated on a 5-point scale (0 = not at all; 4 = very much), 
and evaluate overall spiritual well-being during the previous 
week. FACIT-Sp version 4 consists of quality of life (FACT-
G) and spiritual well-being (Sp). The FACT-G (version 4) 
includes 27 items and four subscales: physical well-being 
(PWB = 7 items, score range 0–28), social/family well-being 
(SWB = 7 items, score range 0–28), emotional well-being 
(EWB = 6 items, score range 0–24), and functional well-
being (FWB = 7 items, score range 0–28). The FACT-G 
scores range from 0 to 108 points, and higher scores indicate 
a better overall QoL. Sp consists of 12 items and three sub-
scales. The scale was developed to assess the spiritual well-
being of cancer patients or individuals with other chronic 
diseases. It enables profound investigation of all components 
of spiritual well-being via three subscales (“Peace,” “Mean-
ing,” and “Faith”). It is a Likert-type scale that includes 12 
items, and scale items are rated between 0 and 4 (0 never, 4 
always). The Meaning (items 2, 3, 5, and 8), Peace (items 
1, 4, 6, and 7), and Faith (items 9–12) subscales each have a 
total score range of 0–16, so that the range of total scores for 
the complete scale is 0–48. A higher score signifies greater 
spiritual well-being. The scale can be applied in 5 to 6 min. 
Peterman et al. determined that the value of Cronbach’s a for 
the scale ranges from 0.81 to 0.83 [27]. In the current study, 
it was found to be 0.84.
The first measurement The Patient Sociodemographic 
and Medical Data Form and the Functional Assessment 
of Chronic Illness Therapy-Spiritual Well-Being (SpWB) 
(FACIT-Sp Version 4) were applied to the patients included 
in the therapy group immediately before the first session. The</paragraph></page><page number="5"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438 
1 3
Page 5 of 12 
438
Patient Sociodemographic and Medical Data Form and the 
Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Spiritual 
Well-Being (SpWB) (FACIT-SpVERSION 4) were applied to 
those included in the control group during the first interview.
Final measurement The patients in the therapy group were re-
applied the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-
Spiritual Well-Being (SpWB) (FACIT-Sp Version 4) imme-
diately after the last session (after 8 weeks). The patients in 
the control group were re-applied the Functional Assessment 
of Chronic Illness Therapy-Spiritual Well-Being (SpWB) 
(FACIT-Sp Version 4) 8 weeks after the first measurement.
Statistical analysis
The data obtained from the research were analyzed using 
the SPSS version 25.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) 
program. Sociodemographic and clinical characteristics 
of the patients in the therapy and control groups were 
examined by taking the number, percentage, arithmetic 
mean, and standard deviation. In order to show the simi-
larity between the groups in terms of sociodemographic 
and clinical characteristics, the significance test of the 
difference between the two averages for the age variable 
and chi-squared analysis for other categorical variables 
were used. The conformity of the data to the normal dis-
tribution was examined using the Shapiro–Wilk test. The 
independent sample t test was used to evaluate the differ-
ence between the mean scores of the quality of life and 
spiritual well-being of the therapy and control groups, 
since the data showed normal distribution. The paired 
sample t test was used to compare the mean scores of 
quality of life and spiritual well-being over time (before 
and after the intervention) in the in-group measurements.
Table 1  Subject of therapy 
group sessions
Preparatory 
session 
• Contact information was obtained with the consent of the participants.
• Brief information was given to the therapy group about the mindfulness 
practice.
• It was explained that the application will be made with an online zoom link 
and the necessity of creating an infrastructure for this.
• The materials required during the mindfulness practice (Comfortable clothes, 
a mat or a soft thick blanket suitable for laying on the floor, three raisins/dried 
fruits) were specified.
• The date and time were determined for the first meeting.
First session
• Meeting with the participants was started by using the awareness meeting 
method. In this form of acquaintance, the participants introduced themselves to 
each other in pairs. The person who listened to what the other person said, told 
what they heard as far as he could remember.
• What is mindfulness? How aware are we of life? These were discussed.
• By showing a picture with nine dots, the participants were asked to connect 
these nine dots with 4 lines without ever raising their hands. This was used as a 
kind of focus exercise.
• The story “Across the Stream”, which contains the messages that we cannot 
focus on our surroundings while trying to keep up with the tempo of time, was 
read.
• A mindful eating technique was applied with three raisins. The task of "eating 
mindfully" was given at least one meal during the week.
• The first session was terminated after one minute of silence.
Second 
session
• Mutual feedback was received on the assigned assignments.
• It was argued that it is not impossible to connect the 9 points.
• Everyone was asked to lie down in a comfortable place or on a mat and focus 
on what was being said. In this way, a body scan was performed, focusing their 
attention on the limbs, trunk, and head, respectively.
• After sharing the thoughts after the body scan, everyone was asked to take a 
comfortable sitting position. In this way, they were told to focus on the breath 
and then focus on sounds coming from near and far. In this way, the sitting 
exercise is completed.
• Participants were asked to do 10-15 minutes of “sitting exercise” every day 
during the week.
• For six days, the participants were asked to perform a “body scan” with the 
audio recording sent to them.
• They were asked to create a “calendar of pleasant moments” by taking notes 
on the topics they liked every day of the week.
• The first session was ended after the eyes were closed and they sat in silence 
for a minute.</paragraph></page><page number="6"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438
1 3
438 
Page 6 of 12
Table 1  (continued)
Third 
Session
• Awareness of what is in the pleasant moments calendar was discussed.
• Experiences during the meditations held during the week were shared.
• What is autopilot? An awareness speech was given about how often we 
experience this. If there are things we prefer to avoid, it was made to be noticed.
• A 15-minute sitting exercise was performed.
• 15 minutes of yoga was practiced with conscious awareness.
• The session was completed with a 3-minute mindful breathing exercise.
• Homework: Creating a “calendar of unpleasant moments” during the week, 
trying to realize the state of being on autopilot during the day, doing yoga with 
awareness every other day and doing daily sitting exercises.
Fourth 
Session
• The unpleasant moments noted during the week and the feelings these 
moments create in individuals were discussed.
• Focusing exercise was carried out by asking the listener to tell the whole 
group what he heard, in pairs, to explain their plans and thoughts about the 
future.
• Mindful breathing exercise was performed by focusing on mindful breathing 
for 20 minutes. The participants were given the command to "breathe as you 
normally would during this exercise, but notice the changes in your chest and 
abdomen during breathing".
• The article on 21 ways to reduce stress was read and the possibilities of 
making it a part of life were discussed.
• The awareness of our body's reactions to stress was explained.
• Yoga was practiced with awareness for 15 minutes.
• One day yoga and one day body scan were given as weekday homework on 
consecutive days.
• The session was completed with 1 minute of silence.
Fifth 
session
• Awareness of the body's reactions in case of stress was discussed during the 
week. Participants were asked to share their experiences.
• Body scanning was done on the mats.
• Mutual experiences were shared on the stress factors brought by the treatment 
process, the difficult situations experienced and the reactions given to them, and 
the methods of coping with the reactions.
• The existence of compassion and self-compassion was discussed and thoughts 
shared.
• The session was completed with a 3-minute awareness breathing exercise.
Sixth 
session
• This week has been determined as the day of silence. Participants were asked 
not to verbally communicate with anyone around them or with us throughout 
the session.
• During the two hours of the session, the participants were kept quiet.
• During this silence, sitting exercise, mindfulness yoga exercises, breathing 
exercise, step exercise were applied.
• During these exercises, if the participants encountered difficult situations such 
as fear, anger, sadness, and impatience, they were asked to turn these feelings 
into friendship and curiosity with awareness.
• It was given as homework to fill in the “communication exercises” calendar 
for the 7th week and the session was completed.
Seventh 
session
• Mutual communication was established regarding the “communication 
exercises” calendar filled during the week.
• The effects of difficulties in communication on our bodies were discussed.
• Body scanning, yoga and sitting exercises were performed.
• The exercise of consciously eating any food available near us was done.
• For the next week, it was given as homework to do body scan, yoga and 
sitting exercises without sound recording, respectively.
• The session was completed by breathing with awareness for 3 minutes.
Eighth 
Session
• Experiences during the week were shared.
• The article “If I had a chance to live my life again” was read.
• The sustainability of the exercises learned without a voice recording was 
discussed. The plans made for this were shared.
• They were asked to question themselves about how they could make sense of 
the stories we read.
• The program was completed with 5 minutes of awareness breathing exercise 
and 1 minute of silence.</paragraph></page><page number="7"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438 
1 3
Page 7 of 12 
438
Results
Baseline characteristics
The distribution and comparison of the patients in the 
therapy and control groups according to their sociodemo-
graphic and medical characteristics are given in Table 2. 
The average age of the patients in the therapy group was 
42.22 ± 6.86, while the average age of those in the con-
trol group was 41.64 ± 6.04. There were no statistically 
significant differences between the groups in terms of 
clinical characteristics. The groups showed homogeneous 
distribution.
Primary outcomes
The comparison of some characteristics of the treatment 
and control groups with the FACIT-Sp mean scores is 
given in Table 3. Accordingly, there was no difference 
between the mean scores of the pretest and posttest 
according to the diagnosis time, receiving chemotherapy, 
receiving radiotherapy, surgical intervention, and stage of 
the breast cancer. The overall average score of the spiritual 
well-being (Sp) and subscale score averages of the both 
groups are given in Table 4 and Fig. 2. Accordingly, in 
the in-group comparison, it was determined that there 
was no statistical difference between the Meaning, Peace, 
Table 2  Baseline demographic 
data and clinical characteristics 
of the patients in the therapy 
and control group
Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation, range, number, and percentage. Data were analyzed by 
unpaired t test, independent sample t test, or chi-squared test as appropriate. Significance level was set at 
p &lt; 0.05, and values in bold are significant
N number, SD standard deviation
* Independent sample t test
** Chi-squared test
Characteristics
Control group (n = 33)
Therapy group (n = 32)
Test
p
Age ( x± SD)
41.64 ±6.04
42.22 ±6.86
0.36*
0.71
n (%)
N (%)
Education status
   Primary school
15 (52.9)
10 (29.0)
3.48
0.32
   High school
12 (36.4)
12 (37.5)
   University
6 (18.2)
10 (31.3)
Working status
   Not working
22 (66.7)
16 (50.0)
1.85**
0.17
   Working
11 (33.3)
16 (50.0)
Marital status
   Married
27 (81.8)
24 (75.0)
0.44**
0.50
   Single
6 (18.2)
8 (25.0)
Diagnosis time
    &gt; 6 months– ≤ 1 year
12 (36.4)
15 (75.0)
1.98**
0.18
    &gt; 1–5 year
21 (63.6)
17 (25.0)
Receiving chemotherapy
   Yes
31 (93.9)
25 (78.1)
3.40**
0.06
   No
2 (6.1)
7 (21.9)
Receiving radiotherapy
   Yes
25 (75.8)
26 (81.3)
0.29**
0.59
   No
8 (24.2)
6 (18.8)
Surgical intervention
   Yes (&gt; 6 months)
33 (100.0)
32 (100.0)
Stage of the breast cancer
   Stage 1
6 (18.2)
13 (40.6)
6.80**
0.07
   Stage 2
17 (51.5)
8 (25.0)
   Stage 3
10 (30.3)
11 (34.4)</paragraph></page><page number="8"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438
1 3
438 
Page 8 of 12
and Faith subscale scores and the overall score average 
of the spiritual well-being in both groups at the first and 
final measurement (p &gt; 0.05). However, although there 
was no significant difference, it was noteworthy that in 
the final measurement, the average score of the patients 
in the therapy group increased, while the average score 
of the control group tended to decrease. In the intra-
group comparisons, it was found that the average score 
of the Meaning subscale (12.25 ± 3.03) and the overall 
score average of the spiritual well-being (31.56 ±  8.90) 
obtained in the last measurement in the therapy group 
were statistically significantly higher than the control 
group (p&lt; 0.05).
Secondary outcomes
The in-group and intra-group comparisons of the qual-
ity of life mean scores and subscales of the patients in 
the therapy and control group are given in Table 5 and 
Fig. 3. According to the in-group comparison, there was 
no statistical difference between the physical well-being, 
social life-family well-being, emotional well-being, func-
tional well-being average scores, and the overall quality 
of life score average in the first and final measurements 
conducted in both groups (p &gt; 0.05). However, although 
there was no significant difference, it was noteworthy 
that the average scores of patients in the therapy group 
increased in the final measurement, while the average 
scores of the control group tended to decrease. According 
to the intra-group comparison, the emotional well-being 
(13.46 ± 5.78), physical well-being (16.71 ±  5.59), and 
the overall quality of life score averages (66.98 ±  17.72) 
of the therapy group obtained in the final measurement 
were found to be statistically significantly higher com-
pared to the control group (p &lt; 0.05).
Table 3  Comparison of some characteristics of therapy and control groups with FACIT-Sp mean scores
* For variables with two categories, Z values are given using Mann Whitney U test, and for variables with three or more categories, X2 values are 
given using Kruskal–Wallis test
Pre-test
Post-test
x∓SD
Z/X2
p
x∓SD
Z/X2
p
Therapy group
Diagnosis time
 &gt; 6 months– ≤ 1 year
85.06 ± 23.46
0.96
0.61
101.76 ± 27.41
0.44
0.64
 &gt; 1–5 years
90.35 ± 27.46
99.22 ± 24.98
Receiving chemotherapy
Yes
84.00 ± 22.05
 − 0.93
0.35
95.59 ± 23.30
1.95
0.12
No
91.45 ± 30.95
122.25 ± 25.77
Receiving radiotherapy
Yes
83.89 ± 22.61
 − 0.99
0.32
98.70 ± 21,29
0.13
0.89
No
93.13 ± 30.08
100.50 ± 47.89
Surgical intervention
Yes
85.08 ± 21.94
 − 0.41
0.68
94.28 ± 21.91
1.78
0.11
No
87.57 ± 31.97
115.50 ± 29.31
Stage of the breast cancer
Stage 1
85.96 ± 29.21
3.54
0.31
101.55 ± 28.35
0.98
0.41
Stage 2
75.89 ± 13.47
91.75 ± 21.04
Stage 3
91.45 ± 23.29
104.45 ± 22.51
Control group
Diagnosis time
 &gt; 6 months– ≤ 1 year
75.27 ± 29.89
1.62
0.20
76.35 ± 27.36
0.60
0.43
 &gt; 1–5 years
88.76 ± 25.36
83.08 ± 28.00
Receiving chemotherapy
Yes
83.62 ± 28.30
 − 0.52
0.59
79.16 ± 27.64
 − 1.05
0.29
No
87.50 ± 3.53
101.00 ± 00.00
Receiving radiotherapy
Yes
82.51 ± 30.09
 − 0.86
0.38
75.49 ± 25.37
 − 1.58
0.11
No
88.06 ± 17.57
99.30 ± 30.43
Operated
Yes
79.38 ± 26.81
 − 1.25
0.21
75.75 ± 28.71
 − 1.29
0.19
No
95.79 ± 26.88
90.66 ± 21.63
Stage of the disease
Stage 1
92.00 ± 34.75
75.05 ± 13.81
Stage 2
81.98 ± 28.91
0.18
0.91
75.31 ± 30.40
1.61
0.44
Stage 3
82.16 ± 21.55
90.35 ± 27.52</paragraph></page><page number="9"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438 
1 3
Page 9 of 12 
438
Discussion
Breast cancer has a spiritual impact on patients, causing them 
to experience spiritual distress. Spiritual distress significantly 
reduces the quality of life of patients. MBT is considered a 
method that can be used to increase physical and psychological 
well-being and quality life of patients with breast cancer, as 
well as making life meaningful. In the current study, the effect 
of MBT on breast cancer patients was examined.
Spirituality is considered a source of strength and sup-
port for improving individuals’ health who are seeking for 
the meaning and purpose of life [28]. Mindfulness-based 
interventions are stated to be effective in reducing psycho-
logical distress and other symptoms in cancer patients [24, 
29]. It was found that mindfulness-based therapy provided 
for breast cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy sig-
nificantly increased the score of the Meaning subscale of 
spiritual well-being [24]. In this study, it was found that 
the average score of the Meaning subscale of the therapy 
group was significantly higher in the last measurement 
compared to the control group. This finding supports the 
knowledge that MBT is considered a way to make life 
meaningful [16]. In addition, it can be concluded that it 
helps breast cancer patients who are questioning and seek-
ing the meaning and purpose of life.
Mindfulness-based interventions are effective in reduc-
ing psychological distress and other symptoms in cancer 
patients [24, 29]. In a previous study, it was found that 
mindfulness-based interventions had no effect on increas-
ing spiritual well-being [7]. In a randomized controlled 
study examining the effect of mindfulness-based cognitive 
therapy in breast cancer patients, it was determined that 
it significantly increased the spiritual well-being levels 
of the patients [25]. In another study, it was determined 
that 1-week MBAT intervention for breast cancer patients 
undergoing chemotherapy significantly decreased the psy-
chological distress and significantly improved the SWB 
in terms of Meaning, Peace, and Faith [24]. Similarly in 
the current study, it was found that the overall spiritual 
well-being (SP-12) score average of the therapy group 
was statistically significantly higher compared to the con-
trol group according to the final measurement. Accord-
ing to the study findings, MBT may have increased the 
level of spiritual well-being by significantly increasing 
Table 4  The overall average score of the spiritual well-being and sub-
scale score averages of the patients in the therapy and control group
Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation, range, number, and 
percentage. Data were analyzed by unpaired t test, independent sam-
ple t test, or paired sample t test as appropriate. Significance level was 
set at p &lt; 0.05, and values in bold are significant
* Independent sample t test
** Paired sample t test
Control group
x± SD
Therapy group
x± SD
t*
p
Meaning
   First measurement
10.15 ±  3.80
11.78 ±  3.15
1.87
0.06
   Final measurement
10.06 ±  3.79
12.25 ±  3.03
2.56
0.01*
   t**/p
0.09/0.92
 − 0.70/0.48
Peace
   First measurement
8.03 ±  3.58
8.43 ±  3.41
0.46
0.64
   Final measurement
7.09 ±  2.77
8.59 ±  3.88
1.79
0.07
   t**/p
1.13/0.26
 − 1.48/0.88
Faith
   First measurement
10.63 ±  4.58
10.65 ±  5.02
0.01
0.98
   Final measurement
9.93 ±  4.77
10.71 ± 4.15
0.70
0.48
   t**/p
0.68/0.49
 − 0.64/0.95
Total
   First measurement
28.81 ±  10.15
30.87 ±  9.22
0.85
0.39
   Final measurement
27.09 ±  9.51
31.56 ± 8.90
1.95
0.04*
   t**/p
0.74/0.46
 − 0.31/0.75
Table 5  The in-group and intra-group comparisons of the quality of 
life mean scores and subscales of the patients in the therapy and con-
trol group
Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation, range, number, and 
percentage. Data were analyzed by unpaired t test, independent sam-
ple t test, or paired sample t test as appropriate. Significance level was 
set at p &lt; 0.05, and values in bold are significant
PWB physical well-being, SWB social/family well-being, EWB emo-
tional well-being, FWB functional well-being
* Independent sample t test
** Paired sample t test
Control group
x± SD
Therapy group
x± SD
t*
p
PWB
   First measurement
13.48 ± 6.48
15.81 ± 6.66
1.42
0.15
   Final measurement
12.87 ± 6.72
16.71 ± 5.59
2.49
0.01
   t**/p
0.41/0.68
 − 0.66/0.50
SWB
   First measurement
19.13 ±  5.49
20.16 ±  5.97
0.72
0.47
   Final measurement
19.06 ± 5.74
20.36 ± 5.38
0.94
0.35
   t**/p
0.06/0.95
 − 0.15/0.88
EWB
   First measurement
9.75 ±5.22
12.90 ±5.40
2.39
0.02
   Final measurement
8.75 ±  5.14
13.46 ±  5.78
3.47
0.00
   t**/p
0.87/0.38
 − 0.39/0.69
FWB
   First measurement
13.03 ±  6.82
14.15 ±  7.56
0.63
0.53
   Final measurement
12.33 ±  7.00
16.75 ±  6.33
2.66
0.10
   t**/p
0.36/0.72
 − 1.60/0.12
Total
   First measurement
55.22 ±  18.26
63.06 ±  19.74
1.66
0.10
   Final measurement
53.03 ±  18.65
66.98 ±  17.72
3.090
0.00
   t**/p
 − 0.86/0.60
0.52/0.39</paragraph></page><page number="10"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438
1 3
438 
Page 10 of 12
the Meaning subscale of spirituality in particular. The H1 
hypothesis of the study was confirmed.
Patients perceiving the disease as posing a life-threatening 
risk may cause them to experience crisis since it influences 
them in physical, psychosocial, behavioral, and spiritual 
aspects [9]. Mindfulness interventions are considered a way 
to ensure physical and psychological well-being in patients 
[16]. In this study, it was determined that the average physi-
cal well-being, emotional well-being subscales, and total 
FACT-G scores of the therapy group in the final measure-
ment were statistically significantly higher compared to the 
first measurement results. In a previous study, it was found 
that 6-week mindfulness-based reduction program increased 
the level of emotional well-being of breast cancer patients 
[30]. In other studies [20, 31, 32] and systematic reviews [3, 
6], mindfulness-based interventions were found to reduce the 
fatigue levels of breast cancer patients. In other systematic 
reviews and meta-analysis studies, it was found that mindful-
ness-based interventions had a significant therapeutic effect 
on sleep [3, 31]. It is reported that the increase in the level of 
mindfulness in individuals mediates an increase in the quality 
of life in addition to an increase in spiritual and mental health 
[33]. In recent studies conducted with breast cancer patients, it 
has been determined that mindfulness-based stress reduction 
program has a positive effect on the quality of life of patients 
[21, 22, 25]. It may be concluded that this result supports 
the knowledge [16] that mindfulness and mindfulness-based 
initiatives are seen as a way to increase the physical and psy-
chological well-being of individuals, helping them live better. 
The H2 hypothesis of the study was confirmed.
Conclusions
In this study, which was carried out in order to determine 
the effect of MBT on spiritual well-being in patients with 
breast cancer, it was determined that MBT program applied 
for 8 weeks increased the level of spiritual well-being and 
quality of life of patients. Nurses who care for patients with 
breast cancer can increase their quality of life by increas-
ing their spiritual well-being during surgery and other treat-
ment processes by using MBT intervention from the first 
Fig. 2  The overall average 
score of the spiritual well-being 
(SP-12) and subscale of the both 
groups
Fig. 3  The overall average 
score of the FACT-G total and 
subscale of the both groups</paragraph></page><page number="11"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438 
1 3
Page 11 of 12 
438
diagnosis. So nurses should be encouraged to perform MBT 
sessions to make it a widespread practice, and to regularly 
evaluate the outcomes.
Limitations
The research has some limitations. Since the study 
was conducted during the COVID-19 pandemic and 
the participants were a risky group, MBT could not be 
applied face to face. Therefore, MBT, which requires 
close communication with patients, has been challenging 
for researchers and patients. In addition, since the 
patients attended from their homes, the noise in the home 
environment and their role in the home negatively affected 
their focus on the MBT intervention.
Acknowledgements We are sisterly grateful to the patients for their 
participation and cooperation.
Author contribution All authors contributed to the study conception 
and design. Conceptualization: Hatice Öner Cengiz. Methodology: 
Hatice Öner Cengiz. Data curation: Berna Bayir and Mehmet Demirtaş. 
Formal analysis and investigation: Serap Sayar and Berna Bayir. 
Writing—original draft preparation: Hatice Öner Cengiz. Writing—
review and editing: Hatice Öner Cengiz, Berna Bayir, Serap Sayar, and 
Mehmet Demirtaş. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.
Data availability The data that support the findings of this study are 
available upon reasonable request.
Declarations 
Ethics approval Ethical approval was obtained from the ethics 
committee (KTO Karatay University Non-pharmaceutical and Non-
medical Device Research Ethics Committee Chairmanship. Date 
September 07, 2021 registration number E-41901325–050.99–
14950/2021/029). In the study, the articles in the Declaration of 
Helsinki were complied with. This study was registered in the 
Clinical Trial Registry (registration number NCT05057078) prior 
to data collection process. All participants were thoroughly briefed 
on the research process before providing their consent, and all were 
ensured that there would be no consequences in case they choose 
to withdraw at any stage. Verbal and written consent was obtained 
from all participants. The study was conducted in accordance with 
the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) 2010 
guidelines.
Consent to participate Informed consent was obtained from all indi-
vidual participants included in the study.
Consent for publication Patients signed informed consent regarding 
publishing their data.
Conflict of interest The authors declare no competing interests.
Ethics committee permission KTO Karatay University Non-pharma-
ceutical and Non-medical Device Research Ethics Committee Chair-
manship. Date: September 07, 2021 E-41901325–050.99-Number of 
decision: 14950/2021/029.
References
 1. Duval A, Davis CG, Khoo EL, Romanow H, Shergill Y, Rice D, 
Smith AM, Poulin PA, Collins B (2022) Mindfulness-based stress 
reduction and cognitive function among breast cancer survivors: a 
randomized controlled trial. Cancer 128(13):2520–2528. https:// 
doi. org/ 10. 1002/ cncr. 34209
 2. Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, Laversanne M, Soerjomataram I, 
Jemal A, Bray F (2021) Global cancer statistics 2020: GLOBO-
CAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 can-
cers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin 71:209–249. https:// doi. 
org/ 10. 3322/ caac. 21660
 3. Jing S, Zhang A, Chen Y, Shen C, Currin-McCulloch J, Zhu 
C (2021) Mindfulness-based interventions for breast cancer 
patients in China across outcome domains: a systematic review 
and meta-analysis of the Chinese literature. Support Care Cancer 
29(10):5611–5621. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s00520- 021- 06166-0
 4. Lee Y, Baek JM, Jeon YW, Im EO (2019) Illness perception and 
sense of well-being in breast cancer patients. Patient Prefer Adher-
ence 13:1557–1567. https:// doi. org/ 10. 2147/ PPA. S2255 61
 5. Würtzen H, Dalton SO, Christensen J, Andersen KK, Elsass 
P, Flyger HL, Pedersen AE, Sumbundu A, Steding-Jensen M, 
Johansen C (2015) Effect of mindfulness-based stress reduction on 
somatic symptoms, distress, mindfulness and spiritual wellbeing 
in women with breast cancer: results of a randomized controlled 
trial. Acta oncol 54(5):712–719. https:// doi. org/ 10. 3109/ 02841 
86X. 2014. 997371
 6. Chang YC, Yeh TL, Chang YM, Hu WY (2021) Short-term effects 
of randomized mindfulness-based ıntervention in female breast 
cancer survivors: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Can-
cer Nurs 44(6):E703–E714. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1097/ NCC. 00000 
00000 000889
 7. Cramer H, Lauche R, Paul A, Dobos G (2012) Mindfulness-based stress 
reduction for breast cancer—a systematic review and meta-analysis. 
Curr Oncol 19(5):e343–e352. https:// doi. org/ 10. 3747/ co. 19. 1016
 8. Jiang N, Zhang YX, Zhao J, Shi HY, Wang T, Jin W, Wang JW, 
Yu JM (2022) The mediator role of stigma in the association of 
mindfulness and social engagement among breast cancer survivors 
in China. Support Care Cancer 30(6):5007–5015. https:// doi. org/ 
10. 1007/ s00520- 022- 06882-1
 9. Yilmaz M, OnerCengiz H (2020) The relationship between spiritual 
well-being and quality of life in cancer survivors. Palliat Support 
Care 18(1):55–62. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1017/ S1478 95151 90004 64
 10. Dydjow-Bendek D, Zagozdzon P (2022) Breast cancer and spiritu-
ality among women in poland: a case-control study. J Relig Health 
61(6):4288–4301. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s10943- 022- 01584-8
 11. Devi MK, Fong K (2019) Spiritual experiences of women with 
breast cancer in singapore: a qualitative study. Asia Pac J Oncol 
Nurs 6(2):145–150. https:// doi. org/ 10. 4103/ apjon. apjon_ 77_ 18
 12. Silva G, Reis D, Miranda T, Melo R, Coutinho M, Paschoal G, 
Chaves É (2019) Religious/spiritual coping and spiritual distress 
in people with cancer. Rev Bras Enferm 72(6):1534–1540. https:// 
doi. org/ 10. 1590/ 0034- 7167- 2018- 0585
 13. Hulett JM, Johnstone B, Armer JM, Deroche C, Millspaugh R, 
Millspaugh J (2021) Associations between religious and spiritual 
variables and neuroimmune activity in survivors of breast can-
cer: a feasibility study. Support Care Cancer 29(11):6421–6429. 
https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s00520- 021- 06224-7
 14 Puchalski C (2012) Spirituality in the cancer trajectory. Ann 
Oncol 3:49–55. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1093/ annonc/ mds088
 15. Kamijo Y, Miyamura T (2020) Spirituality and associated factors 
among cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy. Jpn J Nurs Sci 
17(1):e12276. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1111/ jjns. 12276
 16. Dehghan M, Namjoo Z, MohammadiAkbarabadi F, Fooladi 
Z, Zakeri MA (2021) The relationship between anxiety, stress,</paragraph></page><page number="12"><paragraph>Supportive Care in Cancer (2023) 31:438
1 3
438 
Page 12 of 12
spiritual health, and mindfulness among patients undergoing 
hemodialysis: a survey during the COVID-19 outbreak in South-
east Iran. Health Sci Rep 4(4):e461. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1002/ hsr2. 
461
 17. Bai M, Lazenby M, Jeon S, Dixon J, McCorkle R (2015) Explor-
ing the relationship between spiritual well-being and quality of 
life among patients newly diagnosed with advanced cancer. Palliat 
Support Care 13(4):927–935. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1017/ S1478 95151 
40008 20
 18. Gonçalves JPB, Lucchetti G, Menezes PR, Vallada H (2017) Com-
plementary religious and spiritual interventions in physical health 
and quality of life: a systematic review of randomized controlled 
clinical trials. PLoS One 12(10):e0186539
 19. Ferreira-Valente A, Sharma S, Torres S, Smothers Z, Pais-Ribeiro 
J, Abbott JH, Jensen MP (2022) Correction to: Does religiosity/
spirituality play a role in function, pain-related beliefs, and coping 
in patients with chronic pain? A systematic review. J Relig Health 
61(3):2386–2387. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s10943- 019- 00928-1
 20. Lengacher CA, Gruss LF, Kip KE et al (2021) Mindfulness-based 
stress reduction for breast cancer survivors (MBSR(BC)): evaluat-
ing mediators of psychological and physical outcomes in a large 
randomized controlled trial. J Behav Med 44(5):591–604. https:// 
doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s10865- 021- 00214-0
 21. Jagielski CH, Tucker DC, Dalton SO, Mrug S, Würtzen H, 
Johansen C (2020) Personality as a predictor of well-being in a 
randomized trial of a mindfulness-based stress reduction of Dan-
ish women with breast cancer. J Psychosoc Oncol 38(1):4–19. 
https:// doi. org/ 10. 1080/ 07347 332. 2019. 16265 24
 22. Zhang Q, Zhao H, Zheng Y (2019) Effectiveness of mindfulness-
based stress reduction (MBSR) on symptom variables and health-
related quality of life in breast cancer patients-a systematic review 
and meta-analysis. Support Care Cancer 27(3):771–781. https:// 
doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s00520- 018- 4570-x
 23. Robertson MC, Cox-Martin E, Liao Y, Flores SA, Shegog R, 
Markham CM, Fujimoto K, Durand CP, Brewster A, Lyons EJ, 
Basen-Engquist KM (2022) Acceptance- and mindfulness-based 
techniques for physical activity promotion in breast cancer sur-
vivors: a qualitative study. Support Care Cancer 30(1):465–473. 
https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s00520- 021- 06428-x
 24. Joshi AM, Mehta SA, Pande N, Mehta AO, Randhe KS (2021) 
Effect of Mindfulness-Based Art Therapy (MBAT) on psycho-
logical distress and spiritual wellbeing in breast cancer patients 
undergoing chemotherapy. Indian J Palliat Care 27(4):552–560. 
https:// doi. org/ 10. 25259/ IJPC_ 133_ 21
 25. Park S, Sato Y, Takita Y, Tamura N, Ninomiya A, Kosugi T, Sado 
M, Nakagawa A, Takahashi M, Hayashida T, Fujisawa D (2020) 
Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy for psychological distress, 
fear of cancer recurrence, fatigue, spiritual well-being, and quality 
of life in patients with breast cancer—a randomized controlled 
trial. J Pain Symptom Manage 60(2):381–389. https:// doi. org/ 10. 
1016/j. jpain symman. 2020. 02. 017
 26 Faul F, Erdfelder E, Buchner A, Lang AG (2009) Statistical power 
analyses using G*Power 3.1: tests for correlation and regression 
analyses. Behav Res Methods 41(4):1149–1160. https:// doi. org/ 
10. 3758/ BRM. 41.4. 1149
 27. Peterman AH, Fitchett G, Brady MJ, Hernandez L, Cella D (2002) 
Measuring spiritual well-being in people with cancer: the func-
tional assessment of chronic illness therapy—Spiritual Well-being 
Scale (FACIT-Sp). Ann Behav Med 24(1):49–58. https:// doi. org/ 
10. 1207/ S1532 4796A BM2401_ 06
 28. Al-Natour A, Al Momani SM, Qandil A (2017) The relationship 
between spirituality and quality of life of Jordanian women diag-
nosed with breast cancer. J Relig Health 56(6):2096–2108. https:// 
doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s10943- 017- 0370-8
 29. Cillessen L, Johannsen M, Speckens AE, Zachariae R (2019) 
Mindfulness-based interventions for psychological and physical 
health outcomes in cancer patients and survivors: a systematic 
review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Psy-
chooncology 28:2257–2269. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1002/ pon. 5214
 30. Lengacher CA, Johnson-Mallard V, Post-White J, Moscoso MS, 
Jacobsen PB, Klein TW, Kip KE (2009) Randomized controlled 
trial of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) for survivors 
of breast cancer. Psychooncology 18:1261–1272. https:// doi. org/ 
10. 1002/ pon. 1529
 31. Haller H, Winkler MM, Klose P, Dobos G, Kümmel S, Cramer H 
(2017) Mindfulness-based interventions for women with breast can-
cer: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis. Acta Oncol 
56(12):1665–1676. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1080/ 02841 86X. 2017. 13428 62
 32. Van Der Lee ML, Garssen B (2012) Mindfulness-based cognitive 
therapy reduces chronic cancer-related fatigue: a treatment study. 
Psychooncology 21(3):264–272. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1002/ pon. 1890
 33. Greeson JM, Webber DM, Smoski MJ, Brantley JG, Ekblad AG, 
Suarez EC et al (2011) Changes in spirituality partly explain 
health-related quality of life outcomes after mindfulness-based 
stress reduction. J Behav Med 34:508–518. https:// doi. org/ 10. 
1007/ s10865- 011- 9332-x
 34. Aktürk Ü, Erci B, Araz M (2017) Functional evaluation of treat-
ment of chronic disease: validity and reliability of the Turkish 
version of the Spiritual Well-Being Scale. Palliat Support Care 
15:684–692
Publisher's note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to 
jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.
Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds 
exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the 
author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted 
manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of 
such publishing agreement and applicable law.</paragraph></page></document>