<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document><page number="1"><paragraph>Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice 49 (2022) 101686
Available online 3 November 2022
1744-3881/© 2022 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.
Effects of an online mindfulness-based intervention on Fear of Cancer 
Recurrence and quality of life among Chinese breast cancer survivors 
Li Peng a, Ying Yang b, Muyu Chen a, Chen Xu a, Yanli Chen a, Rongqian Liu a, Xiaozhen Cao b, 
Min Li a,* 
a Department of Military Psychology, Army Medical University, Chongqing, 400038, China 
b Department of Breast and Thyroid Surgery, Southwest Hospital, Army Medical University, Chongqing, 400038, China   
A R T I C L E  I N F O   
Keywords: 
Mindfulness-based intervention 
Fear of cancer recurrence 
Breast cancer survivors 
A B S T R A C T   
Objective: Mindfulness-based interventions (MBIs) targeting cancer-related emotions and quality of life have 
attracted extensive attention in recent years. The purpose of the current study was to assess the feasibility and 
acceptability of an online mindfulness-based intervention and examine its effects on Chinese breast cancer 
survivors. 
Methods: Sixty-five breast cancer survivors were randomized to either an online MBI or to wait for the next 
available program. The control group received usual care, while the intervention group also received six weeks of 
online MBI training. Participants completed the Short Form of the Fear of Cancer Recurrence Inventory (FCRI- 
SF), Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ) and European Organization for Research and Treatment of 
Cancer questionnaire (EORTC-QLQ-C30) at baseline (T1), immediately after the intervention (postintervention: 
T2) and 1 month later (1-month postintervention: T3). In addition, answers provided to questions about the 
experience of participating in the course were analyzed. 
Results: Compared with the control group, the mindfulness, emotional and cognitive function of the MBI group 
was significantly improved after the intervention, and the FCR of breast cancer survivors was significantly 
alleviated. These effects were still significant 1 month after the end of the intervention. Additionally, participants 
were satisfied with the online MBI through the qualitative survey. 
Conclusion: This online MBI showed promise for Chinese breast cancer survivors, facilitating a reduction in FCR 
and improving their quality of life. The results of our study indicated that online MBI treatment could offer a 
scalable approach to manage FCR and maintain mental health for breast cancer survivors.   
Breast cancer is the most commonly diagnosed cancer with the 
highest cancer incidence rate and fatality rate for women worldwide [1]. 
With the progress of modern medicine and the improvement of cancer 
diagnosis and treatment, the survival rate of breast cancer patients is 
exhibiting a rapid upward trend [2]. Meanwhile, the demand for 
follow-up rehabilitation and improvement in quality of life has become 
an important issue in public health. Currently, it has been reported that 
breast cancer survivors have the most common 5-year survival rate 
among all cancer types in China [3]. 
Although improvement in the early diagnosis and treatment of breast 
cancer has greatly prolonged the life span of patients, breast cancer 
survivors face chronic psychological stress and are vulnerable to nega-
tive emotions such as fear and anxiety [4]. Fear of cancer recurrence 
(FCR) is the fear that cancer could return or progress in the same place or 
another part of the body [5] and has become the most prominent and 
prevalent emotional characteristic for breast cancer survivors [6]. Ac-
cording to previous studies, approximately 39%–97% of breast cancer 
survivors have experienced FCR [7]. Mild or temporary FCR has a 
certain protective effect on patients, as it can prompt individuals to pay 
attention to physical changes and detect signs of cancer recurrence in a 
timely manner, which is conducive to early intervention. However, 
excessive FCR will not only reduce patients’ treatment compliance but 
also affect their prognosis of the disease, thereby even increasing the risk 
of recurrence [8]. Additionally, breast cancer survivors with high FCR 
engage in more medical behaviors and thus consume more medical re-
sources [9]. Moreover, all aspects of patients’ health-related quality of 
life, including physical, psychological, and social aspects, are continu-
ously affected by psychosocial symptoms and side effects of cancer 
* Corresponding author. No.30, Gaotanyan Road, Shapingba District, Chongqing, 400038, China. 
E-mail address: limin52267@tmmu.edu.cn (M. Li).  
Contents lists available at ScienceDirect 
Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice 
journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/ctcp 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ctcp.2022.101686 
Received 31 August 2022; Received in revised form 30 September 2022; Accepted 29 October 2022</paragraph></page><page number="2"><paragraph>Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice 49 (2022) 101686
2
treatment [10]. Tran and colleagues surveyed 333 long-term breast 
cancer survivors and found that FCR significantly and negatively 
impacted emotional functioning, and a higher FCR level may impair 
overall health-related quality of life in long-term breast cancer survivors 
[11]. 
Given the negative impact of FCR on quality of life, there has been 
growing interest in developing and conducting interventions to manage 
the FCR faced by breast cancer survivors. Extensive research has been 
carried out to alleviate breast cancer survivors’ FCR through psycho-
logical interventions such as cognitive behavioral therapy, stress man-
agement, and mindfulness-based interventions (MBIs) [12,13]. 
Recently, MBIs have demonstrated benefits and have been found to 
moderate the negative impact of FCR on the quality of life of breast 
cancer survivors. Mindfulness is the practice of directing focused 
attention toward experiences occurring in the present moment and 
empowering a state of awareness without judgment or resistance. MBIs 
can regulate potential biological variables related to stress, such as im-
mune function, hypothalamic pituitary adrenaline regulation and 
autonomic nervous system activity [14]. Among the interventions, 
mindfulness-based training was listed as the first and best recommended 
item for the treatment of anxiety and depression in cancer patients and 
measures to improve the quality of life by the International Association 
for Integrated Clinical Cancer Care in 2014. A randomized controlled 
trial of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) therapy for stage 0 to 
III breast cancer showed improvements in fear of recurrence, depression, 
anxiety, physical functioning, physical role functioning, energy, and 
pain [15]. This evidence indicated that MBSR was recommended to 
support survivors of breast cancer. 
However, owing to service costs and patient mobility restrictions, the 
utilization and availability of MBIs for breast cancer survivors has been 
limited. Compared with face-to-face interventions, online interventions 
have a number of advantages. Online MBIs may be an acceptable 
alternative to face-to-face interventions, and online psychotherapeutic 
interventions have been demonstrated to be more suitable for in-
dividuals with psychological symptoms and physical symptoms [16]. 
Therefore, providing online therapies for breast cancer survivors after 
routine care has been shown to be a promising approach to address these 
challenges. However, although some foreign researchers have investi-
gated the effect of online MBIs in high-income countries, little is known 
about the efficacy of this approach among Chinese breast cancer 
survivors. 
Given the proven value of MBIs in promoting mental health out-
comes in other populations, it is important to investigate the potential 
benefits of their online form among Chinese breast cancer survivors. 
Therefore, the purpose of this study was to assess the long-term effect of 
an MBI on FCR and quality of life among breast cancer survivors and to 
explore a feasible and propagable intervention scheme to reduce the 
FCR among breast cancer survivors and promote their quality of life. 
1. Methods 
1.1. Participants 
All participants were recruited from the First Affiliated Hospital of 
Army Medical University from November 2019 to January 2020. The 
inclusion criteria were as follows: (1) women diagnosed with stage I-IV 
breast cancer; (2) women aged 18–65 years; (3) women with a junior 
middle school education or above; (4) completion of all treatments with 
the exception of hormonal or Herceptin therapy and no cancer recur-
rence or metastasis; and (5) no mindfulness-based training experience. 
The exclusion criteria for all participants were (1) current use of psy-
chotropic medications; (2) severe cognitive impairment or mental dis-
order; and (3) inability to complete scale evaluation and mindfulness- 
based training. Finally, a total of 65 breast cancer survivors were 
recruited. Before entering the group, each participant was phone- 
screened for eligibility. The intervention settings and specific re-
quirements were explained. Two patients voluntarily withdrew from the 
course because they could not participate in the whole intervention, 2 
patients did not finish chemoradiotherapy, and 1 was receiving psy-
chotherapy; ultimately, 60 breast cancer survivors were recruited. The 
Fig. 1. Flowchart of recruitment and dropout.  
L. Peng et al.</paragraph></page><page number="3"><paragraph>Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice 49 (2022) 101686
3
patients were randomly divided into the experimental group (n = 30) 
and the waiting group (n = 30). In addition to usual care, the experi-
mental group received an online MBI, while the control group received 
routine usual care. Two participants in the intervention group and 1 in 
the control group dropped out during the study. The study participant 
flowchart is illustrated in Fig. 1. 
1.2. Procedures 
Each participant enrolled in this study voluntarily took part in the 
study and signed a consent form. Participants were surveyed online by 
demographic questions and self-report measures to assess their level of 
mindfulness, FCR, and quality of life at baseline (preintervention: T1), 
immediately after the intervention group completed their mindfulness- 
based training (postintervention: T2) and 1 month later (1-month 
postintervention: T3). All participants were administered the same 
survey without the baseline demographic questions. This study was 
registered 
in 
the 
Chinese 
Clinical 
Trials 
Registry 
ChiCTR–OOC–17012132. Ethical approval was obtained from the Ethics 
Committee of Army Medical University of China. 
1.3. Interventions 
Based on the MBSR protocol developed by Ref. [17] and 
mindfulness-based cancer recovery (MBCR) [18], this course was 
administered online in a 6-week group structured intervention with 
weekly 1.5-h meetings to guide participants in practicing, integrating, 
and applying mindfulness in their everyday lives. Apart from the weekly 
meetings, the intervention training also included assignments for daily 
home practice (30 min per day) accompanied by the recordings of the 5P 
Medical App (an app to promote mind and brain health and cultivate 
happiness). The app recorded whether the participants had completed 
the practice. The specific mindfulness intervention programs are shown 
in Table 1. 
1.4. Quantitative measures 
Demographic characteristics (including age, marital status, educa-
tion level, employment status, and yearly family income) and clinical 
information (including time since cancer diagnosis, TNM stage and 
cancer treatment received) were assessed. 
The Short Form of the Fear of Cancer Recurrence Inventory 
(FCRI-SF): The original scale has a total of 42 questions, including 7 
factors (trigger, severity, psychological stress, coping strategies, func-
tional impairment, self-awareness and sense of security) [19]. Due to the 
high positive correlation between the severity factor and the total FCR 
score, the severity factor is directly used as the short version in many 
studies. Therefore, the short form of the FCRI with 9 items was used to 
assess the severity of invasive thinking related to FCR in this study [20]. 
Each item was rated on a Likert scale from 0 ("none" or "never") to 4 
("many” or "always"). A higher score indicated a higher level of FCR. The 
Cronbach’s α coefficient in this sample was 0.865. 
Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ): This 39-item scale 
was used to assess individuals’ inclination toward experiencing mind-
fulness [21]. The participants were asked to rate on a 5-point scale (1 =
"ever true", 5 = "always true"), with higher scores indicating more 
mindfulness. This scale includes 5 dimensions: acting with awareness, 
nonjudgment of inner experience, nonreaction to inner experience, 
describing, and observing. Cronbach’s α coefficient in this study was 
0.897. 
European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer 
questionnaire (EORTC-QLQ-C30): This 30-item questionnaire is 
widely used to evaluate the quality of life of patients with cancer, 
including 5 functional scales (physical function, role function, cognitive 
function, emotional function and social function), 3 symptom scales 
(fatigue, pain, nausea and vomiting), a two-item general health and 
quality of life (QoL) scale, and 6 single symptoms (dyspnea, insomnia, 
loss of appetite, constipation, diarrhea and economic difficulties) [22]. 
Among the 30 items, the first 28 items are scored on a 4-point Likert 
scale (1 = "not at all", 2 = "a little", 3 = "quite a lot" and 4 = "very much"), 
and the two items on the global health/QoL scale are scored on a 7-point 
linear analog scale. The higher the scores on the functioning and global 
QoL subscales, the better the health status and QoL. However, the higher 
the scores on the symptom subscales, the worse the QoL. In this study, 
the symptom subscales were not considered. The Cronbach’s α coeffi-
cient was 0.962 in this sample. 
1.5. Qualitative measures 
Qualitative course feedback was obtained postintervention from 
participants via a feedback survey. This consisted of 4 questions: (a) 
How much does mindfulness help you in your daily life? (b) How often 
do you practice mindfulness? (c) If you feel better, how much do you 
benefit from mindfulness? (d) Which mindfulness technique helps you 
most? 
1.6. Data analyses 
All data were analyzed by IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, version 
22.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). Group differences in demographic 
characteristics and clinical information were tested using chi-square 
tests. Baseline levels of FCR and mindfulness in the control and inter-
vention groups were compared using three independent measures t tests. 
For the different analyses of corresponding variables at each time point 
between the two groups, repeated measures analysis of variance was 
conducted. The level of significance was set at 0.05. Common method 
Table 1 
Six-week mindfulness-based intervention program.  
Week 
Theme 
Mindfulness-based Intervention 
1st 
week 
Introduction to Mindfulness 
Introduce mindfulness/mindfulness drinking practice, then discussion and response regarding this practice (formal practice following 
the audio and bringing mindfulness to daily life, e.g., bathing, walking, brushing teeth and dressing) 
2nd 
week 
Coping with Difficult Emotions 
Share and discuss homework/core of MBCT/recognize own automatic thoughts/coping with fear of recurrence and other difficult 
emotions/Set homework (formal practice following the audio, record the delightful event and difficult event) 
3rd 
week 
Mindfulness in Relationships 
Share and discuss homework/mindfulness and interrelationships/impart mindfulness communication skills/mindfulness listening 
practice/record the difficult relationship/set homework (formal practice following the audio, and complete Five-Finger Gratitude 
Exercise) 
4th 
week 
Reaction and Response to 
Stress 
Share and discuss homework/how stress impacts physical and mental health/explain stress and recognize the reaction to stress of 
participants/attempt to “view” stress event by mindfulness thoughts/set homework (formal practice following the audio, record the 
delightful event) 
5th 
week 
Coping with Cancer-related 
Symptoms 
Share and discuss homework/coping with cancer-related symptoms and treatment side effects with mindfulness/mindfulness self-care/ 
differentiating treatment and cure/set homework (formal practice following the audio, practice “self-compassion, common humanity, 
accept pain”) 
6th 
week 
End and Setting Out 
Share and discuss homework/review and summarize the topics of the curriculum/share and discuss curriculum/ending  
L. Peng et al.</paragraph></page><page number="4"><paragraph>Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice 49 (2022) 101686
4
variance was established using Harman’s single-factor test. Exploratory 
factor analysis showed that the interpretation rate of the first factor was 
10.90%, which was &lt;40% of the reference value and indicated that 
there was no serious common method bias. 
2. Results 
2.1. Demographic and clinical characteristics of participants 
No statistically significant differences were revealed in terms of age, 
marital status, education level, employment status, yearly family in-
come, time since cancer diagnosis, TNM stage or cancer treatment 
received between the MBI group and the control group at baseline, 
indicating similar demographic and clinical characteristics across the 
two groups. The details are shown in Table 2. 
2.2. Effects of MBI on all variables 
As for the baseline (T1), there were no statistically significant 
between-group differences in mindfulness (t = 0.33, P = 0.74), FCR (t =
0.50, P = 0.62), physical function (t = −0.25, P = 0.81), role function (t 
= −0.59, P = 0.56), emotional function (t = −0.58, P = 0.57), cognitive 
function (t = −1.04, P = 0.31), social function (t = −1.13, P = 0.26), or 
global QoL (t = −0.50, P = 0.62). In addition, the results of repeated 
measures of ANOVA suggested that there existed significant differences 
between the MBI group and the control group over time in mindfulness 
(F = 9.12, P = 0.00), FCR (F = 9.63, P = 0.00), emotional function (F =
11.61, P = 0.00) and cognitive function (F = 4.21, P = 0.04); the 
interaction effect between two groups were significant as well in 
mindfulness (F = 3.74,P = 0.03), FCR (F = 5.32,P = 0.01), emotional 
function (F = 6.61,P = 0.00) and cognitive function (F = 4.80,P = 0.01) 
(Table 3). 
2.3. Qualitative results 
Fig. 2 indicates that through the qualitative survey with the inter-
vention group, 60.71% of the patients thought that mindfulness was 
Table 2 
Demographic and clinical characteristics of participants.   
MBI group 
(n = 28) 
Control 
group 
(n=29) 
χ2 
Value 
P Value 
(two- 
tailed) 
Age   
0.05 
0.98 
30≤age&lt;40 
6(21.4%) 
6(20.7%)   
40≤age&lt;50 
15(53.6%) 
15(51.7%)   
age≥50 
7(25%) 
8(27.6%)   
Marital status 
1.07 
0.59 
married 
23(82.1%) 
25(86.2%) 
divorced 
4(14.3%) 
4(13.8%) 
widowed 
1(3.6%) 
0(0%) 
Education level 
1.11 
0.58 
junior high school 
6(21.4%) 
5(17.2%) 
high school 
15(53.6%) 
13(44.8%) 
university and above 
7(25%) 
11(37.9%) 
Employment status 
0.22 
0.90 
working 
10(35.7%) 
12(41.4%) 
unemployed 
8(28.6%) 
8(27.6%) 
retired 
10(35.7%) 
9(31%) 
Yearly family income (RMB) 
1.11 
0.78 
&lt;50,000 
8(28.6%) 
7(24.1%) 
50,000≤income&lt;100,000 
13(46.4%) 
11(37.9%) 
100,000≤income&lt;300,000 
5(17.9%) 
8(27.6%) 
≥300,000 
2(7.1%) 
3(10.3%) 
Time since cancer diagnosis 
0.33 
0.85 
time&lt;2 years 
13(46.4%) 
15(51.7%) 
2 years ≤ time&lt; 5 years 
12(42.9%) 
12(41.4%) 
5 years ≤ time&lt;10 years 
3(10.7%) 
2(6.9%) 
TNM stage 
3.71 
0.30 
I 
6(21.4%) 
3(10.3%) 
II 
15(53.6%) 
22(75.9%) 
III 
6(21.4%) 
4(13.8%) 
IV 
1(3.6%) 
0(0%) 
Cancer treatment received 
2.54 
0.28 
mastectomy 
20(71.4%) 
25(86.2%) 
conservative therapy 
6(21.4%) 
2(6.9%) 
mastectomy + breast 
construction 
2(7.1%) 
2(6.9%)  
Table 3 
Mindfulness, FCR and quality of life outcomes at three time points for the two groups.   
Time 
Group 
Group main effect 
Time main effect 
Time × Group Interaction effect 
Mean(SD) 
F 
P 
F 
P 
F 
P 
MBI group (n = 28) 
Control group (n = 29) 
Mindfulness 
T1 
117.89(6.05) 
117.34(6.35) 
9.12 
0.00 
3.44 
0.04 
3.74 
0.03 
T2 
124.36 (6.92) 
117.83 (6.96)   
T3 
123.14 (11.15) 
116.03 (10.65)   
FCR 
T1 
14.00(4.26) 
13.38(5.10) 
9.63 
0.00 
3.37 
0.04 
5.32 
0.00 
T2 
10.61(4.30) 
13.97(4.99)   
T3 
9.79(4.40) 
13.76(2.05)   
Physical function 
T1 
78.33(12.78) 
79.08(10.04) 
0.04 
0.85 
1.97 
0.14 
0.16 
0.85 
T2 
78.33(12.52) 
78.16(10.06)   
T3 
83.10(12.63) 
81.38(14.52)   
Role function 
T1 
80.36(18.73) 
83.33(19.42) 
0.88 
0.35 
0.27 
0.76 
1.27 
0.29 
T2 
79.76(20.47) 
87.93(17.19)   
T3 
85.71(18.54) 
82.76(18.08)   
Emotional function 
T1 
69.94(16.25) 
72.41(16.08) 
11.61 
0.00 
2.62 
0.08 
6.61 
0.00 
T2 
83.33(14.87) 
69.25(8.94)   
T3 
80.95(13.20) 
70.12(9.05)   
Cognitive function 
T1 
67.26(17.85) 
71.84(15.50) 
4.21 
0.04 
2.32 
0.10 
4.80 
0.01 
T2 
79.76(9.47) 
70.69(13.10)   
T3 
77.98(13.65) 
67.82(16.63)   
Social function 
T1 
76.79(15.27) 
81.61(16.87) 
0.93 
0.34 
0.20 
0.82 
0.18 
0.84 
T2 
80.36(17.00) 
82.18(19.38)   
T3 
79.17(20.09) 
79.89(20.11)   
Global QoL 
T1 
69.05(16.49) 
71.26(17.05) 
0.14 
0.71 
0.60 
0.55 
0.16 
0.85 
T2 
72.32(22.11) 
71.26(15.04)   
T3 
66.67(24.00) 
69.25(22.17)   
Note. T1: pre-intervention, T2: immediately post-intervention, T3: 1 month post-intervention. Global QoL: global quality of life. 
L. Peng et al.</paragraph></page><page number="5"><paragraph>Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice 49 (2022) 101686
5
very helpful in their daily life; 82.14% (17.86% + 28.57% + 35.71%) of 
the patients performed mindfulness exercises at least three times a week; 
and 75% of the patients thought their improvement was closely related 
to mindfulness exercises. Among mindfulness exercises, the most helpful 
mindfulness technique was body scanning (71.43%). 
3. Discussion 
This study successfully assessed the feasibility and acceptability of an 
online mindfulness course for Chinese breast cancer survivors. The re-
sults demonstrated that MBIs could improve the level of mindfulness, 
emotional function and cognitive function of breast cancer survivors, 
reduce the level of FCR, and maintain the positive effects 1 month after 
the end of the intervention. 
A few studies of MBIs in women with breast cancer have previously 
been conducted. A study on 53 cancer patients who received a 7-week, 
1.5-h group mindfulness course reported that compared to the waiting 
group, the intervention group had fewer negative emotions, such as fear, 
anxiety, anger and depression [23]. Similarly, another study on 82 
breast cancer survivors found that compared with the control group, 
breast cancer survivors who participated in 6 sessions of MBSR training 
experienced a significant reduction in FCR and had improved QoL [24]. 
However, the effects of mindfulness training reached inconsistent con-
clusions and found no significant difference between the MBSR group 
and the control group in alleviating the FCR among breast cancer pa-
tients [15,25]. Such inconsistent results may be related to different 
intervention plans, assessment of outcome and sample sizes. Therefore, 
more convincing experiments need to be designed to further analyze the 
effect of mindfulness interventions on breast cancer survivors. 
Our results indicated that this mindfulness intervention improved 
emotional and cognitive function in breast cancer survivors but had 
little effect on other functions of QoL. Mindfulness is an uncritical 
awareness to present moment experiences, including thoughts, feelings, 
and physical sensations, with openness, curiosity, and acceptance [26]. 
As a psychological training of stress management widely used around 
the world, MBIs are a set of trainings with international standards that 
also have some flexibility in their implementation process [27]. This 
type of mind-body intervention could gradually cultivate mindfulness 
through formal meditation and informal practice [28]. Breast cancer 
survivors could observe their own internal experience from the 
perspective of an observer, master how to accept themselves, and create 
a real physical and psychological connection [10]. Therefore, MBIs have 
a more direct effect on emotion and cognitive function than other as-
pects of QoL for breast cancer survivors. 
The strengths of our study include its prospective design and 1- 
month duration of follow-up. This 6-week online mindfulness training 
for breast cancer survivors had lasting and positive effects on their FCR 
and emotional and cognitive function, and through the qualitative 
study, most of the participants reported that they could benefit from this 
mindfulness training. Although it has been argued that online MBIs are a 
promising strategy to alleviate psychological symptomatology and 
reduce the prevalence of severe mental health problems, some previous 
Fig. 2. Qualitative results related to the effects of the MBI.  
L. Peng et al.</paragraph></page><page number="6"><paragraph>Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice 49 (2022) 101686
6
studies have also proven the effectiveness of online mindfulness training 
combined with self-help exercises through apps or other media [29,30]. 
It is worth noting that this study had an exceedingly low drop-out rate, 
which might be due to the user-friendly app, so the patients were more 
willing to attend this course and continue their practice. In this study, 
most patients thought this intervention was of great help in their daily 
life, with a practice frequency of at least three times a week, and the 
technique of mindful body scanning was the most helpful method. This 
may be because these methods are easy to learn, readily available and 
free from spatial constraints; they are of great convenience for cancer 
patients with physical inconveniences. Hence, the study provided an 
evidence-based intervention to alleviate FCR and improve QoL in Chi-
nese breast cancer survivors, which could greatly reduce overall health 
care costs due to the more appropriate use of follow-up care and other 
health services in this large population of breast cancer survivors. 
However, several limitations are recognized. First, this was a single- 
center study, and its sample size was relatively small, so the represen-
tativeness of our study might be insufficient. Second, this study failed to 
set up an offline MBI group to compare the efficacy of different inter-
vention methods. Last, the measurement methods of this study were self- 
report scales, and more objective indicators are needed to evaluate 
effectiveness in future studies. 
In conclusion, the current study highlights the challenges associated 
with conducting research in this area. This online MBI with low dose and 
low burden advantages was very suitable for Chinese breast cancer 
survivors. Such benefits could facilitate the transition to post treatment 
survival, which provides a potential effective psychological therapy for 
improving QoL and feasible policy recommendations for the ever- 
increasing numbers of breast cancer survivors. 
Author statement 
Li Peng: Acquisition, Analysis, Interpretation of data, Writing – 
original draft, Writing – review &amp; editing. Ying Yang and Xiaozhen Cao: 
Acquisition of data. Muyu Chen, Chen Xu, Yanli Chen and Rongqian Liu: 
Acquisition, Analysis, Interpretation of data. Min Li: Concept, design, 
and supervision. 
Appendix A. Supplementary data 
Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. 
org/10.1016/j.ctcp.2022.101686. 
References 
[1] X. Wang, C. Wang, J. Guan, B. Chen, L. Xu, C. Chen, Progress of breast cancer basic 
research in China, Int. J. Biol. Sci. 17 (8) (2021) 2069–2079. 
[2] P.A. Ganz, P.J. Goodwin, Breast cancer survivorship: where are we today? Adv. 
Exp. Med. Biol. 862 (2015) 1–8. 
[3] Y.Y. Lei, S.C. Ho, K.L. Cheung, V.A. Yeo, R. Lee, C. Kwok, A. Cheng, F.K.F. Mo, 
W. Yeo, Higher level of sports activities participation during five-year survival is 
associated with better quality of life among Chinese breast cancer survivors, 
Cancers (Basel) 13 (23) (2021) 6056. 
[4] S.M. Rosenberg, L.S. Dominici, S. Gelber, P.D. Poorvu, K.J. Ruddy, J.S. Wong, R. 
M. Tamimi, L. Schapira, S. Come, J.M. Peppercorn, V.F. Borges, A.H. Partridge, 
Association of breast cancer surgery with quality of life and psychosocial well- 
being in young breast cancer survivors, JAMA Surgery 155 (11) (2020) 1035–1042. 
[5] L. Sharpe, L. Curran, P. Butow, B. Thewes, Fear of cancer recurrence and death 
anxiety, Psycho Oncol. 27 (11) (2018) 2559–2565. 
[6] D.W.L. Ng, A. Kwong, D. Suen, M. Chan, A. Or, S.S. Ng, C.C. Foo, B.F.S. Fielding, W. 
W.T. Lam, Fear of cancer recurrence among Chinese cancer survivors: prevalence 
and associations with metacognition and neuroticism, Psycho Oncol. 28 (6) (2019) 
1243–1251. 
[7] M. Tuman, K.E. Roberts, G. Corner, C. Beard, C. Fadalla, T. Coats, E. Slivjak, 
E. Schofield, W.G. Lichtenthal, Interpretation bias in breast cancer survivors 
experiencing fear of cancer recurrence, Front. Psychol. 12 (2021), 682174. 
[8] P. Butow, L. Sharpe, B. Thewes, J. Turner, J. Gilchrist, J. Beith, Fear of cancer 
recurrence: a practical guide for clinicians, Oncology (Williston Park) 32 (1) (2018) 
32–38. 
[9] E.C. Soriano, R. Valera, E.C. Pasipanodya, A.K. Otto, S.D. Siegel, J.P. Laurenceau, 
Checking behavior, fear of recurrence, and daily triggers in breast cancer survivors, 
Ann. Behav. Med. 53 (3) (2019) 244–254. 
[10] H. Haller, M.M. Winkler, P. Klose, G. Dobos, S. Kümmel, H. Cramer, Mindfulness- 
based interventions for women with breast cancer: an updated systematic review 
and meta-analysis, Acta Oncologica 56 (12) (2017) 1665–1676. 
[11] T.X.M. Tran, S. Jung, E.G. Lee, H. Cho, N.Y. Kim, S. Shim, H.Y. Kim, D. Kang, 
J. Cho, E. Lee, Y. Chang, H. Cho, Fear of Cancer Recurrence and its Negative Impact 
on Health-Related Quality of Life in Long-Term Breast Cancer Survivors, vol. 9, 
Cancer Research and Treatment, 2021. 
[12] N.M. Tauber, M.S. O’Toole, A. Dinkel, J. Galica, G. Humphris, S. Lebel, C. Maheu, 
G. Ozakinci, J. Prins, L. Sharpe, A.B. Smith, B. Thewes, S. Simard, R. Zachariae, 
Effect of psychological intervention on fear of cancer recurrence: a systematic 
review and meta-analysis, J. Clin. Oncol. 37 (31) (2019) 2899–2915. 
[13] S. Cheli, L. Caligiani, F. Martella, P. De Bartolo, F. Mancini, L. Fioretto, Mindfulness 
and metacognition in facing with fear of recurrence: a proof-of-concept study with 
breast-cancer women, Psycho Oncol. 28 (3) (2019) 600–606. 
[14] L. Witek Janusek, D. Tell, H.L. Mathews, Mindfulness based stress reduction 
provides psychological benefit and restores immune function of women newly 
diagnosed with breast cancer: a randomized trial with active control, Brain Behav. 
Immun. 80 (2019) 358–373. 
[15] C.A. Lengacher, V. Johnson-Mallard, J. Post-White, M.S. Moscoso, P.B. Jacobsen, 
T.W. Klein, R.H. Widen, S.G. Fitzgerald, M.M. Shelton, M. Barta, M. Goodman, C. 
E. Cox, K.E. Kip, Randomized controlled trial of mindfulness-based stress reduction 
(MBSR) for survivors of breast cancer, Psycho Oncol. 18 (12) (2009) 1261–1272. 
[16] A. Barak, L. Hen, M. Boniel-Nissim, N. Shapira, A comprehensive review and a 
meta-analysis of the effectiveness of internet-based psychotherapeutic 
interventions, J. Technol. Hum. Serv. 26 (2008) 109–160. 
[17] J. Kabat-Zinn, Full Catastrophe Living: Using the Wisdom of Your Body and Mind 
to Face Stress, Pain, and Illness, Revised Edition, U.S.A: Bantam, 2013. 
[18] J. Pedro, S. Monteiro-Reis, C. Carvalho-Maia, R. Henrique, C. Jer´onimo, E.R. Silva, 
Evidence of psychological and biological effects of structured Mindfulness-Based 
Interventions for cancer patients and survivors: a meta-review, Psycho Oncol. 30 
(11) (2021) 1836–1848. 
[19] A.B. Smith, D. Costa, J. Galica, S. Lebel, N. Tauber, S.J. van Helmondt, 
R. Zachariae, Spotlight on the fear of cancer recurrence inventory (FCRI), Psychol. 
Res. Behav. Manag. 13 (2020) 1257–1268. 
[20] J.E. Fardell, G. Jones, A.B. Smith, S. Lebel, B. Thewes, D. Costa, K. Tiller, S. Simard, 
A. Feldstain, S. Beattie, M. McCallum, , Conquer Fear authorship group, P. Butow, 
Exploring the screening capacity of the Fear of Cancer Recurrence Inventory-Short 
Form for clinical levels of fear of cancer recurrence, Psycho Oncol. 27 (2) (2018) 
492–499. 
[21] A. Shallcross, N.Y. Lu, R.D. Hays, Evaluation of the psychometric properties of the 
five Facet of mindfulness questionnaire. Journal of, Psychopathology and 
Behavioral Assessment 42 (2) (2020) 271–280. 
[22] N.K. Aaronson, S. Ahmedzai, B. Bergman, M. Bullinger, A. Cull, N.J. Duez, 
A. Filiberti, H. Flechtner, S.B. Fleishman, J.C. de Haes, S. Kaasa, M. Klee, D. Osoba, 
D. Razavi, P.B. Rofe, S. Schraub, K. Sneeuw, M. Sullivan, F. Takeda, The European 
Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QLQ-C30: a quality-of-life 
instrument for use in international clinical trials in oncology, J. Natl. Cancer Inst. 
85 (5) (1993) 365–376. 
[23] M. Speca, L. Carlson, E. Goodey, M.A. Angen, A randomized, wait-list controlled 
clinical trial: the effect of a mindfulness meditation-based stress reduction program 
on mood and symptoms of stress in cancer outpatients, Psychosom. Med. 62 (5) 
(2000) 613–622. 
[24] C.A. Lengacher, R.R. Reich, K.E. Kip, M. Barta, S. Ramesar, C.L. Paterson, M. 
S. Moscoso, I. Carranza, P.H. Budhrani, S.J. Kim, Influence of mindfulness-based 
stress reduction (MBSR) on telomerase activity in women with breast cancer (BC), 
Biol. Res. Nurs. 16 (4) (2014) 438–447. 
[25] C.A. Lengacher, R.R. Reich, C.L. Paterson, S. Ramesar, J.Y. Park, C. Alinat, 
V. Johnson-Mallard, M. Moscoso, P. Budhrani-Shani, B. Miladinovic, P.B. Jacobsen, 
C.E. Cox, M. Goodman, K.E. Kip, Examination of broad symptom improvement 
resulting from mindfulness-based stress reduction in breast cancer survivors: a 
randomized controlled trial, J. Clin. Oncol. 34 (24) (2016) 2827–2834. 
[26] Y. Matchim, J.M. Armer, B.R. Stewart, Mindfulness-based stress reduction among 
breast cancer survivors: a literature review and discussion, Oncol. Nurs. Forum 38 
(2) (2011) E61–E71. 
[27] L. Cillessen, M. Johannsen, A.E.M. Speckens, R. Zachariae, Mindfulness-based 
interventions for psychological and physical health outcomes in cancer patients 
and survivors: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled 
trials, Psycho Oncol. 28 (12) (2019) 2257–2269. 
[28] J.E. Bower, A.D. Crosswell, A.L. Stanton, C.M. Crespi, D. Winston, J. Arevalo, 
J. Ma, S.W. Cole, P.A. Ganz, Mindfulness meditation for younger breast cancer 
survivors: a randomized controlled trial, Cancer 121 (8) (2015) 1231–1240. 
[29] K.A. Zernicke, T.S. Campbell, M. Speca, K. McCabe-Ruff, S. Flowers, L.E. Carlson, 
A randomized wait-list controlled trial of feasibility and efficacy of an online 
mindfulness-based cancer recovery program: the e-Therapy for cancer applying 
mindfulness trial, Psychosom. Med. 76 (4) (2014) 257–267. 
[30] C.A. Lengacher, K.E. Kip, R.R. Reich, B.M. Craig, M. Mogos, S. Ramesar, C. 
L. Paterson, J.R. Farias, E. Pracht, A cost-effective mindfulness stress reduction 
program: a randomized control trial for breast cancer survivors, Nurs. Econ. 33 (4) 
(2015) 210–218, 232. 
L. Peng et al.</paragraph></page></document>